<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "file:///usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="airbus-nonnormal">
  <title>Airbus Non-Normal Notes</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Miscellaneous</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine failure after V1</title>

        <para>Apply rudder conventionally on the runway. When airborne, adjust rudder to maintain &beta;
        target. Autopilot can be engaged once gear is up. Consider the use of TOGA if a FLX takeoff was carried
        out. Initiate ECAM actions at 400ft AGL. Delay acceleration past acceleration altitude if the engine is not yet
        secure (e.g. master switch turned off or the first fire bottle discharged). To accelerate, push V/S to level
        off. Managed target speed will jump to initial climb speed. Accelerate to either S speed if an immediate visual
        return is expected or green dot speed if transiting, then set MCT (will require selecting CL then MCT for FLX
        takeoff) and continue climb in OP CLIMB.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Immediate VMC recovery with single engine</title>
        <para>Fly circuit in CONF 1. Select CONF 2 at start of base turn. Gear will usually be extended once flaps have
        run to 2, but may be delayed until final approach if performance is an issue. Select CONF 3 once gear is down
        and CONF full when on final approach. {TODO: Check how climb gradient/ flap decision is determined.}</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine failure in cruise</title>
        <para>Set MCT on live engine then disconnect the autothrust. Start ECAM actions and notify ATC. Decide on
        strategy - standard strategy increases the chance of an engine relight, whilst obstacle strategy maintains the
        greatest possible obstacle clearance. If using standard strategy select speed .78/300kt. If using obstacle
        strategy select green dot speed. Select altitude to LRC ceiling or green dot ceiling as appropriate to allow
        drift down once speed is reached. If obstacles remain a problem, MCT and green dot speed can be maintained to
        give a shallow climbing profile. Once obstacles are no longer a problem, descend to LRC ceiling (use V/S if
        &lt;500 fpm descent rate), engage the autothrust and continue at LRC speed.
        </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Single engine circling</title>
        <para>It may not be possible to fly level in the standard circling configuration of CONF 3 gear down. This can
        be ascertained by checking the table in Vol 3. Gear extension may be delayed until final approach if
        required.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Emergency descent</title>
        <para>Don oxygen masks, set them to the N position and establish communication. Descent with autopilot engaged
        is preferred. The configuration is thrust idle, full speed brake and maximum appropriate speed, taking into
        account possible structural damage. Target altitude is FL100 or MORA if this is higher. If speed is low, allow
        speed to increase before deploying full speedbrake to prevent activation of the angle of attack
        protection. Landing gear may be used below 25,000ft, but speed must be below V<subscript>LE</subscript> when it
        is extended and remain below V<subscript>LO</subscript>.</para>

        <para>Once descent is established, check the cabin altitude and manually deploy passenger oxygen if it is
        &gt;14,000ft. The passenger signs should be turned on, the ignitors should be turned on and ATC should be
        notified.</para>
        
        <para>Once level, restore the aircraft to a Normal configuration. When safe to do so, advise cabin crew and
        passengers that it is safe to remove their masks.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Smoke</title>
        <para>Smoke procedures are detailed on p1.08 of the QRH. Smoke removal procedures are detailed on p1.07 of the
        QRH. </para>
        <para>Immediate actions are to don oxygen masks and establish communication, then isolate the more likely
        sources by turning off the cabin fans, putting the avionics ventilation system into smoke removal configuration
        (OVRD on both BLOWER and EXTRACT) and shedding the galley and cabin electrics. The cabin signs should then be
        turned on. The origin of the smoke should be identified, possibly requiring communication with the cabin, and if
        successful, the faulty equipment should be isolated.</para>
        <para>If smoke becomes excessively dense at any time during the procedure, turn on the emergency exit lights and
        apply the smoke removal procedure. Also consider adopting the emergency electrical configuration.</para>
        <para>The eventual aim of the smoke removal procedure is depressurisation and the use of ram air. During the
        descent, the outflow valve is opened by setting the landing elevation to 10,000ft. If the packs are suspected as
        a smoke source (indicated by fuel vapors), they are turned off and the cabin fans are turned off. Otherwise, the
        air conditioning is used to provide air flow during the descent phase by setting the pack flow to HIGH and
        turning off the cabin fans. As a final resort, once below 200kt and depressurised, the cockpit windows can be
        opened.</para>
        
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Bomb on board</title>
        <para>The primary aim is to get the aircraft on the ground and evacuated ASAP.</para>

        <para>The secondary aim is to prevent detonation of the device. This is acheived by preventing further increases
        in cabin altitude through the use of manual pressure control and by avoiding sharp maneuvres and
        turbulence.</para>

        <para>The tertiary aim is to minimise the effect of any explosion, This is acheived by reducing the diff to 1
        psi, by descending to a level 2500ft above cabin altitude, and by flying at suitable speeds. As further descent
        is required, the manual controls should be used to maintain the 1 psi diff for as long as possible. The aircraft
        should be configured for landing as early as possible to avoid an explosion damaging landing systems.</para>

        <para>In the cabin, procedures are laid down for assessing the risks of moving the device and for moving the
        device to the LRBL at door 2R.</para> 

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Windshear</title>
        <sect3>
          <title>Reactive</title>
          <para>Indicated by a red "WINDSHEAR" flag on the PFD and a "WINDSHEAR, WINDSHEAR, WINDSHEAR" aural
          warning.</para>
          <para>Below V1, reject the TO if significant airspeed variations occur and there is sufficient runway to
          stop.</para>
          <para>If on the ground and above V1 , apply TOGA power, rotate at V<subscript>r</subscript> and follow SRS
          orders. SRS will maintain a minimum rate of climb, even if airspeed must be sacrificed.</para>

          <para>When airborne, maintain current configuration and apply TOGA power. The autopilot can fly the escape
          maneuvre as long as &alpha;<subscript>req</subscript>&lt;&alpha;<subscript>prot</subscript>. If the autopilot
          is not engaged, follow the SRS orders on the FD. If the FD is not available, initially pitch up to 17.5°, then
          increase as required.</para>

        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Predictive</title>
          <para>When below 2300ft AGL, the weather radar scans a 5nm radius 60° arc ahead of the aircraft for returns
          indicating potential windshear.</para>

          <para>Alerts are categorised as advisory, caution or warning, in increasing order of severity. Severity is
          determined by range, position and phase of flight. They are inhibited in flight when below 50ft or above
          1500ft, and inhibited on the ground when above 100kt.</para>

          <para>All types of alert produce an indication of windshear position on the ND, providing the ND range is set
          to 10nm. A message on the ND instructs the crew to change range to 10nm if not already set. Cautions also give
          an amber "W/S AHEAD" message on both PFDs and an aural "MONITOR RADAR DISPLAY" warning. Warnings give a red
          "W/S AHEAD" message on the PFDs and either a "WINDSHEAR AHEAD, WINDSHEAR AHEAD" or "GO AROUND, WINDSHEAR
          AHEAD" aural message.</para>

          <para>If a warning alert occurs duting the takeoff roll, reject the takeoff. If it occurs during initial
          climb, apply TOGA thrust and follow SRS orders. Configuration may be changed as long as the windshear is not
          entered.</para>

          <para>If a warning alert occurs during approach, carry out a normal go-around. If positive verification is
          made that no hazard exists, the crew may downgrade the warning to a caution. If a caution alert occurs during
          approach, consider use of CONF 3 and increasing V<subscript>APP</subscript> to a maximum of
          V<subscript>LS</subscript>+10.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Overweight landing</title>
        <para>A landing can be made at any weight, providing sufficient landing distance is available. The preferred
        landing configuration is CONF FULL, but lower settings may be used if required by QRH/ECAM procedures or if
        aircraft weight exceeds the CONF 3 go around limit (see QRH 2.25). Packs should be turned off to provide
        additional go around thrust. If configuration is less than FULL, use 1+F for go-around.</para>
        <para>It is possible that S speed will be higher than V<subscript>FE next</subscript> for CONF 2. In this case,
        a speed below V<subscript>FE next</subscript> should be selected until CONF 2 is acheived, then managed speed
        can be re-engaged.</para>
        <para>In the final stages of the approach, reduce speed to acheive V<subscript>LS</subscript> at runway
        threshold. Land as smoothly as possible, and apply max reverse as soon as the main gear touches down. Use brakes
        as necessary and monitor brake temperatures carefully after landing. If temperatures exceed 800°C, tyre
        deflation may occur.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Stall recovery</title>
        <para>As soon as a stall warning occurs, apply TOGA power while simultaneously reducing pitch attitude and
        rolling wings level. Ensure the speedbrake is retracted. If there is a danger of ground contact, maintain a
        pitch attitude that results in a gradual increase in speed to V<subscript>sw</subscript> (i.e. top of barber's
        pole), then maintain V<subscript>sw</subscript>. Note that V<subscript>sw</subscript> is g sensitive.</para>
        <para>If below 20,000ft and CONF 0, select FLAP 1. If the gear is down, retract it once there is no danger of
        ground contact.</para>
        <para>A stall warning may occur at high altitude to indicate that the aircraft is reaching
        &alpha;<subscript>buffet</subscript>. In this case simply reduce the back pressure on the sidestick and/or
        reduce bank angle.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Rejected Takeoff</title>

        <para>Call "Stop" while simultaneously bringing the thrust levers to idle, then to max reverse. Monitor
        automatic braking, and if there is any doubt, apply maximum manual braking. If normal braking fails, activate
        alternate braking by turning the A/SKID &amp; N/W STRG switch off, then modulate brake pressure at 1000psi. The
        F/O meanwhile monitors braking, confirms reverse, cancels any warnings, informs ATC and locates the evac
        checklist.</para>
        <para>If the reason for the stop was an engine fire on the upwind side, consider turning the aircraft into wind
        to keep the fire away from the fuselage.</para>
        <para>If there is any chance of requiring evacuation, bring the aircraft to a complete halt, apply the parking
        brake, and order "Attention, crew at stations". ECAM actions should then be carried out and the requirement for
        evacuation assessed. Otherwise order "Cabin crew, normal operations".</para>
        <para>If the aircraft has come to a complete halt using autobrake MAX, the brakes can be released by disarming
        the spoilers.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Evacuation</title>
        <para>Evacuation should be done in accordance with the emergency evacuation checklist. The first two items
        confirm the RTO actions of stopping the aircraft, setting the parking brake and alerting the cabin crew. The
        next action is to alert ATC.</para>
        <para>The next four items prepare the aircraft for evacuation. Check cabin diff is zero, and if necessary open
        the outflow valve manually. Shut the engines down, and press all the fire buttons, including the APU. If there
        are positive signs of fire, deploy the remaining extinguishers as required.</para>
        <para>Finally, order the evacuation. This is primarily done with the PA "Evacuate, unfasten your seat belts and
        get out", with the evacuation alarm being triggered as a backup.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Electrical</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Generator fault</title>
        <para>Try to reset the generator by turning it off, then after a short pause, turning it on again. If
        unsuccessful, turn it back off.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>AC Bus 1 fault</title>
        <para>All equipment on AC bus 1 becomes unavailable, including TR1. DC Bus 2 is powered from DC Bus 1 via the
        battery bus, the Essential AC bus is powered by AC bus 2 and the Essential TR powers the DC Essential
        bus.</para>
        <para>Notable lost equipment includes the blue hydraulic system and associated services (including spoiler 3),
        radio altimeter 1 (and hence Cat III capability), half the fuel pumps, the nose wheel steering, the avionics
        blower fan and p1 windshield heat. Landing distance will increase by 10%.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>IDG low pressure or overheat</title>
        <para>The affected IDG must be disconnected. This is done by pressing the guarded IDG button until the FAULT
        light comes on on the associated generator button. The button should be held down for a maximum of three
        seconds. The unaffected generator will power the associated AC bus, with the galley being shed.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Emergency configuration</title>
        <para>Attempt to restore normal power by recycling the main generators. If that fails, try again after splitting
        the systems. Start the APU once at least 45 seconds has elapsed since loss of main generators.</para>
        <para>If normal power cannot be restored, ensure that the emergency generator is on line, deploying the RAT
        manually if required and maintain speed &gt;140kt to avoid RAT stall. So much equipment is lost in the emergency
        configuration that a table is provided in the QRH for surviving equipment. Notable losses are all the fuel pumps
        (so ignition on, avoid negative G, centre tank fuel is unusable), the anti-skid and three fifths of the
        spoilers. Landing speeds and distances are increased.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Flight controls</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Landing with slats or flaps jammed</title>
        <para>The selected landing configuration should be CONF 3. If the slats are jammed, the flaps will still move
        and vice versa. Therefore V<subscript>FE</subscript> (barbers pole with CONF&gt;0) and V<subscript>FE
        next</subscript>, which are a function of flap lever position, must be honored during
        configuration. V<subscript>LS</subscript> is computed according to actual configuration. It is possible that
        V<subscript>LS</subscript>&gt;V<subscript>FE next</subscript>. If this occurs, speed should be reduced below
        V<subscript>LS</subscript> as the surfaces extend. This will require temporary disconnection of the
        autothrust. Use of managed speed is not recommended during configuration.</para>
        <para>The autopilot may be used down to 500ft AAL, but since it is not tuned for the abnormal configuration it
        must be closely monitored.</para>
        <para>For the go-around, initially maintain flap/ slat configuration. Maximum speeds are available on page 2.05
        of the QRH, and in general a speed 10kt lower than max speed should be flown. If it is the slats that are jammed
        or if the flaps are jammed at 0, clean configuration can be used to transit to a diversion airfield.</para>
        <para>Diversion with flaps and/or slats extended may as much as double fuel consumption. The centre tank pumps
        will have to be manually controlled to access the fuel if slats are extended.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Slats and Flaps fault in CONF 0</title>
        <para>If the fault cannot be cleared by recycling the flap lever, a flaps and slats up landing must be made. The
        V<subscript>REF</subscript> increment is 60kt for the approach, but speed is reduced at 500ft to be at
        V<subscript>REF</subscript>+50kt by the the threshold. Landing distances will increase by a factor of
        1.8. Landing speed is very close to tyre limiting speed.</para>
        <para>The flap lever is set to 1 for the approach to enable AP/FD go-arounds. The centre tank pumps must be
        turned off manually since their automatic mode is triggered by slat extension. Depending on the reason for the
        failure, flight controls may revert to Alternate Law.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Fire</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine fire</title>
        <para>The basic sequence is to bring the thrust lever of the affected engine to idle, turn off its engine
        master, push its fire button, wait 10 seconds then deploy its first fire bottle. If the fire is not extinguished
        after 30 seconds, indicated by the fire button remaining lit, deploy the second bottle. This sequence is
        modified on the ground in that both fire bottles are fired immediately, and the remaining engine is then also
        shut down.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Landing gear</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Gear not downlocked</title>
        <para>If the gear has not downlocked, retract the gear and wait until it has fully stowed, then redeploy. If
        this is not successful, attempt to deploy the gear by gravity using page 2.11 of the QRH .</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Power plant</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Dual engine failure</title>
        <para>It is recommended that the QRH paper procedure on page 1.16 is used rather than the ECAM.</para>
        <para>First priority, assuming fuel remains, is to attempt a relight by turning the ignitors on and setting the
        thrust levers to idle. The speed should initially be increased to 300kt to increase windmilling and improve the
        chance of a relight. At this speed, the aircraft will cover approximately 2nm for every 1000ft lost. With this
        in mind, a suitable plan should be constructed to cover the possibility that relight is not possible.</para>
        <para>Whilst awaiting a relight, ensure that the emergency electrical generator is on line and recycle FAC1 to
        recover characteristic speed display and rudder trim. For communications, VHF1 and ATC1 are available in the
        emergency electrical config. Due to lack of engine bleeds, a slow depressurisation will be occuring, so be ready
        to don oxygen masks.</para>
        <para>If there has been no relight after 30 seconds, the combustion chambers should be ventilated by turning
        both engine masters off for 30 seconds. Another attempt can then be made by turning them back on. This sequence
        should be repeated until successful or until APU bleed air becomes available at FL200.</para>
        <para>Once below FL250, the APU can be started. Once below FL200, speed should be reduced to green dot and
        assisted starts should be attempted. At green dot speed, 2½nm will be covered for every 1000ft lost. Attempt to
        start one engine at a time in the normal manner.</para>
        <para>If a landing must be made without power, CONF 3 slats are recommended (flaps are
        unavailable). V<subscript>app</subscript> should be V<subscript>ref</subscript>+25kt or 150kt, whichever is
        higher. The gear is available with gravity extension. The stabilizer will be frozen once engine driven
        hydraulics are lost and elevator trimming will cease with transition to direct law at gear extension. Therefore,
        gear extension should be delayed until CONF 3 and V<subscript>app</subscript> are reached. If ditching, do not
        extend the gear.</para>
        <para>If an airfield can be reached, cross the outer marker at twice the normal height with CONF 1, gear up. For
        a clean aircraft, the following rules of thumb apply {TODO: these are Boeing rules - check that they hold for
        Airbus}:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A standard hold loses 8000ft</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>An orbit loses 4000ft</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>400ft is lost per nm</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        CONF 3, gear down will give a glide ratio of 800ft per nm.
        </para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Navigation</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>ADR faults</title>
        <para>A single ADR fault simply requires switching to the hot spare and turning the affected unit off. Loss of
        ADR1 will lead to the loss of the extended functions of the EGPWS. Loss of ADR2 will lead to both baro reference
        channels being driven by the same FCU channel {TODO: Find out details of this}, so the baro refs should be
        checked.</para>

        <para>Loss of two ADRs will lead to Alternate Law with associated speed restrictions and landing configuration
        considerations. Air data switching is used as necessary, and the affected ADRs are turned off. ATC switching may
        be required to restore transponder. If ADR 1 and 3 are lost, the landing gear safety valve is controlled closed,
        so the gear must be gravity extended and cannot subsequently be retracted.</para>

        <para>Loss of all ADRs requires reversion to standby instruments. There is no ECAM procedure - the procedure
        displayed is for single ADR operation. Therefore, refer to page 2.20 of the QRH. In addition to the failures
        associated with dual loss, the stall warning is lost, the rudder travel limiter is frozen (full rudder travel
        will be recovered at slat extension) and automatic cabin pressure control is lost.</para> 
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>RA faults</title>
        <para>A single RA fault results in degradation of approach capability to Cat II. Loss of both RAs will lead to
        direct law at landing gear extension and a loss of ILS APPR mode capability. Therefore, landing will be CONF 3
        with associated corrections, the approach should be flown in LOC and FPA and autopilot disconnect should be
        anticipated at gear extension.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>IR faults</title>
        <para>A single IR fault will simply require ATT/HDG switching. This may lead to loss of the extended functions
        of the EPGWS and/or loss of TCAS. It may be possible to recover the IR in ATT mode using the procedure on page
        2.21 of the QRH.</para>

        <para>A dual IR fault will lead to loss of PFD indications on at least one side so use ATT/HDG switching to
        recover. It will also lead to Alternate Law and associated speed restrictions and landing configuration
        considerations.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Auto-flight</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>FCU faults</title>
        <para>Loss of a single channel will result in the spare channel automatically taking over. All that is required
        is a cross check of the baro refs.</para>
        <para>Loss of both channels leads to loss of all FCU and EFIS panels. The autopilots and autothrust are
        lost and parameters that are normally controlled by the panels revert to sensible default values. If the weather
        radar image remains displayed, disregard it since the scale will be incorrect.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Hydraulics</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Low Reservoir Air Pressure</title>
        <para>Loss of air pressure to a hydraulic reservoir may lead to pump cavitation and hence fluctuating
        pressures. If this occurs, turn off the affected pump, and if applicable, turn off the PTU. Cavitation reduces
        with altitude, so it may be possible to reinstate the system during the descent.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Overheat</title>
        <para>Turn off all affected pumps and if applicable, turn off the PTU. The system should be reinstated for the
        approach if it has cooled sufficiently.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Loss of GREEN system</title>
        <para>The major lost systems are normal landing gear operation (gravity extension is available), nose wheel
        steering and normal brake system (including autobrake). Landing distance will be increased due to loss of two
        spoilers per wing and reverser 1. Flap and slat deployment will be slow.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Loss of YELLOW system</title>
        <para>Two spoilers per wing and reverser 2 are lost, so landing distance will increase slightly. Flap deployment
        will be slow. As the alternate braking system is only available through the brake accumulator, ensure there is
        sufficient pressure when the parking brake is set.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Loss of BLUE system</title>
        <para>One spoiler per wing will be lost but this has negligible effect on landing distance. Slats will be slow to
        deploy. Deployment of the RAT is not recommended unless another system is lost.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Loss of GREEN + BLUE </title>
        <para>If BLUE has been lost due to the loss of its electrical pump, it may be recovered by deploying the
        RAT.</para>
        <para>The systems lost include the union of losses for the single hydraulic system losses described above. In
        addition, the slats are jammed and the ailerons and left elevator are lost. This leads to Alternate Law and
        hence loss of autopilots. Whilst the autothrust is available, it should be disconnected early in the approach as
        it is not able to cope with the quantity of failed systems. The speed brake should not be used since the
        differential spoilers are required for roll control. Due to the single elevator and lost ailerons, expect
        slightly sluggish response in the flare.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Loss of GREEN + YELLOW</title>
        <para>It may be possible to recover the YELLOW system using the YELLOW electrical pump.</para>
        <para>The systems lost include the union of losses for the single hydraulic system losses described above. In
        addition, the flaps are jammed, the reversers are lost, the yaw damper is lost, the stabiliser is frozen, and
        the braking is by accumulator only (anti-skid lost). This is the worst case scenario for landing distance. The
        lost systems lead to reversion to Alternate Law. With the stabiliser frozen, the transition to Direct Law at
        gear extension should be delayed until CONF 3 and V<subscript>app</subscript> are achieved to allow the
        elevators to be trimmed correctly for the approach.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Loss of BLUE + YELLOW</title>
        <para>It may be possible to recover the YELLOW system using the YELLOW electrical pump or the BLUE system using
        the RAT.</para>
        <para>This is the least significant dual hydraulic loss. The systems lost include the union of losses for the
        single hydraulic system losses described above. In addition the right elevator is lost and, due to losing
        spoilers 2+3+4, the speed brake is unusable. Flight controls revert to Alternate Law so the autopilots are
        lost.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
</article>

