<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "file:///usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="airbus-nonnormal">
  <title>Airbus Non-Normal Notes</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>Operating techniques</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Rejected Takeoff</title>
      <para>[EOM B.3.2.10, FCOM 3.2.10.1000]</para>

      <para>The decision to reject rests solely with CM1. This decision is communicated with the words "Stop" or
      "Continue". "Stop" implies that CM1 is taking control of the aircraft. Below 100kt the RTO is relatively risk free
      and a decision to stop should be made for any ECAM and most other problems. Above 100kt the RTO may be hazardous
      and stopping should only be considered for loss of engine thrust, any fire warning, any uninhibited ECAM or
      anything which indicates the aircraft will be unsafe or unable to fly.</para>
      
      <para>If a stop is required, CM1 calls "Stop" while simultaneously bringing the thrust levers to idle, then to max
      reverse. If the stop was commenced below 72kt the ground spoilers will not automatically deploy and the autobrake
      will therefore not engage. Monitor automatic braking, and if there is any doubt, apply manual braking as
      required. If normal braking fails, announce "Loss of braking" and proceed with the loss of braking memory items
      (see <xref linkend="loss-of-braking"/>). If the reason for the stop was an engine fire on the upwind side,
      consider turning the aircraft to keep the fire away from the fuselage. If there is any chance of requiring
      evacuation, bring the aircraft to a complete halt, stow the reversers, apply the parking brake, and order
      "Attention, crew at stations" on the PA. If evacuation will definitely not be required, once the aircraft's safety
      is assured, the RTO can be discontinued and the runway cleared. In this case make a PA of "Cabin crew, normal
      operations".</para>

      <para>During this initial phase, CM2 confirms reverse ("Reverse green"), confirms deceleration ("Decel"), cancels
      any audio warnings, informs ATC and announces "70 knots" when appropriate. Once the aircraft comes to a halt, CM2
      locates the emergency evacuation checklist.</para>

      <para>Once the aircraft has stopped, CM1 takes the radios and asks CM2 to carry out any required ECAM
      actions. Whilst the ECAM actions are being completed, CM1 will build up a decision as to whether to evacuate. If
      an evacuation is required see <xref linkend="evacuation"/>. Otherwise order "Cabin crew, normal
      operations".</para>

      <para>If the aircraft has come to a complete halt using autobrake MAX, the brakes can be released by disarming the
      spoilers.</para>
      </sect2>
      
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Miscellaneous</title>
    <sect2>
      <title>Emergency descent <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>
      <para>[QRH 1.25, FCOM 3.2.80.4000, EOM B.3.2.80]</para>
      
      <para>Don oxygen masks, set them to the N position and establish communication.</para>
      
      <para>Descent with autopilot and autothrottle engaged is preferred. The configuration is thrust idle, full speed
      brake and maximum appropriate speed, taking into account possible structural damage. Target altitude is FL100 or
      MORA if this is higher. If speed is low, allow speed to increase before deploying full speedbrake to prevent
      activation of the angle of attack protection. Landing gear may be used below 25,000ft, but speed must be below
      V<subscript>LE</subscript> when it is extended and remain below V<subscript>LO</subscript>. If on an airway,
      consider turning 90° to the left.</para>

      <para>PNF should, from memory, turn seatbelt signs on, set continuous ignition on the engines, set 7700 on the
      transponder and inform ATC of the descent. If cabin altitude will exceed 14,000ft, he should also deploy the cabin
      oxygen masks.</para>

        <para>The rapid decompression PA is:
        <blockquote><para>"Ladies and Gentlemen, this is the Captain. We have lost cabin pressure and are descending to a lower
        altitude. Put your oxygen masks on and obey the instructions of the cabin crew"</para></blockquote></para>

        <para>Once level, restore the aircraft to a Normal configuration. When safe to do so, advise cabin crew and
        passengers that it is safe to remove their masks.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Windshear <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>
        <sect3>
          <title>Reactive</title>
          <para>[FCOM 3.2.80.13000]</para>

          <para>Indicated by a red "WINDSHEAR" flag on the PFD and a "WINDSHEAR, WINDSHEAR, WINDSHEAR" aural
          warning.</para>

          <para>Below V1, reject the TO if significant airspeed variations occur and there is sufficient runway to
          stop.</para>

          <para>If on the ground and above V1 , apply TOGA power, rotate at V<subscript>r</subscript> and follow SRS
          orders. SRS will maintain a minimum rate of climb, even if airspeed must be sacrificed.</para>

          <para>When airborne, maintain current configuration and apply TOGA power. The autopilot can fly the escape
          maneuvre as long as &alpha;<subscript>req</subscript>&lt;&alpha;<subscript>prot</subscript>. If the autopilot
          is not engaged, follow the SRS orders on the FD. If the FD is not available, initially pitch up to 17.5°, then
          increase as required.</para>

        </sect3>
        <sect3>
          <title>Predictive</title>
          <para>[FCOM 3.2.80.14000, FCOM 3.4.91]</para>

          <para>When below 2300ft AGL, the weather radar scans a 5nm radius 60° arc ahead of the aircraft for returns
          indicating potential windshear.</para>

          <para>Alerts are categorised as advisory, caution or warning, in increasing order of severity. Severity is
          determined by range, position and phase of flight. They are inhibited in flight when below 50ft or above
          1500ft, and inhibited on the ground when above 100kt.</para>

          <para>All types of alert produce an indication of windshear position on the ND, providing the ND range is set
          to 10nm. A message on the ND instructs the crew to change range to 10nm if not already set. Cautions also give
          an amber "W/S AHEAD" message on both PFDs and an aural "MONITOR RADAR DISPLAY" warning. Warnings give a red
          "W/S AHEAD" message on the PFDs and either a "WINDSHEAR AHEAD, WINDSHEAR AHEAD" or "GO AROUND, WINDSHEAR
          AHEAD" aural message.</para>

          <para>If a warning alert occurs duting the takeoff roll, reject the takeoff. If it occurs during initial
          climb, apply TOGA thrust and follow SRS orders. Configuration may be changed as long as the windshear is not
          entered.</para>

          <para>If a warning alert occurs during approach, carry out a normal go-around. If positive verification is
          made that no hazard exists, the crew may downgrade the warning to a caution. If a caution alert occurs during
          approach, consider use of CONF 3 and increasing V<subscript>APP</subscript> to a maximum of
          V<subscript>LS</subscript>+15.</para>
        </sect3>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Unreliable airspeed <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>

        <para>[QRH 2.15, FCOM 3.2.34.30000]</para>

        <para>Unreliable airspeed indications may result from radome damage and/or unserviceable probes or
        ports. Altitude indications may also be erroneous if static probes are affected.</para>

        <para>The FMGCs normally reject erroneous ADR data by isolating a single source that has significant differences
        to the other two sources. It is possible that a single remaining good source may be rejected if the other two
        sources are erroneous in a sufficiently similar way. In this case, it falls to the pilots to identify and turn
        off the erroneous sources to recover good data.</para>

        <para>The first problem is recognition of a failure, since the aircraft systems may be unable to warn of a
        problem. The primary method of doing this is correlation of aircraft attitude and thrust to displayed
        performance. Correlation of radio altimeter and GPIRS derived data (available on GPS MONITOR page) may also aid
        identification. The stall warning (available in alternate or direct law) is based on alpha probes, so will
        likely be valid. Other clues may include fluctuations in readings, abnormal behavior of the automatics, high
        speed buffet or low aerodynamic noise.</para>

        <para>If the aircraft flight path is in doubt, disconnect the automatics and fly the following short term
        attitude and thrust settings to initiate a climb:

        <informaltable>
          <tgroup cols="3">
            <colspec align="left" colwidth="2.25in"/><colspec align="center" colwidth="1in"/><colspec align="center" colwidth="1in"/>
            <thead>
              <row><entry align="center">Condition</entry><entry>Thrust</entry><entry>Pitch</entry></row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row><entry>Below Thrust Reduction Altitude</entry><entry>TOGA</entry><entry>15°</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Below FL100</entry><entry>Climb</entry><entry>10°</entry></row>
              <row><entry>Above FL100</entry><entry>Climb</entry><entry>5°</entry></row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </informaltable>

        Flap configuration should be maintained except when a go-around is initiated with flap full, in which case CONF
        3 should be selected. The gear and speedbrake should be retracted. If there is any doubt over the validity of
        altitude information, the FPV must be disregarded. If altitude information is definitely good, the FPV may be
        used.</para>

        <para>Once the flight path is under control and a safe altitude is attained, refer to the table on page 2.15 of
        the QRH to extract a pitch and thrust combination for your weight and configuration. Speed should be adjusted
        until the aircraft flies level with these parameters set. Level flight can be established using the VSI, which
        is an inertial instrument unless there is there is an amber box around the numerical indication on the V/S scale
        {TODO: Confirm this - QRH indicates that VSI should not be used if altitude is in doubt}. Once stabilised, an
        attempt should be made to recover good data by switching off faulty ADRs.</para>

        <para>If good ADR information cannot be recovered, tables are provided on page 2.17 and 2.18 of the QRH to
        enable all phases of flight to be flown using just pitch and thrust settings. The approach configuration should
        be flown in level flight, stabilising each configuration before the next configuration is selected.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="ditching">
        <title>Ditching</title>
        <para>[QRH 1.23, QRH 1.16, QRH 1.20 FCOM 3.2.80]</para>
        
        <para>The QRH 1.23 procedure applies if the engines are running. If the engines are not running, refer to QRH
        1.16 or QRH 1.20 which include ditching.</para>

        <para>Preparation for ditching involves notifying ATC in order to expedite rescue, preparing survival equipment
        and securing the aircraft for impact. The GPWS should be inhibited to prevent nuisance warnings. The crew oxygen
        should be turned off below FL100 to prevent potentially dangerous leaks {TODO: this is an assumption}.</para>

        <para>The engines operative ditching configuration is gear up, config full, 11° pitch and minimal V/S. If both
        engines are inoperative, use config 3 (only slats available) and maintain at least 150kt. In strong winds, land
        into wind. In lighter winds, land parallel to swell. The bleeds are all turned off and ditching button pushed
        (ensure pressurisation is in auto for this to work) in order to close all openings below the waterline and
        reduce water ingress. At 2000ft, make a PA "Cabin crew, landing positions". At 500ft, make a PA "Brace,
        brace"</para>

        <para>At touchdown, turn the engine and APU masters off. After coming to a stop, notify ATC, push all fire
        buttons, discharge all agents (engine agent 2 may not be available) and evacuate the aircraft. {TODO: There is a
        discrepancy between engines operative/ inoperative regarding use of the fire buttons after stopping}</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="forced-landing">
        <title>Forced landing</title>
        <para>[QRH 1.24, QRH 1.16 &amp; 1.20, FCOM 3.2.80.3000]</para>

        <para>The QRH 1.24 procedure applies if the engines are running. If the engines are not running, refer to QRH
        1.16 or QRH 1.20 which include forced landing.</para>

        <para>Preparation for forced landing involves notifying ATC in order to expedite rescue, preparing survival equipment
        and securing the aircraft for impact. The GPWS should be inhibited to prevent nuisance warnings. The crew oxygen
        should be turned off below FL100 to prevent potentially dangerous leaks {TODO: this is an assumption}.</para>

        <para>The engines operative forced landing configuration is gear down, config full, spoilers armed. If the
        engines are inoperative, use config 3 (only slats available) and maintain at least 150kt. The ram air button is
        used to ensure that the aircraft will be completely depressurised at touchdown. At 2000ft, make a PA "Cabin
        crew, landing positions". At 500ft, make a PA "Brace, brace"</para>

        <para>At touchdown, turn the engine and APU masters off. This will leave accumulator baraking only. After coming
        to a stop, set the parking brake, notify ATC, push all fire buttons, discharge all agents (engine agent 2 may
        not be available) and evacuate the aircraft.{TODO: There is a discrepancy between engines operative/ inoperative
        regarding use of the fire buttons after stopping}</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine failure after V1</title>

        <para>Apply rudder conventionally on the runway. When airborne, adjust rudder to maintain &beta;
        target. Autopilot can be engaged once gear is up. Consider the use of TOGA if a FLX takeoff was carried
        out. Initiate ECAM actions at 400ft AGL. Delay acceleration past acceleration altitude if the engine is not yet
        secure (e.g. master switch turned off or the first fire bottle discharged). To accelerate, push V/S to level
        off. Managed target speed will jump to initial climb speed. Accelerate to either S speed if an immediate visual
        return is expected or green dot speed if transiting, then set MCT (will require selecting CL then MCT for FLX
        takeoff) and continue climb in OP CLIMB.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Immediate VMC recovery with single engine</title>
        <para>Fly circuit in CONF 1. Select CONF 2 at start of base turn. Gear will usually be extended once flaps have
        run to 2, but may be delayed until final approach if performance is an issue. Select CONF 3 once gear is down
        and CONF full when on final approach. {TODO: Check how climb gradient/ flap decision is determined.}</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine inoperative approach</title>
        <para>Landing configuration is flap full unless a level off is required during final approach. In this case
        CONF 3 should be used. Selection of full flaps should be delayed until final descent. It is not permissable to
        use the autopilot to perform single engine NPAs in FINAL APP, NAV V/S or NAV FPA modes. These modes may,
        however, be used with the FDs.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine failure in cruise</title>
        <para>Set MCT on live engine then disconnect the autothrust. Start ECAM actions and notify ATC. Decide on
        strategy - standard strategy increases the chance of an engine relight, whilst obstacle strategy maintains the
        greatest possible obstacle clearance. If using standard strategy select speed .78/300kt. If using obstacle
        strategy select green dot speed. Select altitude to LRC ceiling or green dot ceiling as appropriate to allow
        drift down once speed is reached. If obstacles remain a problem, MCT and green dot speed can be maintained to
        give a shallow climbing profile. Once obstacles are no longer a problem, descend to LRC ceiling (use V/S if
        &lt;500 fpm descent rate), engage the autothrust and continue at LRC speed.
        </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Single engine circling</title>
        <para>It may not be possible to fly level in the standard circling configuration of CONF 3 gear down. This can
        be ascertained by checking the table in Vol 3. Gear extension may be delayed until final approach if
        required.</para>
      </sect2>
<sect2>
        <title>Bomb on board</title>
        <para>The primary aim is to get the aircraft on the ground and evacuated ASAP.</para>

        <para>The secondary aim is to prevent detonation of the device. This is acheived by preventing further increases
        in cabin altitude through the use of manual pressure control and by avoiding sharp maneuvres and
        turbulence.</para>

        <para>The tertiary aim is to minimise the effect of any explosion, This is acheived by reducing the diff to 1
        psi, by descending to a level 2500ft above cabin altitude, and by flying at suitable speeds. As further descent
        is required, the manual controls should be used to maintain the 1 psi diff for as long as possible. The aircraft
        should be configured for landing as early as possible to avoid an explosion damaging landing systems.</para>

        <para>In the cabin, procedures are laid down for assessing the risks of moving the device and for moving the
        device to the LRBL at door 2R.</para> 

      </sect2>
<sect2>
        <title>Overweight landing</title>
        <para>A landing can be made at any weight, providing sufficient landing distance is available. The preferred
        landing configuration is CONF FULL, but lower settings may be used if required by QRH/ECAM procedures or if
        aircraft weight exceeds the CONF 3 go around limit (see QRH 2.25). Packs should be turned off to provide
        additional go around thrust. If configuration is less than FULL, use 1+F for go-around.</para>
        <para>It is possible that S speed will be higher than V<subscript>FE next</subscript> for CONF 2. In this case,
        a speed below V<subscript>FE next</subscript> should be selected until CONF 2 is acheived, then managed speed
        can be re-engaged.</para>
        <para>In the final stages of the approach, reduce speed to acheive V<subscript>LS</subscript> at runway
        threshold. Land as smoothly as possible, and apply max reverse as soon as the main gear touches down. Use brakes
        as necessary and monitor brake temperatures carefully after landing. If temperatures exceed 800°C, tyre
        deflation may occur.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Stall recovery</title>
        <para>As soon as a stall warning occurs, apply TOGA power while simultaneously reducing pitch attitude and
        rolling wings level. Ensure the speedbrake is retracted. If there is a danger of ground contact, maintain a
        pitch attitude that results in a gradual increase in speed to V<subscript>sw</subscript> (i.e. top of barber's
        pole), then maintain V<subscript>sw</subscript>. Note that V<subscript>sw</subscript> is g sensitive.</para>
        <para>If below 20,000ft and CONF 0, select FLAP 1. If the gear is down, retract it once there is no danger of
        ground contact.</para>
        <para>A stall warning may occur at high altitude to indicate that the aircraft is reaching
        &alpha;<subscript>buffet</subscript>. In this case simply reduce the back pressure on the sidestick and/or
        reduce bank angle.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="evacuation">
        <title>Evacuation</title>
        <para>Evacuation should be done in accordance with the emergency evacuation checklist. The first two items
        confirm the RTO actions of stopping the aircraft, setting the parking brake and alerting the cabin crew. The
        next action is to alert ATC.</para>
        <para>The next four items prepare the aircraft for evacuation. Check cabin diff is zero, and if necessary open
        the outflow valve manually. Shut the engines down, and press all the fire buttons, including the APU. If there
        are positive signs of fire, deploy the remaining extinguishers as required.</para>
        <para>Finally, order the evacuation. This is primarily done with the PA "Evacuate, unfasten your seat belts and
        get out", with the evacuation alarm being triggered as a backup.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Incapacitation</title>
        <para>Take control, using the stick priority button if necessary. Contact cabin crew ASAP. They should strap the
        incapacitated pilot to his seat, move the seat back, then recline the seat. If there are two members available,
        the body can be moved. Medical help should be sought from passengers, and the presence of any type rated company
        pilots on board ascertained.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Computer reset</title>
        <para>Abnormal computer behaviour can often be stopped by interupting the power supply of the affected
        computer. This can be done either with cockpit controls or with circuit breakers. The general procedure is to
        interupt the power supply, wait 3 seconds (5 seconds if a C/B was used), restore the power, then wait another
        three seconds for the reset to complete. Specific procedures are detailed in the computer reset tables on page
        2.36 of the QRH.</para>

        <para>On the ground, almost all computers can be reset. The exceptions are the ECU and EIU while the associated
        engine is running and the BDCU when the aircraft is not stopped.</para>

        <para>In flight, only the computers listed in the reset table should be considered for reset.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Air conditioning, pressurisation and ventilation</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Cabin overpressure</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.01, FCOM 3.2.21.27000]</para>

        <para>There is no ECAM in the case of total loss of pressure control leading to an overpressure, so apply the
        QRH procedure. The basic procedure is to reduce air inflow by turning off one of the packs and put the avionics
        ventilation system in its smoke removal configuration so that it dumps cabin air overboard. The ΔP is monitored,
        and the remaining pack is turned off if it exceeds 9 psi. 10 minutes before landing, both packs are turned off
        and remain off, and the avionics ventilation is returned to its normal configuration.</para>

      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Electrical</title>
      <sect2 id="emerg-elec-config">
        <title>Emergency configuration</title>
        <para>[QRH 1.01 &amp; 1.05, FCOM 1.24.20.5000, FCOM 3.2.24.17000, red ECAM: <emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> EMER CONFIG]</para>

        <para>Attempt to restore normal power by recycling the main generators. If that fails, try again after splitting
        the systems. Start the APU once at least 45 seconds has elapsed since loss of main generators.</para>
        <para>If normal power cannot be restored, ensure that the emergency generator is on line, deploying the RAT
        manually if required and maintain speed &gt;140kt to avoid RAT stall.</para>

        <para>So much equipment is lost in the emergency configuration that a table is provided in the QRH for surviving
        equipment. Notable losses are all the fuel pumps (so ignition on, avoid negative G, centre tank fuel is
        unusable), the anti-skid and three fifths of the spoilers. Landing speeds and distances are increased.</para>

        <para>A paper summary is provided on page 1.05 of the QRH, which should be applied once ECAM actions are complete.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Generator fault</title>
        <para>Try to reset the generator by turning it off, then after a short pause, turning it on again. If
        unsuccessful, turn it back off.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>AC Bus 1 fault</title>
        <para>All equipment on AC bus 1 becomes unavailable, including TR1. DC Bus 2 is powered from DC Bus 1 via the
        battery bus, the Essential AC bus is powered by AC bus 2 and the Essential TR powers the DC Essential
        bus.</para>
        <para>Notable lost equipment includes the blue hydraulic system and associated services (including spoiler 3),
        radio altimeter 1 (and hence Cat III capability), half the fuel pumps, the nose wheel steering, the avionics
        blower fan and p1 windshield heat. Landing distance will increase by 10%.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>IDG low pressure or overheat</title>
        <para>The affected IDG must be disconnected. This is done by pressing the guarded IDG button until the FAULT
        light comes on on the associated generator button. The button should be held down for a maximum of three
        seconds. The unaffected generator will power the associated AC bus, with the galley being shed.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Flight controls</title>
      <sect2 id="flight-controls.slats-flaps-fault">
        <title>Flaps and/or slats fault/locked</title>
        <para>If the flaps and/or slats cannot be retracted, max operating speed is reduced to the placard limit for the
        flap lever position required to attain the position of the most extended device. Bear in mind that CONF 2 and
        CONF 3 result in the same slat position. V<subscript>FE</subscript> is calculated directly from flap lever
        position, so the barber's pole will show accurate max operating speed when the flap lever is set to this
        position.</para>

        <para>The flap lever can be recycled if there is not an obvious reason not to (e.g. wing tip brake on or fault
        due to dual hydraulic failure).</para>

        <para>The flap lever will continue to move the slats if the flaps are locked and vice versa. In general, flap 3
        should be selected for landing. There are two exceptions. If flaps are locked at &gt;3, flap full should be
        used. If both slats and flaps are locked at 0, flap 1 should be used so that the AP/FD go-around is
        armed.</para>
        
        <para>Speeds and landing distance corrections are available on page 2.32 of the QRH. If a flapless and slatless
        landing is required, the approach speed correction is 60kt, reducing from 500ft aal to be at the threshold at
        V<subscript>REF</subscript>+50kt. The threshold speed in this case may be below V<subscript>LS</subscript>, but
        this is necessary as the landing speeds are very close to tyre limit speeds.</para>

        <para>During configuration, V<subscript>LS</subscript> is computed from actual configuration and V<subscript>FE
        next</subscript> is computed from flap lever position. This may lead to a situation where
        V<subscript>LS</subscript>&gt;V<subscript>FE next</subscript>. It is therefore acceptable to set the next flap
        lever position when above V<subscript>FE next</subscript> and reduce the speed to follow
        V<subscript>LS</subscript> as the surfaces extend. Use of managed speed is not recommended during
        configuration.</para>

        <para>The autopilot may be used down to 500ft AAL, but since it is not tuned for the abnormal configuration it
        must be closely monitored.</para>

        <para>For the go-around, initially maintain flap/ slat configuration. A speed 10kt lower than max operating
        speed should be flown. If it is the slats that are jammed or if the flaps are jammed at 0, clean configuration
        can be used to transit to a diversion airfield. Diversion with flaps and/or slats extended may as much as double
        fuel consumption.</para>

        <para>Other issues include the possible loss of the automatic operation of the centre tank pumps (which
        is sequenced to the slats) and possible reversion to Alternate Law.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>SFCC faults</title>
        <para>Each SFCC has fully independant slat and flap channels. A failure of a channel in a single controller will
        lead to slow operation of the associated surfaces. In addition, the flap channel of SFFC1 provides input to the
        idle control part of the FADECs and to the EGPWC.</para>
        <para>Failure of both flap channels or failure of both slat channels is covered in <xref
        linkend="flight-controls.slats-flaps-fault"/>. </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Wingtip brake fault</title>
        <para>The wingtip brakes activate in case of assymetry, mechanism overspeed, symmetrical runaway or uncommanded
        movements. This protection is lost.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Flap attach sensor failure</title>
        <para>The flap attach sensor monitors detects excessive differential movement between the inner and outer flaps
        which would indicate failure of a flap attachment. This protection is lost.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="flight-controls.elac">
        <title>ELAC fault</title>
        <para>In normal operations, ELAC 1 controls the ailerons and ELAC 2 controls the elevators and
        stabiliser. Failure of a single ELAC will result it failover to the remaining computer. Provided no uncommanded
        maneuvres occured, an attempt can be made to reset the failed ELAC.</para>

        <para>Failure of both ELACs leads to loss of ailerons and hence Alternate Law. One of the SECs will take over
        control of the elevators and stabiliser. Again, an attempt can be made to reset the computers.</para>
        
        <para>If the fault is designated a pitch fault, only the pitch function of the associated ELAC is lost.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>SEC fault</title>
        <para>Each SEC controls either 1 or 2 spoilers per wing. SEC 1 and 2 also provide back up for the ELACs (see
        <xref linkend="flight-controls.elac"/>). Loss of a SEC leads to loss of its associated spoilers. SEC 1 provides
        spoiler position to the FACs. If speedbrakes are deployed with SEC 1 u/s and SEC 3 operative, spoiler 2 will
        deploy without a corresponding increase in V<subscript>LS</subscript>. Therefore, do not use speedbrake if SEC 1
        is affected (it won't do much anyway!). Pairs of SECs also provide the signal for reverse thrust lever angle to
        the reversers and spoiler deployment to the autobrake. A dual SEC failure will therefore lead to a loss of a
        reverser and loss of autobraking.</para>
        <para>If all SECs are lost, all the above holds true. Furthermore the flight controls revert to Alternate Law
        due to the complete loss of spoilers. Also, due to routing of LGCIU data to the ELACs via the SECs, Direct Law
        will occur at slat extension rather than gear extension.</para>
        <para>An attempt should be made to reset the affected SEC(s).</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Direct Law</title>
        <para>In Direct Law, deflection of the control surfaces is a linear function of deflection of the side-stick and
        trimming must be done manually. The controls are very sensitive at high speeds. Use of manual thrust is
        recommended as power changes will result in pitch changes. Similarly, use of the speed brake will result in nose
        up pitch changes so it should be used with care. Protections are unavailable, so speed is limited to 320kt/0.77M
        and care must be taken in GPWS or windshear maneuvres. Approach speed is increased by 10kt and landing distances
        increase by a factor of 1.2.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Stabilizer jam</title>
        <para>Manual pitch trim is a mechanical connection to the stabilizer actuator. It may be possible to use manual
        pitch trim when the ELACs have detected a stabilizer jam, although it may be heavier than normal. If it is
        useable, trim for neutral elevators.</para>
        <para>The flight controls will revert to Alternate Law. If the stabilizer could not be moved, gear extension
        should be delayed until CONF 3 and V<subscript>APP</subscript> are acheived so that the elevators are properly
        trimmed.</para>
        <para>If the jam is caused by the mechanical connection, it is possible that the ELACs will not detect the
        problem. The procedure in this case is similar, but Normal Law will remain.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Fire</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Smoke and fumes</title>
        <para>[QRH 1.06, FCOM 3.2.26.6000, amber ECAM: <emphasis role="underline">AVIONICS</emphasis> SMOKE]</para>
        
        <para>The QRH procedure should be applied when smoke is detected and the crew suspect the avionics, air
        conditioning or cabin equipment as the source. The paper procedure includes all the steps of the avionics smoke
        ECAM procedure, so if this caution is triggered, the paper procedure should be applied after completing the
        immediate actions of the ECAM procedure.</para>

        <para>In the case of other smoke related ECAMs, the relevant ECAM procedure should be applied first and then the
        use of the paper checklist considered.</para>

        <para>Rain repellent fluid leaks are not covered. Orange peel smells are toxic, pine needle smells
        non-toxic.</para>

        <para>The SMOKE/ FUMES/ AVNCS SMOKE checklist attempts to isolate the source of the smoke. It is possible that
        it may become impossible to carry out this checklist due to smoke density. In this case, interrupt the checklist
        and carry out the smoke removal drill (see <xref linkend="smoke-fumes-removal"/>). It is also possible that the
        situation may deteriorate to a level that an immediate forced landing becomes the preferable option. In general,
        unless the source of the smoke is obvious and extinguishable, a diversion should be initiated immediately. The
        smoke removal drill is most effective and adaptable at lower levels, so a descent to 10,000ft or MSA is also a
        priority.</para>

        <para>The first priority is to protect yourself, so get an oxygen mask on.</para>

        <para>The most likely sources are the avionics, the cabin fans and the galleys. Therefore immediate initial
        actions are to turn off the cabin fans and galleys and put the avionics ventilation in smoke removal mode by
        selecting both fans to OVRD.</para>

        <para>Where the smoke source is not immediately obvious and the initial actions have not caused it to cease, the
        QRH provides drills for suspected air conditioning smoke, suspected cabin equipment smoke or suspected
        avionics/ electrical smoke. In addition the avionics/ electrical smoke drill includes undetermined and
        continuing smoke sources.</para>

        <para>Suspect air conditioning smoke if it initially comes out of the ventilation outlets. Several ECAM warnings
        are also likely to occur as sensors detect the smoke in other areas. The displayed ECAM procedures must be
        applied. Following an engine or APU failure, smoke may initially enter the air conditioning system but should
        dissipate quickly once the failure is contained. The air conditioning drill starts by turning the APU bleed off
        in case this is the source. The packs are then turned off one at a time to determine if the source of the smoke
        is a pack.</para>

        <para>The cabin equipment smoke drill isolates involves selecting the commercial button off and searching for
        faulty cabin equipment.</para>

        <para>Suspect avionics smoke if the only triggered ECAM is AVIONICS SMOKE. If an item of electrical equipment
        fails immediately prior to the appearance of the smoke, that piece of equipment should be suspected as the
        source. The avionics/ electrical drill (which includes the undetermined source drill) involves shedding the AC
        buses one at a time by preventing bus transfers and turning generators off. This allows significant portions of
        the electrical equipment to be isolated in blocks. Note that if AC bus 1 is shed, the Captain's instruments and
        the STBY instruments are both supplied from non de-iced sensors and should be suspected if there is any
        disagreements. If this does not work, the emergency electrical configuration is adopted (see <xref
        linkend="emerg-elec-config"/>).</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="smoke-fumes-removal">
        <title>Smoke/ fumes removal</title>
        <para>[QRH 1.06, FCOM 3.2.26.7000]</para>
        
        <para>Smoke removal procedures initially use the pressurisation system to draw smoke and fumes overboard by
        increasing the cabin altitude. If there are no fuel vapours present, the packs are used to drive the smoke
        overboard. Otherwise it is driven overboard by residual pressure.</para>

        <para>The final target configuration is packs off, outflow valve fully open and ram air on. As this
        depressurises the aircraft, it can only be acheived at lower levels (preferably FL100). If in emergency
        configuration, turning the APU master switch on connects the batteries for a maximum of 3 minutes and allows
        manual control of the DC powered outflow valve motor. Once at a suitable level and below 200kt, as a last resort
        PNF's cockpit window can be opened.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine fire</title>
        <para>The basic sequence is to bring the thrust lever of the affected engine to idle, turn off its engine
        master, push its fire button, wait 10 seconds then deploy its first fire bottle. If the fire is not extinguished
        after 30 seconds, indicated by the fire button remaining lit, deploy the second bottle. This sequence is
        modified on the ground in that both fire bottles are fired immediately, and the remaining engine is then also
        shut down.</para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Landing gear</title>
      <sect2 id="loss-of-braking">
        <title>Loss of braking <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>
        <para>[QRH 1.13, FCOM 3.2.32.20000]</para>
        <para>If it is simply an autobrake failure, just brake manually. Otherwise, apply max reverse and attempt to use
        the alternate brake system. To do this, release the brake pedals and turn off the ASKID &amp; NW STRG switch. If
        the alternate system also appears to have failed, short successive applications of the parking brake may be
        used. Use of the parking brake in this way risks tire burst and lateral control difficulties (due brake onset
        assymetry) so delay until low speed if at all possible.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Residual braking procedure</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.10B, FCOM 3.2.32.23000]</para>
        <para>Residual brake pressure must be checked after landing gear extension as there is no ECAM warning. {TODO:
        This is in 3.3.18 but not in ezy-b - check whether our brake systems are modified}. A brief brake pressure
        indication is expected as the alternate system self tests after the gear is down locked, but pressure should
        quickly return to zero. If the triple indicator shows residual pressure after this test, try to zero it by
        pressing the brake pedals several times. If a landing must be made with residual pressure in the alternate
        braking system, use autobrake MED or immediate manual braking to prioritise the normal system. Anticipate brake
        assymetry at touchdown.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="gear-gravity-extension">
        <title>Gravity extension</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.11, FCOM 3.2.32.4000]</para>
        <para>Gravity extension is acheived by turning the GRAVITY GEAR EXTN handcrank clockwise three times until a
        mechanical stop is reached. Once the gear is down, the LG lever should be set to down to extinguish the UNLK
        lights and remove the LG CTL message from the WHEEL page.</para>
        
        <para>Availability of landing gear indications depends on the nature of the failure that resulted in the
        requirement for gravity extension. LDG GEAR control panel indications may still be available if LGCIU 1 is
        otherwise unserviceable, providing that it is electrically supplied.</para>

        <para>Gear doors may show amber on the WHEEL page after gravity extension. There may also be spurious LGCIU 2
        FAULT or BRAKES SYS 1(2) FAULT ECAM warnings</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="asymmetric-braking">
        <title>Asymmetric braking</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.11, FCOM 3.2.32.32000, FCOM 1.32.30]</para>
        <para>If brakes are only available on one side (indicated by amber brake release indicators on both wheels of
        one main gear {TODO: check this} ), apply the remaining brake progressively whilst countering swing
        with rudder. Do not use the reverse on the same side as the working brake. Landing distances will increase
        significantly so check QRH 2.32 for landing distance factor.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Landing with abnormal landing gear</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.12, FCOM 3.2.32.11000]</para>
        <para>A landing should be carried out on a hard surface runway using any available landing gear. Foaming of the
        runway is recommended. Manual braking should be used. Reverse thrust should not be used as it will cause ground
        spoiler extension. The GRVTY GEAR EXTN handcrank should be turned back to normal to allow the landing gear down
        actuators to be pressurised and thus reduce the chance of gear collapse.</para>
        
        <para>If the nose gear is not available, move the CG aft by moving passengers to the rear of the aircraft. Use
        elevator to keep the nose off the runway, but lower the nose onto the runway before elevator control is
        lost. Braking must be progressive and balanced against available elevator authority. The engines should be shut
        down with the ENG MASTER switches prior to nose impact.</para>
        
        <para>If one main gear is not available, consider crossfeeding to remove the fuel from the wing with the
        unserviceable gear. The anti-skid system cannot operate with a single main gear extended and must be switched
        off to avoid permanent brake release. The ground spoilers should not be armed in order to maintain the maximum
        possible roll authority. The engines should be shut down at touchdown. After touchdown, use roll control to keep
        the unsupported wing from touching down for as long as possible.</para>

        <para>If both main gear are unavailable, the engines should be shut down in the flare. Pitch attitude at
        touchdown must be >6°.</para>

        <para>All doors and slides are available for evacuation in any of the normal gear up attitudes.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="flight-with-gear-extended">
        <title>Flight with landing gear extended</title>
        <para>[FCOM 2.4.25]</para>

        <para>Flight into expected icing conditions is not approved. Gear down ditching has not been demonstrated. FMGC
        predictions will be erroneous - selected speed should be used for all phases except approach. Altitude alerting
        will not be available. Any failure that normally causes a degradation to alternate law will instead cause a
        degradation to direct law.</para>

        <para>The dual engine failure scenario is modified to reflect the gear limiting speed. Assisted start should be
        preferred. If the APU is not available, gear limit speeds should be disregarded to achieve a windmill start. Do
        not select flaps or slats below 200kt {TODO: find out why this is.}</para>

        <para>Performance in all phases will be affected. In particular, approach climb limiting weights for go-around
        (see FCOM 3.5.35) must be reduced by 14%. Fuel burn will increase (approximate factor is 2.3). Engine out
        ceiling and take-off performance are also impacted. Tables for calculation are available in FCOM 2.4.25.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Gear shock absorber fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.1000, FCOM 1.32.10.4000, amber ECAM: L/G SHOCK ABSORBER FAULT]</para>
        
        <para>A shock absorber did not extend when airborne or did not compress on landing. If airborne the gear cannot
        be retracted. Respect the gear extended limit speed of 280kt and see <xref
        linkend="flight-with-gear-extended"/>.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Gear not uplocked</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.2000, FCOM 1.32.10.4000, amber ECAM: L/G GEAR NOT UPLOCKED]</para>
        <para>Landing gear retraction sequence has not completed within 30 seconds. If the gear doors have closed, the
        gear will rest on the doors so avoid excess g loads. If the doors have not closed, recycle the gear. If this
        does not work, select the gear down and see <xref linkend="flight-with-gear-extended"/>.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Gear not downlocked</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.3000, FCOM 1.32.10.4000, red ECAM: L/G GEAR NOT DOWNLOCKED]</para>

        <para>Landing gear extension sequence has not completed within 30 seconds. Retract the gear and wait until it
        has fully stowed, then redeploy. If this is not successful, attempt to deploy the gear by gravity (see <xref
        linkend="gear-gravity-extension"/>).</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Gear doors not closed</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.5000, FCOM 1.32.10.4000, amber ECAM: L/G DOORS NOT CLOSED]</para>
        
        <para>A gear door is not uplocked. Recycle the gear. If the doors cannot be closed, speed is limited to
        250kt/M0.6.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Uplock fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.6000, FCOM 1.32.10.4000, amber ECAM: L/G GEAR UPLOCK FAULT]</para>
        <para>An uplock is engaged when the corresponding gear is downlocked. As the uplock will not move to accept the
        gear the gear must be left down. See <xref linkend="flight-with-gear-extended"/>.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>LGCIU disagreement</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.8000, FCOM 1.32.10.4000, amber ECAM: L/G SYS DISAGREE]</para>
        <para>The LGCIUs disagree on the position of the gear. In the absence of other ECAM warnings, the gear position
        can be assumed to agree with the gear lever position.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>LGCIU fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.9000, FCOM 1.32.10.4000, amber ECAM: L/G LGCIU 1(2) FAULT]</para>
        
        <para>The FADECs use LGCIU input to determine idle mode. If a LGCIU is determined to be faulty, the system
        failsafes to approach idle mode, and modulated idle and reverse idle (and hence reversers) will not be
        available. {TODO: This is inferred from the information in FCOM 1.70.40 - check that it's true}.</para>

        <para>The GPWS uses LGCIU 1 to determine landing gear position. If this LGCIU is faulty, the GPWS will need to
        be inhibited to prevent spurious warnings.</para>

        <para>If both LGCIUs are lost, normal landing gear control and indicating systems are lost. The gear must be
        gravity extended (see <xref linkend="gear-gravity-extension"/>). {TODO: Autopilot and autothrust are also lost -
        find out why this is}</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Gear not down</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.10000, FCOM 1.32.10.4000, red ECAM: L/G GEAR NOT DOWN]</para>
        
        <para>Indicates that the landing gear is not downlocked when radio altitude is below 750ft rad alt and N1 and
        flap setting indicate that the aircraft is on approach. If rad alt data is not available, it indicates gear is
        not down when flap 3 or flap full is selected. In some cases the warning may be cancelled with the emergency
        cancel pushbutton.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Park brake on</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.12000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, red ECAM: CONFIG PARK BRK ON]</para>
        <para>The parking brake is set when the thrust levers are set to FLX or TOGA. Check the position of the brake
        handle position and for pressure indications on the brake triple gauge.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Nosewheel steering fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.14000, FCOM 1.32.20.3000, amber ECAM: WHEEL N/W STRG FAULT]</para>
        <para>Nosewheel steering is unavailable so differential braking must be used to steer the aircraft. The
        nosewheel may not be aligned if the L/G shock absorber ECAM is also displayed, in which case delay nosewheel
        touch down as long as possible. Cat III dual will not be available.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="antiskid-nosewheel-steering-off">
        <title>Antiskid nosewheel steering off</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.15000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRAKES ANTI SKID/NWS OFF]</para>
        <para>The A/SKID &amp; NW STRG switch is off. The ABCU controls
        braking through the alternate braking system. Antiskid is not available so landing distance will increase
        significantly. Autobrake and nosewheel steering will also not be available.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Antiskid nosewheel steering fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.15000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRAKES A/SKID NWS FAULT]</para>
        <para>Either:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>both BSCU channels have failed or</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>the normal brake system has been lost and the yellow hydraulic pressure is
          low.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>Effects are as for <xref linkend="antiskid-nosewheel-steering-off"/>, although if yellow hydraulic
          pressure is low braking will be accumulator only.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Brake system fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.17000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRAKES SYS 1(2) FAULT]</para>
        <para>A fault has been detected in one channel of the BSCU. Loss of redundancy only.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Brakes hot</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.18000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRAKES HOT]</para>

        <para>At least one brake temperature is &gt;300°C. Check <xref linkend="brake-temperature-limitations"/> if the
        temperature is excessive or the brake temperatures are not reasonably even.</para>
        
        <para>Temperature must be &lt;300°C for takeoff to prevent ignition of any hydraulic fluid that leaks onto the
        brake. Use brake fans as necessary to bring the temperature down in time for the next takeoff. The brake fans
        also cool the temperature sensor, so assume the real brake temperature is twice that indicated if they have
        recently been used. {TODO: Check whether we use chocks and release the parking brake}.</para>

        <para>If the warning appears in flight, providing that performance permits, the landing gear should be extended
        to allow the brakes to cool.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Auto brake fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.19000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRAKES AUTO BRK FAULT]</para>
        <para>A failure was detected when the autobrake was armed. Brake manually.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Hydraulic selector valve fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.21000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: WHEEL HYD SEL FAULT]</para>
        <para>This ECAM message may indicate two completely different conditions:
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>The normal brake selector valve has failed in the open position. The normal servo valves
          (downstream of the selector valve) will have continuous full pressure at their inlets, but, as long as
          anti-skid is operative, will control brake pressure and anti-skid normally.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>The steering selector valve has failed in the open position. This means that the steering will
          remain pressurised as long as there is pressure in the yellow hydraulic system. This has obvious implications
          if towing is attempted, but will also mean that the nosewheel will go to maximum deflection if the A/SKID
          &amp; N/W STRG switch is selected off or the BSCU is reset.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Failure of normal braking system</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.26000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: NORM BRK FAULT]</para>
        <para>Normal braking is lost, but alternate braking and anti-skid are available. Landing distance increases
        slightly.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Failure of alternate braking system</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.30000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRAKES ALTN BRK FAULT]</para>
        <para>Loss of redundancy only.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Failure of normal and alternate braking systems</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.25000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: NORM + ALTN FAULT]</para>
        <para>The only braking remaining is the parking brake. See <xref linkend="loss-of-braking"/> for method.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Brake accumulator low pressure</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.27000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRK Y ACCU LO PR]</para>
        <para>Braking is not available unless either the green or yellow hydraulic systems are pressurised. If the
        engines are shut down, attempt to recharge the accumulator using the yellow system electrical pump. When parking
        the aircraft, use chocks.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="released-normal-brakes">
        <title>Released brakes, normal system</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.28000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRAKES RELEASED]</para>
        <para>If normal braking is active and at least one engine is running, the BSCU self tests when it receives a
        "gear downlocked" signal from either of the LGCIUs. The BRAKES RELEASED ECAM is provided if at least one set of
        brakes on a main wheel is incorrectly released during this test. The failed brake is shown by an amber release
        symbol on the WHEEL page. Loss of a brake leads to increased landing distances. If both brakes on the same gear
        are released, see <xref linkend="asymmetric-braking"/>.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Released brakes, alternate system</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.28000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: ALTERNATE L(R) RELEASED]</para>
        <para>The ABCU self tests the brakes in a similar manner to the BSCU (see <xref
        linkend="released-normal-brakes"/>). If this test is failed, normal braking can be expected as long as the
        normal braking system is active. If the alternate braking system is active, braking will be asymmetric (see
        <xref linkend="asymmetric-braking"/>).</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Minor nosewheel steering fault</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.2.32.29000, FCOM 1.32.30.3000, amber ECAM: BRAKES-N/WS MINOR FAULT]</para>
        <para>{TODO: Its not very clear from the FCOM what this refers to}</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2 id="brake-temperature-limitations">
        <title>Brake temperature limitations requiring maintenance action</title>
        <para>[FCOM 3.4.32.3000]</para>
        <para>Maintenance is required if:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>One brake temp is &gt;600°C and the other brake on the same gear is 150°C less</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>One brake temp is &lt;60°C and the other brake on the same gear is 150°C
          more</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>The average temp of one gear is 200°C more than the average temp of the
          other</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Any brake temp exceeds 900°C</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>A fuse plug has melted</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Power plant</title>
      <sect2 id="dual-engine-failure">
        <title>Dual engine failure</title>
        <para>[QRH 1.16 &amp; 1.20, FCOM 3.2.70.53000, FCOM 1.70.90.4000, red ECAM: ENG DUAL FAILURE]</para>

        <para>It is recommended that the QRH paper procedure on page 1.16 is used rather than the ECAM.</para>

        <para>First priority, assuming fuel remains, is to attempt a relight by turning the ignitors on and setting the
        thrust levers to idle. The speed should initially be increased to 300kt to increase windmilling and improve the
        chance of a relight. At this speed, the aircraft will cover approximately 2nm for every 1000ft lost. With this
        in mind, a suitable plan should be constructed to cover the possibility that relight is not possible.</para>

        <para>Whilst awaiting a relight, ensure that the emergency electrical generator is on line and recycle FAC1 to
        recover characteristic speed display and rudder trim. For communications, VHF1 and ATC1 are available in the
        emergency electrical config. Due to lack of engine bleeds, a slow depressurisation will be occuring, so be ready
        to don oxygen masks.</para>

        <para>If there has been no relight after 30 seconds, the combustion chambers should be ventilated by turning
        both engine masters off for 30 seconds. Another attempt can then be made by turning them back on. This sequence
        should be repeated until successful or until APU bleed air becomes available at FL200.</para>

        <para>Once below FL250, the APU can be started. Once below FL200, speed should be reduced to green dot and
        assisted starts should be attempted. At green dot speed, 2½nm will be covered for every 1000ft lost. Attempt to
        start one engine at a time in the normal manner.</para>

        <para>If a landing must be made without power, CONF 3 slats are recommended (flaps are
        unavailable). V<subscript>app</subscript> should be V<subscript>ref</subscript>+25kt or 150kt, whichever is
        higher. The gear is available with gravity extension. The stabilizer will be frozen once engine driven
        hydraulics are lost and elevator trimming will cease with transition to direct law at gear extension. Therefore,
        gear extension should be delayed until CONF 3 and V<subscript>app</subscript> are reached. If ditching, do not
        extend the gear.</para>

        <para>If an airfield can be reached, cross the outer marker at twice the normal height with CONF 1, gear up. For
        a clean aircraft, the following rules of thumb apply {TODO: these are Boeing rules - check that they hold for
        Airbus}:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A standard hold loses 8000ft</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>An orbit loses 4000ft</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>400ft is lost per nm</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        CONF 3, gear down will give a glide ratio of 800ft per nm.
        </para>

        <para>If an airfield cannot be reached, refer to <xref linkend="ditching"/> or <xref linkend="forced-landing"/>
        as appropriate.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine relight in flight</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.22, FCOM 3.2.70.31000]</para>

        <para>A graph showing the in flight relight envelope is provided on page 2.22 of the QRH. The ceiling is 27000
        ft. Automatic start is recommended, but crew action is required in case of abnormal start.</para>

        <para>To prepare for the start, ensure the affected engine master switch is turned off and the affected thrust
        lever is at idle. Select ignition on the engine mode selector and open the cross bleed. If it is anticipated
        starter assist may be required, ensure wing anti ice is selected off.</para>

        <para>To begin the start sequence, select the affected master switch on. The FADEC will determine whether
        starter assist is required and will open the start valve as needed. Both ignitors are energised as soon as the
        master switch is turned on, and the HP fuel valve opens at 15% N2. Closure of the start valve and
        de-energisation of the ignitors occurs at 50% N2 as normal. Light off must occur within 30 seconds of fuel flow
        initiation. If uncertain about successful relight, move the thrust lever to check for engine response. The START
        FAULT ENG STALL ECAM may be disregarded if all other parameters are normal. </para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine stall</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.23, FCOM 1.70.90.5000, FCOM 3.2.70.15000, amber ECAM ENG 1(2) STALL]</para>

        <para>A stall is indicated by abnormal engine noise, flame from the engine exhaust (and possibly inlet in
        extreme cases), fluctuating performance parameters, sluggish thrust lever response, high EGT and/ or rapid EGT
        rise when the thrust lever is advanced. The ECAM warning will be triggered when N2 is between 50% and idle. If
        N2 is above idle, the QRH should be used.</para>

        <para>The ECAM simply instructs the master switch to be turned off, and then secures the engine using the after
        engine shut down procedure (see <xref linkend="engine-shut-down"/>). This procedure should also be followed if a
        stall occurs on the ground.</para>

        <para>In flight, if no ECAM is triggered, the affected thrust lever should be retarded to idle. If the engine
        parameters remain abnormal, shut the engine down with the master switch. If the parameters are normal, turn on
        all the anti-icing to increase bleed demand {TODO: This is inferred - check it} and slowly advance the thrust
        lever. If the stall recurs, the engine can be operated at low thrust settings, otherwise it can be operated
        normally.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine tailpipe fire</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.23, FCOM 3.2.70.62000, reverse side of normal checklist]</para>

        <para>An internal engine fire may be encountered during engine start or shutdown. It will either be seen by
        ground crew or may be indicated by EGT failing to decrease after the master switch is selected off.</para>

        <para>Start by getting the engine to a known state by ensuring the man start button is selected off and the
        affected engine master is selected off.</para>

        <para>The concept is to blow the fire out by dry cranking the engine. It is therefore essential that the fire
        button is <emphasis>not</emphasis> pressed, as this will remove external power from the FADEC and prevent dry
        cranking. Firstly, a source of bleed air must be available to power the starter. Possibilities, in order of
        preference, are the APU, the opposite engine or a ground air cart. If using the opposite engine, the source
        engine bleed must be on, the target engine bleed should be off, the cross bleed should be opened and thrust
        increased to provide 30 psi of pressure. {TODO: This is just the crossbleed start procedure from 3.4.70.4000 -
        check that there are no differences}. If using ground air, both engine bleeds should be off and the cross bleed
        opened. Once high pressure air is available, select the engine mode selector to crank and select the man start
        button to on. Once the fire is extinguished, select the man start button off and the engine mode selector to
        normal.</para>

        <para>As a last resort, external fire suppression agents may be used. They are, however, highly corrosive and
        the engine will be a write off.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>High engine vibration</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.24, FCOM 3.2.70.63000]</para>

        <para>The ECAM VIB advisory (N1≥6 units, N2≥4.3 units) is simply an indication that engine parameters should be
        monitored more closely. High VIB indications alone do not require the engine to be shut down.</para>

        <para>High engine vibration combined with burning smells may be due to contact of compressor blade tips with
        associated abradable seals.</para>

        <para>If in icing conditions, high engine vibration may be due to fan blade or spinner icing. The QRH provides a
        drill to shed this ice, after which normal operations can be resumed.</para>

        <para>If vibrations rapidly increase above the advisory level, the engine should be operated at lower power
        settings to keep the vibrations below the advisory level.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="engine-shut-down">
        <title>Engine shut down</title>
        <para>[FCOM 1.70.90.5000, FCOM 3.2.70.35000, amber ECAM ENG 1(2) SHUT DOWN]</para>

        <para>This ECAM warning indicates that an engine master switch is off between the start of the takeoff roll and
        the completion of the landing roll, or that a fire button has been pushed in the other phases. It deals with the
        subsequent issues arising from single engine operation.</para>

        <para>The most pressing issue is that a single engine cannot support wing anti-ice and two packs, so if wing
        anti-ice is in use, one of the packs must be turned off. This will generally be the pack on the affected side,
        but will need to be pack 1 in electrical emergency configuration. The cross bleed must be opened for symmetrical
        wing anti-icing. If a fire button has been pushed, the cross bleed cannot be opened, and wing anti-ice is
        unavailable.</para>

        <para>The remaining engine must be safeguarded. To this end, continuous ignition should be selected.</para>

        <para>A fuel imbalance may develop. Fuel imbalance limitations are detailed in FCOM 3.1.28, but an inner tank
        imbalance of &lt;1500kg will never be limiting if the outer tanks are balanced. Fuel may still need to be
        crossfed to prevent fuel starvation of the remaining engine. {TODO: Where is the cross feed procedure?}</para>

        <para>TCAS should be selected to TA to avoid unflyable climb RAs.</para>
        
        <para>If a reverser is unlocked with associated buffet, speed should be limited to 240kt.</para>
        
        <para>If the remaining engine is operated at maximum power with the aircraft at low speed (e.g. responding to
        windshear) it is possible that directional control may be lost before the flight computer protections apply. Be
        cautious about reducing speed below V<subscript>LS</subscript> on one engine.</para>

        <para>The main systems lost are the generator, bleeds and hydraulic pump associated with the engine. Other
        systems may be lost depending on the reason for the shutdown.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Low engine oil pressure</title>

        <para>[FCOM 3.2.70.6000, FCOM 1.70.90.4000, red ECAM: ENG 1(2) OIL LO PR]</para>
        
        <para>The sources for the gauge on the ECAM ENG page and the ECAM warning are different. If there is a
        discrepancy between the two, a faulty transducer is the most likely cause and the engine can continue to be
        operated normally. If both sources agree, the engine should be shut down by retarding its thrust lever and
        selecting its master switch off and the after shutdown procedure applied (see <xref
        linkend="engine-shut-down"/>).</para>
      </sect2>


    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Navigation</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>EPGWS alerts <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>
        <para>[QRH 1.14, FCOM 3.2.34.23000]</para>

        <para>EPGWS alerts can be categorised into warnings and cautions. A warning is any alert with the instruction
        "Pull up" attached. All other alerts are cautions. A warning may be downgraded to a caution if flying in
        daylight VMC and positive visual verification is made that no hazard exists [EOM-A 8.3.5].</para>

        <para>The response to a warning is to call "Pull up, TOGA", disconnect the autopilot and simultaneously roll the
        wings level, apply full backstick and set TOGA power. The speedbrake should then be checked retracted. Once the
        flight path is safe and the warning stops, accelerate and clean up as required.</para>

        <para>The response to a caution is to correct the flight path or aircraft configuration as necessary. A
        configuration warning will almost always require a go around.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>TCAS warnings <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>
        <para>[QRH 1.15, FCOM 3.2.34.26000]</para>
        
        <para>TCAS warnings may be either traffic advisories ("Traffic, Traffic") or resolution advisories (anything
        else). The first response to either advisory is to call "TCAS, I have control" to unequivocally establish who
        will be carrying out any maneuvers. If it is a resolution advisory, the autopilot should be disconnected and the
        flight directors turned off. The autothrottle remains engaged and reverts to speed mode. A vertical maneuver
        should then be flown to keep the V/S needle out of the red areas shown on the V/S scale. ATC should then be
        notified (e.g "Radar, Easy 123 - TCAS climb"). When clear of conflict, negotiate a new clearance with ATC and
        re-engage the automatics.</para>

        <para>If a climb resolution advisory occurs on final approach, a go around must be flown.</para>
        
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>ADR faults</title>
        <para>A single ADR fault simply requires switching to the hot spare and turning the affected unit off. Loss of
        ADR1 will lead to the loss of the extended functions of the EGPWS. Loss of ADR2 will lead to both baro reference
        channels being driven by the same FCU channel {TODO: Find out details of this}, so the baro refs should be
        checked.</para>

        <para>Loss of two ADRs will lead to Alternate Law with associated speed restrictions and landing configuration
        considerations. Air data switching is used as necessary, and the affected ADRs are turned off. ATC switching may
        be required to restore transponder. If ADR 1 and 3 are lost, the landing gear safety valve is controlled closed,
        so the gear must be gravity extended and cannot subsequently be retracted.</para>

        <para>Loss of all ADRs requires reversion to standby instruments. There is no ECAM procedure - the procedure
        displayed is for single ADR operation. Therefore, refer to page 2.20 of the QRH. In addition to the failures
        associated with dual loss, the stall warning is lost, the rudder travel limiter is frozen (full rudder travel
        will be recovered at slat extension) and automatic cabin pressure control is lost.</para> 
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>RA faults</title>
        <para>A single RA fault results in degradation of approach capability to Cat II. Loss of both RAs will lead to
        direct law at landing gear extension and a loss of ILS APPR mode capability. Therefore, landing will be CONF 3
        with associated corrections, the approach should be flown in LOC and FPA and autopilot disconnect should be
        anticipated at gear extension.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>IR faults</title>
        <para>A single IR fault will simply require ATT/HDG switching. This may lead to loss of the extended functions
        of the EPGWS and/or loss of TCAS. It may be possible to recover the IR in ATT mode using the procedure on page
        2.21 of the QRH.</para>

        <para>A dual IR fault will lead to loss of PFD indications on at least one side so use ATT/HDG switching to
        recover. It will also lead to Alternate Law and associated speed restrictions and landing configuration
        considerations.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Auto-flight</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>FCU faults</title>
        <para>Loss of a single channel will result in the spare channel automatically taking over. All that is required
        is a cross check of the baro refs.</para>
        <para>Loss of both channels leads to loss of all FCU and EFIS panels. The autopilots and autothrust are
        lost and parameters that are normally controlled by the panels revert to sensible default values. If the weather
        radar image remains displayed, disregard it since the scale will be incorrect.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Hydraulics</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Blue + yellow systems low pressure</title>

        <para>[QRH 1.10, FCOM 1.29.20.4000, FCOM 3.2.29.6000, red ECAM: <emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> B + Y
        SYS LO PR]</para>

        <para>It may be possible to recover the yellow system using the yellow electrical pump or the blue system using
        the RAT. Systems lost because of low air pressure in the reservoir will be recoverable at lower
        altitudes. Systems lost due to reservoir overheats may be usable for the approach once they have cooled
        down.</para>

        <para>This is the least significant dual hydraulic loss. The systems lost include the union of losses for the
        single hydraulic system losses described in <xref linkend="blue-low-pr"/> and <xref
        linkend="yellow-low-pr"/>. In addition the right elevator is lost, the speedbrake is unusable due to losing
        spoilers 2+3+4 and the gear will be gravity extended to protect the green system (gear retraction becomes
        unavailable). The flight controls remain in Normal Law, but the autopilots are not available. Landing will be
        CONF FULL, but distances are approximately doubled.</para>

        <para>A paper summary is available on page 1.10 of the QRH, and this should be applied once all ECAM actions are
        completed.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Green + blue systems low pressure</title>

        <para>[QRH 1.11, FCOM 1.29.20.4000, FCOM 3.2.29.4000, red ECAM: <emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G + B
        SYS LO PR]</para>

        <para>If the blue system has been lost due to the loss of its electrical pump, it may be recovered by deploying
        the RAT. Systems lost because of low air pressure in the reservoir will be recoverable at lower
        altitudes. Systems lost due to reservoir overheats may be usable for the approach once they have cooled
        down.</para>

        <para>The systems lost include the union of losses for the single hydraulic system losses described in <xref
        linkend="green-low-pr"/> and <xref linkend="blue-low-pr"/>. In addition, the slats are jammed (see <xref
        linkend="flight-controls.slats-flaps-fault"/>) and the ailerons and left elevator are lost. This leads to
        Alternate Law and hence loss of autopilots. Whilst the autothrust is available, it should be disconnected early
        in the approach as it is not able to cope with the quantity of failed systems. The gear should be gravity
        extended (hence Direct Law) at 200kt in order to improve contollability with the single elevator. The speed
        brake should not be used since the differential spoilers are required for roll control. Due to the single
        elevator and lost ailerons, expect slightly sluggish response in the flare. Landing will be CONF 3 (flaps only)
        and landing distance is approximately doubled.</para>

        <para>A paper summary is available on page 1.11 of the QRH, and this should be applied once all ECAM actions are
        completed.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Green + yellow systems low pressure</title>

        <para>[QRH 1.12, FCOM 1.29.20.4000, FCOM 3.2.29.5000, red ECAM: <emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G + Y
        SYS LO PR]</para>

        <para>It may be possible to recover the yellow system using the yellow electrical pump. Systems lost because of
        low air pressure in the reservoir will be recoverable at lower altitudes. Systems lost due to reservoir
        overheats may be usable for the approach once they have cooled down.</para>

        <para>This is the worst case dual hydraulic loss. The systems lost include the union of losses for the single
        hydraulic system losses described in <xref linkend="green-low-pr"/> and <xref linkend="yellow-low-pr"/>. In
        addition, the flaps are jammed (see <xref linkend="flight-controls.slats-flaps-fault"/>), the reversers are
        lost, the yaw damper is lost, the stabiliser is frozen, and the braking is by accumulator only (7 full
        applications available, anti-skid lost). The lost systems lead to reversion to Alternate Law. With the
        stabiliser frozen, the transition to Direct Law at gear extension should be delayed until CONF 3 and
        V<subscript>app</subscript> are achieved to allow the elevators to be trimmed correctly for the
        approach. Landing will be CONF 3 (slats only), and landing distances are almost tripled.</para>

        <para>A paper summary is available on page 1.12 of the QRH, and this should be applied once all ECAM actions are
        completed.</para>

      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="green-low-pr">
        <title>Green system low pressure</title>
        <para>The major lost systems are normal landing gear operation (gravity extension is available), nose wheel
        steering and normal brake system (including autobrake). Landing distance will be increased due to loss of two
        spoilers per wing and reverser 1. Flap and slat deployment will be slow.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="yellow-low-pr">
        <title>Yellow system low pressure</title>
        <para>Two spoilers per wing and reverser 2 are lost, so landing distance will increase slightly. Flap deployment
        will be slow. As the alternate braking system is only available through the brake accumulator, ensure there is
        sufficient pressure when the parking brake is set.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2 id="blue-low-pr">
        <title>Blue system low pressure</title>
        <para>One spoiler per wing will be lost but this has negligible effect on landing distance. Slats will be slow to
        deploy. Deployment of the RAT is not recommended unless another system is lost. If the system is lost due to low
        reservoir level, emergency generation capability is lost.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Low Reservoir Air Pressure</title>
        <para>Loss of air pressure to a hydraulic reservoir may lead to pump cavitation and hence fluctuating
        pressures. If this occurs, turn off the affected pump, and if applicable, turn off the PTU. Cavitation reduces
        with altitude, so it may be possible to reinstate the system during the descent.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Overheat</title>
        <para>Turn off all affected pumps and if applicable, turn off the PTU. The system should be reinstated for the
        approach if it has cooled sufficiently.</para>
      </sect2>

    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Pneumatic</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Dual bleed failure</title>
        <para>[QRH 2.02, FCOM 3.2.36.6000, NTC 1.106]</para>

        <para>A known problem with the A319 is that the load on a single bleed supplying two packs at high altitude may
        be sufficient to cause it to trip off. In this case, turning off one pack may allow a bleed reset.</para>

        <para>There is no ECAM associated with a dual bleed failure. The QRH 2.02 procedure applies both to the case
        where the aircraft has dispatched with an inoperative bleed IAW MEL, and in the case where an in-flight failure
        has left a single bleed remaining.</para>

        <para>In the case of an isolated bleed duct (due bleed air leak, engine fire or failed open start valve), the
        bleed associated with the duct is clearly unrecoverable. Since the remaining bleed would only have been
        supplying a single pack, the overload case does not apply. Hence, this bleed is also considered unrecoverable,
        and a bleed reset should not be attempted. If, on the other hand, both ducts are available and a single bleed
        has been supplying two packs, an overload may be suspected and an attempt can be made to reset the overloaded
        bleed once one of the packs is turned off.</para>

        <para>If an engine bleed cannot be recovered, providing #1 bleed duct is available, the APU bleed may be used to
        supply a single pack when below FL225. If the #2 bleed duct is isolated, only pack 1 can be used since the cross
        bleed will be closed. Otherwise, either pack may be used. Note that the APU bleed is not capable of supplying
        bleed air for wing anti-ice.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
</article>


