<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<!-- use fill column 100 -->
<book id="airbus-nonnormal">
  <title>Airbus A320 Family Non-Normal Notes</title>
  <subtitle>Version 2.5</subtitle>

<preface>
  <title>Change log</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Change highlighting</title>

    <para>Change highlighting is only available in the online version. This may be found at:

    <blockquote><para><ulink url="https://hursts.org.uk"/></para></blockquote></para>

    <para>Changes since version 2.4 are highlighted.</para>

    <para>Changed sections have a green background, added sections have a yellow background. Removed
    sections are notified in the change log.</para>

    <para>Changes to cross references induced by Airbus re-jigging their manuals are not
    highlighted.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Changes since version 2.4</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Removed reference to “read ECAM” from <xref linkend="efato"/> as easyJet has
      now standardised of Airbus SOPs for ECAM handling.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Updated target go around speed for <xref linkend="dualhyd.gy"/> to comply with
      new Airbus guidance. My thanks to Sjoerd de Vries for pointing this out.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Updated approximate diversionary fuel flows for <xref linkend="dualhyd.gy"/>,
      <xref linkend="dualhyd.by"/> and <xref linkend="dualhyd.gb"/> to take account of data
      introduced by the new Fuel Penalty Factor tables in the QRH.</para></listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Changes since version 2.3</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Cross references are updated throughout to account for February 2018
      re-jigging of FCOM, FCTM, QRH and EOM-B.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Added footnote to <xref linkend="rejected_takeoff"/> to explain that the Feb
      2018 changes to RTO procedures do not really change anything.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Added advice for a fresh takeoff attempt following an RTO to <xref
      linkend="rejected_takeoff"/>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Removed “engine failure” and “engine fire” calls from <xref linkend="efato"/>.
      These calls have been dropped from EOM-B. Due to EOM-B ambiguity, added advice to state the
      first ECAM procedure title with a footnote explaining that this is an interpretation of the
      ambiguous procedures.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Deleted “Immediate VMC recovery” section; it has been removed from FCOM and
      hasn't surfaced anywhere else.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Improved <xref linkend="efic"/> to explain reasons for required
      actions.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Added requirement for FLAP 3 landing to <xref
      linkend="se_circling"/>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Added <xref linkend="ldg-elev-fault"/>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Added advice about direct law go-arounds to <xref
      linkend="direct-law"/>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Added FCTM info regarding spurious AVIONICS SMOKE ECAMs to <xref
      linkend="smoke-fumes"/>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Improved <xref linkend="asymmetric-braking"/>.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Removed section with reference to “if engines are running” from <xref
      linkend="dual-engine-failure"/> since this is clearly nonsense. Sorry.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Added explanation of interaction between ECAM and QRH to <xref
      linkend="dual-engine-failure"/>.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

</preface>


<chapter>
  <title>Operating techniques</title>

  <sect1 id="rejected_takeoff">
    <title>Rejected Takeoff</title>

    <para>The decision to reject rests solely with CM1. This decision is communicated with the words
    “Stop” or “Go”. “Stop” implies that CM1 is taking control of the aircraft. Below 100kt the RTO
    is relatively risk free and a decision to stop should be made for any ECAM and most other
    problems. Above 100kt the RTO may be hazardous and stopping should only be considered for loss
    of engine thrust, any fire warning, any uninhibited ECAM<footnote><para>A
    change was introduced in Feb 2018 whereby five amber ECAM cautions requiring a high speed stop
    are specifically listed. An exhaustive search of amber ECAM cautions that are not inhibited
    between 80kt and lift off revealed only two cautions in addition to this list: ENG 1(2) THR
    LEVER DISAGREE if the FADEC automatically selects idle thrust and FWS FWC 1+2 FAULT. The first
    of these should theoretically never happen due to FADEC logic. The second generates a message on
    the EWD but no master caution, since it is the computers that generate master cautions that have
    failed. You could therefore modify this rule to: stop for any ECAM warning or caution except the
    caution-like FWS FWC 1+2 FAULT.</para></footnote> or anything which indicates the aircraft will
    be unsafe or unable to fly.</para>

    <para>If a stop is required, CM1 calls “Stop” while simultaneously bringing the thrust levers to
    idle, then to max reverse. If the stop was commenced below 72kt the ground spoilers will not
    automatically deploy and the autobrake will therefore not engage. Monitor automatic braking, and
    if there is any doubt, apply manual braking as required. If normal braking fails, announce “Loss
    of braking” and proceed with the loss of braking memory items (see <xref
    linkend="loss-of-braking"/>). If the reason for the stop was an engine fire on the upwind side,
    consider turning the aircraft to keep the fire away from the fuselage. If there is any chance of
    requiring evacuation, bring the aircraft to a complete halt, stow the reversers, apply the
    parking brake, and order “Attention, crew at stations” on the PA. If evacuation will definitely
    not be required, once the aircraft’s safety is assured the RTO can be discontinued and the
    runway cleared. In this case make a PA of “Cabin crew, normal operations”.</para>

    <para>During this initial phase, CM2 confirms reverse (“Reverse green”), confirms deceleration
    (“Decel”), cancels any audio warnings, informs ATC and announces “70 knots” when
    appropriate. CM2 then locates the emergency evacuation checklist.</para>

    <para>Once the aircraft has stopped, CM1 takes the radios and asks CM2 to carry out any required
    ECAM actions. Whilst the ECAM actions are being completed, CM1 will build up a decision as to
    whether to evacuate. If an evacuation is required see <xref linkend="evacuation"/>. Otherwise
    order “Cabin crew, normal operations”.</para>

    <para>If the aircraft has come to a complete halt using autobrake MAX, the brakes can be
    released by disarming the spoilers.</para>

    <para>If, following an RTO, a new takeoff is to be attempted, reset both
    FDs, set the FCU, then restart SOPs from the After Start checklist. Carefully consider brake
    temperatures; temperature indications continue to climb for some time after a significant
    braking event.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOMB 3.10, FCTM PRO.AEP.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="efato">
    <title>Failures during takeoff when above V1</title>

    <para>If an engine has lost thrust, apply rudder conventionally. At V<subscript>r</subscript>
    rotate towards an initial pitch target of 12½° at a slightly reduced rate, then target speed
    V<subscript>2</subscript> to V<subscript>2</subscript>+15kt. Bank angle should be limited to 15°
    when more than 3kt below manoeuvring speed for the current configuration<footnote><para>This is
    a conservative rule of thumb. If the FMGC has correctly identified an engine out condition, the
    FD/AP will automatically limit bank angle according to a less conservative
    algorithm. [FCOM SYS.22.20.60.40]</para></footnote>.</para>

    <para>When the ground to flight mode transition is complete<footnote><para>Introducing TOGA
    during the ground to flight mode transition (commences as the pitch increases through 8°,
    complete after 5 seconds) results in a pitch up moment at a time where the effect of stick pitch
    control is not wholly predictable: the stick will need to be moved forward of neutral to
    counteract the introduced pitch moment and then returned to neutral as flight mode blends in. A
    slight pause before selecting TOGA results in much more normal and predictable
    handling.</para></footnote>, select TOGA (FLX may be used but this tends to allow speed to decay
    unless pitch is reduced), adjust and trim rudder to maintain &beta; target and request “pull
    heading”. If the EOSID follows the track of the cleared SID, NAV may be used, but this is very
    rare with easyJet EOSIDs.  Engage the autopilot once gear is up and rudder is trimmed.</para>

    <para>Whilst below 400ft, the only failure related actions should be:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>If applicable, PM should state the title of the first
      displayed ECAM procedure, but should delay confirmation.<footnote><para
     >The Feb 2018 update to EOM-B removed the “engine failure” and “engine
      fire” calls, but leaves the timing of the reading of the ECAM title ambiguous. The advice
      given here is one interpretation. Since these calls were good for situational awareness,
      replacing them with a bald statement of the first ECAM procedure title seems
      sensible.</para></footnote></para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Cancellation of master warning or master caution when both pilots confirm they
      are aware of it.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Heightened awareness of the possibility of missing essential normal actions,
      such as calling rotate or raising the gear due to the distraction of the
      failure.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>Once above 400ft with safe flight path assured, decide on an initial strategy. In general,
    where a loss of thrust has occurred or is anticipated, the strategy will be to fly the EOSID
    with a level acceleration segment (see <xref linkend="eosid"/>). Otherwise, it will be to remain
    on the normal SID and fly a normal climb profile. Any deviation from the cleared SID will
    require ATC to be informed as a priority, usually as part of a PAN or MAYDAY message. In rare
    cases where the cleared SID requires a very early turn it may be necessary to determine and
    action a strategy when below 400ft. If this is the case, it must be thoroughly briefed.</para>

    <para revisionflag="changed">Once the flight path strategy has been agreed and actioned, the
    failure can be triaged, diagnosed and contained. Once the diagnosis is agreed, PF will take the
    radios and request PNF to carry out the containment actions. The standard phraseology is “My
    Radios, ECAM actions”. PF taking the radios is also a good trigger to consider a Mayday and an
    “Attention crew at stations”.</para>

    <para>When applying ECAM procedures, PF is responsible for moving the thrust levers once
    confirmed by PNF. PNF is responsible for everything else, but movement of engine master
    switches, IR selectors and any guarded switch must be confirmed with PF.</para>

    <para>PNF indicates high priorty tasks are completed with the phrase “Engine is secure.”  This
    call is not official SOP (i.e. it is not mentioned in any manual), but has evolved to be
    standard in the sim since it is PF’s trigger to interrupt ECAM and accelerate.  High priority
    tasks are defined as:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>For engine failure, the master switch of the affected engine has been turned
      off.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>For engine fire, one squib has been fired and the fire warning has
      extinguished or both squibs have been fired.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCTM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="eosid">
    <title>EOSID</title>

    <para>Before the divergence point (the last common point between the SID and the EOSID), if the
    aircraft detects a loss of thrust the EOSID will be displayed as a temporary flight plan. In
    this case the temporary flight plan can be inserted and NAV mode used. Otherwise it will be
    necessary to pull heading and manually follow either the yellow line or bring up a pre-prepared
    secondary flight plan and follow the white line.</para>

    <para>If beyond the divergence point, pull heading and make an <emphasis>immediate</emphasis>
    turn the shortest way onto the EOSID. Airbus specifically recommends against this in
    DSC.22_20.60.40, but easyJet states it as policy in EOMB 4.4.4.</para>

    <para>Electing to fly the EOSID implies a level acceleration segment:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Initially fly a TOGA climb at the higher of
      V<subscript>2</subscript> or current speed, up to a limit of
      V<subscript>2</subscript>+15kt. If a FLEX takeoff was carried out, a FLEX climb is
      permissible. This climb is continued until all high priority tasks are complete (see <xref
      linkend="efato"/>) and the aircraft is above single engine acceleration altitude (usually
      1000ft QFE, but may be higher if so specified by the take-off performance calculation). If the
      FMGS has detected the engine out condition, the automatic mode change from SRS to CLB will be
      inhibited; if not, intervention with selected modes will be required to prevent untimely
      acceleration.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>The next segment is a TOGA level acceleration and clean
      up, either to Conf 1 and S speed if an immediate VMC return is desired or to Conf 0 and green
      dot. Again FLEX may be used if a FLEX takeoff was carried out. Level acceleration is usually
      achieved by pushing V/S; if the FMGS has detected the engine out condition, all preselected
      speeds entered in the MCDU will have been deleted, so the managed target speed should
      automatically move to 250kt. The phrases “Stop ECAM” and “Continue ECAM” can be used to
      interrupt ECAM procedures in order to initiate this segment.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>The final segment is a MCT climb segment to MSA, either
      at S speed if in Conf 1 or at green dot speed if in Conf 0. This is usually achieved in open
      climb; if the FMGS has detected the engine out condition, the managed target speed becomes
      dependent on flight phase, and in this case should automatically select green
      dot.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    TOGA may be used for a maximum of 10 minutes.</para>

    <para>If an EOSID is annotated as “STD”, then acceleration to green dot should be completed
    prior to commencing the first turn. If “NON-STD”, the turn takes priority.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOMB 4.4.4, FCOM DSC.22_20.60.40]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Miscellaneous</title>

  <sect1 id="emerg-descent">
    <title>Emergency descent <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>

    <para>If an emergency descent is required, the Captain should consider
    taking control if not already PF. PF initiates the memory items by announcing “Emergency
    Descent.”</para>

    <para>Don oxygen masks, set them to the N position<footnote><para>There
    may be insufficient oxygen to cover the entire emergency descent profile if the oxygen masks are
    left set to 100%.</para></footnote> and establish communication.</para>

    <para>PF then flies the emergency descent.  Descent with autopilot and
    autothrust engaged is preferred. The configuration is thrust idle, full speed brake and maximum
    appropriate speed, taking into account possible structural damage.<footnote><para>According to
    Airbus, structural damage may be suspected if there has been a “loud bang” or there is a high
    cabin vertical speed. When limiting descent speed due to suspected structural damage, it is IAS
    rather than Mach that is relevant.</para></footnote> Target altitude is FL100 or MORA if this is
    higher. If speed is low, allow speed to increase before deploying full speedbrake to prevent
    activation of the angle of attack protection. Landing gear may be used below 25,000ft, but speed
    must be below V<subscript>LO</subscript> when it is extended and remain below
    V<subscript>LE</subscript>. If on an airway, consider turning 90° to the left.</para>

    <para>PM’s only memory action is to turn the seatbelt signs
    on.<footnote><para>Prior to a 2017 update from Airbus, PM would complete a fairly lengthy list
    of memory items at the start of the Emergency Descent procedure. It was found that PM was more
    usefully employed monitoring PF’s actions, and hence most of these memory items were removed to
    a read and do checklist to be completed once descent had been initiated.</para></footnote>
    Initially, PM’s main task is to ensure that PF has promptly and correctly initiated the
    descent.</para>

    <para>Once the memory actions are complete and the aircraft is
    descending, PF should call for the Emergency Descent Checklist (“My radios, Emergency Descent
    Checklist”). This will lead PF to finesse the speed and altitude targets and inform ATC of the
    descent; PM to set continuous ignition on the engines, set 7700 on the transponder and, if cabin
    altitude will exceed 14,000ft, deploy the cabin oxygen masks. On easyJet aircraft, the CIDS/PRAM
    will automatically play a suitable PA, so it is not necessary for the flight crew to carry out
    the EMER DESCENT (PA) action.</para>

    <para>Once level, restore the aircraft to a normal configuration. When
    safe to do so, advise cabin crew and passengers that it is safe to remove their masks. To
    deactivate the mask microphone and switch off the oxygen flow, close the oxygen mask stowage
    compartment and press the “PRESS TO RESET” oxygen control slide.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOMB 3.80.2, QRH AEP.MISC, FCOM AEP.MISC, FCTM AEP.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Windshear <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>

    <sect2 id="reactive-windshear">
      <title>Reactive</title>

      <para>The windshear detection system is a function of the Flight Augmentation Computer
      (FAC). It only operates during the takeoff and landing phases with at least CONF 1
      selected. In the takeoff phase, warnings are provided from 3 seconds after lift off until
      1300ft RA is achieved. In the landing phase warnings are provided between 1300ft RA and 50ft
      RA. A warning is indicated by a red “WINDSHEAR” flag on the PFD and a “WINDSHEAR, WINDSHEAR,
      WINDSHEAR” aural warning.</para>

      <para>When on the ground, windshear is <emphasis>only</emphasis> indicated by significant
      airspeed variations. It is possible that these fluctuations may cause
      V<subscript>1</subscript> to occur significantly later in the takeoff run then it should. It
      therefore falls to the Captain to make an assessment of whether sufficient runway remains to
      reject the takeoff, or whether getting airborne below V<subscript>r</subscript> would be the
      better option. If the takeoff is to be continued in windshear conditions, call “Windshear,
      TOGA” and apply TOGA power.  Rotate at V<subscript>r</subscript> or with sufficient runway
      remaining and follow SRS orders.<footnote><para>“Sufficient runway remaining” is actually
      Boeing advice – Airbus offers no guidance for the case where there is insufficient runway
      available to stop nor to rotate at normal speeds.</para></footnote> SRS will maintain a
      minimum rate of climb, even if airspeed must be sacrificed.</para>

      <para>If a warning occurs when airborne, call “Windshear, TOGA”, apply TOGA power and maintain
      current configuration. The autopilot can fly the escape manoeuvre as long as
      &alpha;<subscript>req</subscript>&nbsp;&lt;&nbsp;&alpha;<subscript>prot</subscript>. If the
      autopilot is not engaged, follow the SRS orders on the FD. If the FD is not available,
      initially pitch up to 17.5°, then increase as required. Do not change configuration until out
      of the windshear.</para>

      <para>In severe windshear, it is possible that ALPHA FLOOR protection
      will activate. As TOGA will already be selected, this will have no immediate effect. Once
      clear of the windshear, however, TOGA LK will be active, requiring the autothrust to be
      disconnected to avoid an overspeed. This is most naturally achieved by pressing the
      “instinctive disconnect pb” on the thrust levers then flying manual thrust until the situation
      has sufficiently stabilised to re-engage the autothrust.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.AEP.SURV]</para>
    </sect2>


    <sect2 id="predictive_ws">
      <title>Predictive</title>

      <para>When below 2300ft AGL, the weather radar scans a 5nm radius 60° arc ahead of the
      aircraft for returns indicating potential windshear.</para>

      <para>Alerts are categorised as advisory, caution or warning, in increasing order of
      severity. Severity is determined by range, position and phase of flight. Alerts are only
      provided when between 50ft and 1500ft, or on the ground when below 100kt.</para>

      <para>All types of alert produce an indication of windshear position on the ND, providing the
      ND range is set to 10nm. A message on the ND instructs the crew to change range to 10nm if not
      already set. Cautions also give an amber “W/S AHEAD” message on both PFDs and an aural
      “MONITOR RADAR DISPLAY” warning. Warnings give a red “W/S AHEAD” message on the PFDs and
      either a “WINDSHEAR AHEAD, WINDSHEAR AHEAD” or “GO AROUND, WINDSHEAR AHEAD” aural
      message.</para>

      <para>If a warning alert occurs during the takeoff roll, reject the takeoff. If it occurs
      during initial climb, call “Windshear, TOGA”, apply TOGA thrust and follow SRS
      orders. Configuration may be changed as long as the windshear is not entered.</para>

      <para>If a warning alert occurs during approach, carry out a normal go-around. If positive
      verification is made that no hazard exists, providing that the reactive windshear is
      serviceable the crew may downgrade the warning to a caution. If a caution alert occurs during
      approach, consider use of CONF 3 and increasing V<subscript>APP</subscript> to a maximum of
      V<subscript>LS</subscript>+15.</para>

      <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.AES.SURV]</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="unreliable-airspeed">
    <title>Unreliable airspeed <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>

    <para>Unreliable airspeed indications may result from radome damage and/or unserviceable probes
    or ports. Altitude indications may also be erroneous if static probes are affected.</para>

    <para>The FMGCs normally reject erroneous ADR data by isolating a single source that has
    significant differences to the other two sources. It is possible that a single remaining good
    source may be rejected if the other two sources are erroneous in a sufficiently similar way. In
    this case, it falls to the pilots to identify and turn off the erroneous sources to recover good
    data.</para>

    <para>The first problem is recognition of a failure, since the aircraft systems may be unable to
    warn of a problem. The primary method of doing this is correlation of aircraft attitude and
    thrust to displayed performance. Correlation of radio altimeter and GPIRS derived data
    (available on GPS MONITOR page) may also aid identification. The stall warning (available in
    alternate or direct law) is based on alpha probes, so will likely be valid. Other clues may
    include fluctuations in readings, abnormal behaviour of the automatics, high speed buffet or low
    aerodynamic noise.</para>

    <para>If the aircraft flight path is in doubt, disconnect the automatics and fly the following
    short term attitude and thrust settings to initiate a climb:

    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <colspec align="left" colwidth="2*"/>
        <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <colspec align="center" colwidth="*"/>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry align="center">Condition</entry><entry>Thrust</entry><entry>Pitch</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Below Thrust Reduction Altitude</entry>
            <entry>TOGA</entry><entry>15°</entry>
          </row>
          <row><entry>Below FL100</entry><entry>Climb</entry><entry>10°</entry></row>
          <row><entry>Above FL100</entry><entry>Climb</entry><entry>5°</entry></row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>

    If configured CONF Full, select CONF 3, otherwise flap/slat configuration should be
    maintained. The gear and speedbrake should be retracted. If there is any doubt over the validity
    of altitude information, the FPV must be disregarded. If altitude information is definitely
    good, the FPV may be used.</para>

    <para>It is important to understand that at this stage, while the pilot has
    identified that airspeed is unreliable, the aircraft systems have not. Thus flight envelope
    protections based on airspeed data from unreliable ADRs may activate. This may lead to pitch
    inputs from the flight computers that cannot be overridden with the sidesticks. In this case,
    immediately switch off any two ADRs; this causes the flight computers to revert to Alternate Law
    with no protections, and thus allows control of the aircraft to be regained.</para>

    <para>Once the flight path is under control and a safe altitude is attained, the aircraft should
    be transitioned into level flight. Refer to QRH AEP.NAV.USI to extract a ballpark thrust
    setting, a reference attitude and a reference speed for the current configuration, bearing in
    mind that an auto-retraction of the flap may have occurred. Set the ballpark thrust setting and
    adjust pitch attitude to fly level; if barometric altitude data is considered accurate use the
    VSI, otherwise fly a constant GPS altitude. The thrust should then be adjusted until level
    flight is achieved with the reference attitude. Note that in the radome damage case, the
    required N1 may be as much as 5% greater than the ballpark figure. Once stable, the speed will
    be equal to the reference speed.</para>

    <para>If there is insufficient data available to fly level (e.g. GPS data unavailable and
    barometric data unreliable), fly the reference attitude with the ballpark thrust setting. This
    will give approximately level flight at approximately reference speed.</para>

    <para>With the speed now known, the ADRs can be checked to see if any are giving accurate
    data. If at least one ADR is reliable, turn off the faulty ADRs. GPS and IRS ground speeds may
    also be used for an approximate cross check.</para>

    <para>If all ADRs are considered unreliable, turn off any two of them; one is kept on to provide
    stall warning from the alpha probes. More recent aircraft have backup speed/altitude scales
    based on AOA probes and GPS altitudes which are activated when below FL250 by turning off the
    third ADR. The ALL ADR OFF procedure in QRH AEP.NAV describes the use of these scales, but it
    boils down to fly the green on the speed scale and anticipate slightly reduced accuracy from the
    altitude scale.  For aircraft without this functionality, tables are provided in section
    AEP.NAV.USI of the QRH to enable all phases of flight to be flown using just pitch and thrust
    settings. Acceleration and clean up are carried out in level flight. Flap 1 can be selected as
    soon as climb thrust is selected, flap 0 once the appropriate S speed pitch attitude from the
    table on the first page of the QRH AEP.NAV.USI procedure is reached. Configuration
    for approach is also carried out in level flight, stabilising in each configuration using the
    technique described above. The approach is flown in CONF 3 at an attitude that should result in
    VLS+10 when flying a 3° glide. Landing distance will be increased.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.NAV, FCOM PRO.AEP.NAV, FCTM PRO.AEP.NAV]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Incapacitation</title>

    <para>Take control, using the stick priority button if necessary. Contact cabin crew ASAP. They
    should strap the incapacitated pilot to his seat, move the seat back, then recline it. If there
    are two cabin crew available, the body can be moved. Medical help should be sought from
    passengers, and the presence of any type rated company pilots on board ascertained.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCTM PRO.AEP.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="ditching">
    <title>Ditching</title>

    <para>If time is short due to loss of thrust at low altitude, a “quick“
    ditching procedure is available on the back of the normal checklist. This procedure gives you a
    suitable configuration for ditching (CONF 2, Gear up) and a table for determining a suitable
    approach speed given your gross weight. It also instructs that the APU be started, the ditching
    button be pushed, provides guidance for the flare (minimise VS, attitude 11°) and provides
    instructions for shutting down the engines and APU on touchdown (all masters off).</para>

    <para>If time is available, apply the procedures in the QRH. The
    QRH AEP.MISC Ditching procedure applies if the engines are running. If the engines are not
    running, refer to the appropriate QRH AEP.ENG <emphasis role="underline">ENG</emphasis> DUAL
    FAILURE procedure, both of which include ditching.</para>

    <para>Preparation for ditching involves notifying ATC in order to
    expedite rescue, preparing survival equipment and securing the aircraft for impact. The GPWS
    should be inhibited to prevent nuisance warnings. The crew oxygen should be turned off below
    FL100 to prevent potentially dangerous leaks.<footnote id="fnoxyoff"><para>The reasoning behind
    turning off the crew oxygen is an assumption on my part.</para></footnote></para>

    <para>The engines operative ditching configuration is gear up, config full, 11° pitch and
    minimal V/S. If both engines are inoperative, use config 3 (only slats available) and maintain
    at least 150kt. In strong winds, land into wind. In lighter winds, land parallel to swell. The
    bleeds are all turned off and ditching button pushed (ensure pressurisation is in auto for this
    to work) in order to close all openings below the waterline and reduce water ingress. At 2000ft,
    make a PA “Cabin crew, landing positions”. At 500ft, make a PA “Brace, brace”</para>

    <para>At touchdown, turn the engine and APU masters off. After coming to
    a stop, notify ATC, push all fire buttons, discharge all agents (engine agent 2 may not be
    available) and evacuate the aircraft.<footnote id="fnnfr"><para>The “no fuel remaining”
    procedure does not directly call for the fire buttons to be pushed or the agents to be
    discharged, but the evacuation action includes these items.</para></footnote></para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.MISC, QRH AEP.ENG, FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="forced-landing">
    <title>Forced landing</title>

    <para>If time is short due to loss of thrust at low altitude, a “quick“
    forced landing procedure is available on the back of the normal checklist. This procedure gives
    you a suitable configuration for forced landing (CONF 2, Gear down by gravity, spoilers armed)
    and a table for determining a suitable approach speed given your gross weight. It also instructs
    that the APU be started, provides guidance for the flare (minimise VS) and provides instructions
    for shutting down the engines and APU on touchdown (all masters off).</para>

    <para>If time is available, apply the procedures in the QRH.  The
    QRH AEP.MISC Forced Landing procedure applies if the engines are running. If the engines are not
    running, refer to the appropriate QRH AEP.ENG <emphasis role="underline">ENG</emphasis> DUAL
    FAILURE procedure, both of which include forced landing.</para>

    <para>Preparation for forced landing involves notifying ATC in order to expedite rescue,
    preparing survival equipment and securing the aircraft for impact. The GPWS should be inhibited
    to prevent nuisance warnings. The crew oxygen should be turned off below FL100 to prevent
    potentially dangerous leaks.<footnoteref linkend="fnoxyoff"/></para>

    <para>The engines operative forced landing configuration is gear down, config full, spoilers
    armed. If the engines are inoperative, use config 3 (only slats available) and maintain at least
    150kt. The ram air button is used to ensure that the aircraft will be completely depressurised
    at touchdown. At 2000ft, make a PA “Cabin crew, landing positions”. At 500ft, make a PA “Brace,
    brace”</para>

    <para>At touchdown, turn the engine and APU masters off. This will leave accumulator braking
    only. After coming to a stop, set the parking brake, notify ATC, push all fire buttons,
    discharge all agents (engine agent 2 may not be available) and evacuate the
    aircraft.<footnoteref linkend="fnnfr"/></para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.MISC, QRH AEP.ENG, FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="evacuation">
    <title>Evacuation</title>

    <para>Evacuation should be carried out in accordance with the emergency evacuation
    checklist. The easyJet procedure is for CM1 to call for the checklist and then send a Mayday
    message to ATC before commencing the checklist.</para>

    <para>The first two items confirm the RTO actions of stopping the aircraft, setting the parking
    brake and alerting the cabin crew. The next item confirms ATC has been alerted.</para>

    <para>The next four items prepare the aircraft for evacuation. If manual
    cabin pressure has been used, CM2 checks cabin diff is zero, and if necessary manually opens the
    outflow valve. CM2 then shuts the engines down with their master switches, and pushes all the
    fire buttons (including the APU). Confirmation is not required before carrying out these
    actions.<footnote><para>The Airbus Training Study Guide was recently (mid 2017) changed to align
    with the FCTM.</para></footnote> In response to the next checklist item, “Agents”, CM1 decides
    if any extinguishing agents should be discharged and instructs CM2 to discharge them as
    required. Engine agent 2 will not be available. Agents should only be discharged if there are
    positive signs of fire.</para>

    <para>Finally, order the evacuation. This is primarily done with the PA “Evacuate, unfasten your
    seat belts and get out”, with the evacuation alarm being triggered as a backup.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOMB 3.80.1, FCOM PRO.AER.MISC, FCTM PRO.AER.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="overweight_landing">
    <title>Overweight landing</title>

    <para>A landing can be made at any weight, providing sufficient landing
    distance is available. In general, automatic landings are only certified up to MLW, but the FCOM
    specifies that, for the A319 only, autoland is available up to 69000kg in case of emergency. The
    preferred landing configuration is CONF&nbsp;FULL, but lower settings may be used if required by
    QRH/ECAM procedures. QRH AER.MISC.OL also specifies CONF 3 if the aircraft weight exceeds the
    CONF&nbsp;3 go around limit; this will only ever be a factor for airfields with elevations above
    1000ft. Packs should be turned off to provide additional go around thrust. If planned landing
    configuration is less than FULL, use 1+F for go-around.</para>

    <para>It is possible that S speed will be higher than V<subscript>FE&nbsp;next</subscript> for
    CONF 2. In this case, a speed below V<subscript>FE&nbsp;next</subscript> should be selected
    until CONF 2 is achieved, then managed speed can be re-engaged.</para>

    <para>In the final stages of the approach, reduce speed to achieve V<subscript>LS</subscript> at
    runway threshold. Land as smoothly as possible, and apply max reverse as soon as the main gear
    touches down. Maximum braking can be used after nosewheel touchdown. After landing, switch on
    the brake fans and monitor brake temperatures carefully. If temperatures exceed 800°C, tyre
    deflation may occur.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AER.MISC, FCOM PRO.AER.MISC, FCTM PRO.AER.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="efic">
    <title>Engine failure in cruise</title>

    <para>Engine out ceiling is highly dependent on weight; ISA deviation also has a modest
    effect. It will generally lie between FL180 and FL350.</para>

    <para>The first action will be to select both thrust levers to MCT so as to allow the autothrust
    its full engine out range. If the N1 gauges indicate a thrust margin exists, then the aircraft
    is below engine out ceiling; descent may be appropriate to increase the available thrust margin,
    but there is no immediate threat. If, however, the N1 gauges indicate that the autothrust is
    commanding MCT, and the speed is still decaying, then the aircraft is above engine out ceiling
    and prompt execution of a drift down procedure is required.</para>

    <para>Drift down with autopilot engaged in OP DES is preferred. Engagement of this vertical mode
    normally results in the autothrust commanding idle thrust, which is not what is desired. Thus,
    having set the thrust lever to MCT, the autothrust is disconnected. The PROG page provides a REC
    MAX EO flight level to use as an altitude target. If the speed decay is modest, it may be
    possible to alert ATC before initiating the descent, but in-service events have shown that speed
    decay is often very rapid, requiring descent initiation to be prioritised.</para>

    <para>Once drift down has been initiated, a decision needs to be made about speed. If obstacles
    are a concern, the lowest drift down rate and highest ceiling are acheived at green dot. Airbus
    refers to drifting down at green dot as “Obstacle strategy”. Flying at green dot reduces the
    chance of the FADECs automatically relighting the failed engine as the engine will be
    windmilling more slowly. Therefore, if obstacles are not a concern, M.78/300kt is flown, a speed
    that will always fall within the stabilized windmill engine relight envelope; Airbus refers to
    this as “Standard Strategy”.</para>

    <para>If obstacles remain a problem, MCT and green dot speed can be maintained to give a shallow
    climbing profile. Once obstacles are no longer a problem, descend to LRC ceiling (use V/S if
    &lt;500 fpm descent rate), engage the autothrust and continue at LRC speed.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCTM PRO.AEP.ENG.EFDC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="se_circling">
    <title>Single engine circling</title>

    <para>It may not be possible to fly level in the standard circling
    configuration of CONF 3 gear down. This can be ascertained by checking the table in QRH AEP.MISC
    One Engine Inoperative – Circling Approach. If affected, plan a FLAP 3 landing and delay gear
    extension until level flight is no longer required; a L/G NOT DOWN warning which will occur if
    circling below 750ft (can be silenced with the EMER CANC pb) and a TOO LOW GEAR should be
    anticipated if below 500ft RA.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="bomb">
    <title>Bomb on board</title>

    <para>The primary aim is to get the aircraft on the ground and evacuated ASAP.</para>

    <para>The secondary aim is to prevent detonation of the device. This is achieved by preventing
    further increases in cabin altitude through the use of manual pressure control and by avoiding
    sharp manoeuvres and turbulence.</para>

    <para>The tertiary aim is to minimise the effect of any explosion. This is achieved by reducing
    the diff to 1 psi. The method is to set cabin vertical speed to zero using manual pressurisation
    control, then descend to an altitude 2500ft above cabin altitude. As further descent is
    required, cabin vertical speed should be adjusted to maintain the 1 psi diff for as long as
    possible. Automatic pressure control is then reinstated on approach. Low speeds reduce the
    damage from an explosion but increase the risk of a timed explosion occurring whilst airborne; a
    compromise needs to be found. The aircraft should be configured for landing as early as possible
    to avoid an explosion damaging landing systems.</para>

    <para>In the cabin, procedures are laid down for assessing the risks of moving the device and
    for moving the device to the LRBL at door 2R.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AER.80, FCOM PRO.AER.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="stall">
    <title>Stall recovery <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>

    <para>Aerofoil stall is always and only an angle of attack issue. It is not possible to directly
    prove an unstalled condition from attitude and airspeed data. The flight recorders from the
    December 2014 Air Asia accident recorded an angle of attack of 40 degrees (i.e. around 25
    degrees greater than critical angle) with both pitch and roll zero and speeds up to
    160kt. Importantly, it is perfectly possible to be fully stalled in the emergency configurations
    described in <xref linkend="unreliable-airspeed"/>. Identification of a fully stalled condition
    is thus largely dependent on identifying a high and uncontrollable descent rate that does not
    correlate with normal flight path expectations for the attitude and thrust applied.</para>

    <para>To recover from a fully stalled condition, the angle of attack of the aerofoils must be
    reduced to below critical. The generic stall recovery is therefore simply to pitch the nose down
    sufficiently to break the stall and level the wings. In normal operations, the velocity vector
    of the aircraft is around 3° below the centreline of the aircraft (i.e. an attitude of around 3°
    is required to fly level). In a stalled condition, the velocity vector may be 40° or more below
    the centreline of the aircraft. Thus the amount of pitch down required to recover a fully
    stalled aircraft can be 30° or more.</para>

    <para>The aircraft's thrust vector helps to accelerate the aircraft during the recovery, and
    increasing speed along the aircraft's centreline acts to reduce the stalled angle of
    attack. Thus, while thrust is not a primary means of recovery, it does help. Unfortunately,
    Airbus have determined that due to the pitch couple associated with underslung engines, there
    may be insufficient longitudinal control authority to pitch the aircraft sufficiently to recover
    from a stall if TOGA is selected. It may therefore be necessary to initially reduce thrust to
    allow the primary recovery technique to be applied; this is extremely counterintuitive.</para>

    <para>In the two recent Airbus accidents involving stalls, the lack of physical cross coupling
    of sidesticks was a major factor. If one pilot elects to hold full back sidestick, the aircraft
    cannot be recovered by the other pilot unless the takeover pushbutton is used. With all the
    alarms, it is easy to miss “Dual Input”.</para>

    <para>Once there are no longer any indications of the stall, smoothly recover from the dive,
    adjust thrust, check speedbrakes retracted and if appropriate (clean and below 20,000ft) deploy
    the slats by selecting flaps 1. The load factor associated with an overly aggressive pull out
    can induce a secondary stall; on the flip side, once reattachment of the airflow occurs, drag
    rapidly diminishes and exceedance of high speed airframe limitations becomes a threat.</para>

    <para>If a stall warner sounds on takeoff it is likely to be spurious since you are almost
    certainly in normal law. The procedure in this case is essentially to initially assume
    unreliable airspeed and fly TOGA, 15°, wings level until it can be confirmed that the warning is
    spurious.</para>

    <para>A stall warning may occur at high altitude to indicate that the aircraft is reaching
    &alpha;<subscript>buffet</subscript>. In this case simply reduce the back pressure on the
    sidestick and/or reduce bank angle.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.AER.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="computer-reset">
    <title>Computer reset</title>

    <para>Abnormal computer behaviour can often be stopped by interrupting the power supply of the
    affected computer. This can be done either with cockpit controls or with circuit breakers. The
    general procedure is to interrupt the power supply, wait 3 seconds (5 seconds if a C/B was
    used), restore the power, then wait another three seconds for the reset to
    complete. QRH AER.SYSTEM RESET details the specific procedures for a variety of systems.</para>

    <para>On the ground, almost all computers can be reset. MOC can usually supply a reset procedure
    if nothing applicable is available in the QRH. The exceptions are the ECU and EIU while the
    associated engine is running and the BSCU when the aircraft is not stopped.</para>

    <para>In flight, only the computers listed in the QRH should be considered for reset.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AER.SYSTEM RESET]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="landing-distance">
    <title>Landing distance calculations</title>

    <para>Many failures result in a longer than normal landing distance. The QRH inflight
    performance section has tables for calculating V<subscript>APP</subscript> and Reference Landing
    Distances for single failures. These reflect the performance achievable in a typical operational
    landing without margin. easyJet requires a factor of 1.15 to be applied to these
    distances.</para>

    <para>The EFB module provides both factored and unfactored landing distances, and also can
    calculate for multiple failures.</para>

    <para>The safety factor may be disregarded in exceptional circumstances.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH IFP, FCOM PER.LDG, EOMB 4.14.2]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="abn-valphaprot">
    <title>Abnormal V Alpha Prot</title>
    <para>If two or more angle of attack vanes become blocked at the same angle during climb, alpha
    floor protection will be activated once a Mach number is reached where the angle of attack at
    which the vanes were blocked becomes indicitive of an incipient stall condition. Since the
    flight computer's attempts to reduce angle of attack will not be registered by the blocked
    vanes, a continuous nose down pitch rate which cannot be stopped with sidestick inputs will
    result.</para>

    <para>Indications of the incipient condition are available from the Alpha Prot and Alpha max
    strips. If the Alpha Max strip (solid red) completely hides the Alpha Prot strip (black and
    amber) or the Alpha Prot strip moves rapidly by more than 30kt during flight manoeuvres with AP
    on and speed brakes retracted, blocked angle of attack vanes should be suspected.</para>

    <para>The solution is to force the flight computers into Alternate Law where the protection does
    not apply. This is most conventiently done by turning off any two ADRs. Once in Alternate Law,
    the stall warning strip (red and black) becomes available. Since this may be receiving data from
    a blocked angle of attack vane, erroneous presentation is possible.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[OEBPROC-48]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="overspeed">
    <title>Overspeed Recovery</title>

    <para>In general the response to an overspeed should be to deploy the speedbrake and monitor the
    thrust reduction actioned by the autothrust. Disconnection of the autopilot will not normally be
    required. If autothrust is not in use, the thrust levers will need to be manually
    retarded.</para>

    <para>It is possible that the autopilot will automatically disengage and high speed protection
    will activate, resulting in an automatic pitch up. In this case, smoothly adjust pitch attitude
    as required.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCTM PRO.AER.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="volcanic">
    <title>Volcanic Ash Encounter</title>

    <para>Volcanic ash clouds are usually extensive, so the quickest exit will be acheived by a 180°
    turn.</para>

    <para>Air quality may be affected, so crew oxygen masks should be donned with 100% oxygen to
    exclude fumes. Passenger oxygen may also need to be deployed.</para>

    <para>Be prepared to carry out the unreliable speed procedure as airspeed indications may be
    compromised.</para>

    <para>Disconnect the autothrust to prevent thrust variations. To minimise the impact on the
    engines, if conditions permit thrust should be reduced. Turn on all anti-ice and set pack flow
    to high in order to increase bleed demand and thus increase stall margin. Wing anti-ice should
    be turned off before restart in case of double engine flameout.</para>

    <para>If engine EGT limits are exceeded, consider precautionary engine shutdown with restart
    once clear of volcanic ash. Engine acceleration may be very slow during restart. Since
    compressor and turbine blades may have been eroded, avoid sudden thrust changes.</para>

    <para>Damage to the windshield may necessitate an autoland or landing with a sliding window
    open.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.MISC, FCOM PRO.AEP.MISC, FCTM PRO.AEP.MISC]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter id="aircon-press-vent">
  <title>Air conditioning, pressurisation and ventilation</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Cabin overpressure</title>

    <para>There is no ECAM in the case of total loss of pressure control leading to an overpressure,
    so apply the QRH procedure. The basic procedure is to reduce air inflow by turning off one of
    the packs and put the avionics ventilation system in its smoke removal configuration so that it
    dumps cabin air overboard. The ΔP is monitored, and the remaining pack is turned off if it
    exceeds 9 psi. 10 minutes before landing, both packs are turned off and remain off, and the
    avionics ventilation is returned to its normal configuration.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.CAB PR, FCOM PRO.AEP.CAB PR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Excess cabin altitude</title>

    <para>An ECAM warning of excess (>9550ft) cabin altitude should be relied upon, even if not
    backed up by other indications.</para>

    <para>The initial response should be to protect yourself by getting an oxygen mask on. Initiate
    a descent; if above FL160, this should be according to <xref linkend="emerg-descent"/>. Once the
    descent is established and all relevant checklists are complete, check the position of the
    outflow valve and, if it is not fully closed, use manual control to close it.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">CAB PR</emphasis> EXCESS CAB ALT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.CAB PR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="ldg-elev-fault">
    <title>Landing Elevation Fault</title>

    <para>If the landing field elevation is not available from the FMGS, the landing elevation must
    be manually selected. This is done by pulling out and turning the LDG ELEV knob. The scale on
    the knob is only a rough indication; use the LDG ELEV displayed on either the CRUISE page or the
    CAB PRESS SD page instead.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">CAB PR</emphasis> LDG ELEV FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.CAB PR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="pack-fault">
    <title>Pack fault</title>

    <para>The PACK FAULT ECAM indicates that the pack valve position disagrees with the selected
    position or that the pack valve is closed. The affected pack should be turned off. A possible
    reason for this failure is loss of both channels of an Air Conditioning System Controller
    (ACSC). If this occurs, the associated hot air trimming will also be lost (cockpit for ACSC 1,
    cabin for ACSC 2).</para>

    <para>If there are simultaneous faults with both packs, ram air must be used. This will
    necessitate depressurisation of the aircraft, so a descent to FL100 (or MEA if higher) is
    required. If a PACK button FAULT light subsequently extinguishes, an attempt should be made to
    reinstate that pack.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AIR</emphasis> PACK 1(2)(1+2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AIR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Pack overheat</title>

    <para>The associated pack flow control valve closes automatically in the event of a pack
    overheating (outlet temp > 260°C or outlet temp > 230°C four times in one flight). The remaining
    pack will automatically go to high flow, and is capable of supplying all of the air conditioning
    requirement. This system’s automatic response is backed up by turning off the pack. The FAULT
    light in the PACK button remains illuminated whilst the overheat condition exists. The pack can
    be turned back on once it has cooled.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AIR</emphasis> PACK 1(2) OVHT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AIR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Pack off</title>

    <para>A warning is generated if a functional pack is selected off in a phase of flight when it
    would be expected to be on. This is usually the result of neglecting to re-instate the packs
    after a packs off takeoff. Unless there is a reason not to, turn the affected pack(s) on.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AIR</emphasis> PACK 1(2) OFF,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AIR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Pack regulator faults</title>

    <para>A regulator fault is defined as a failure of one of four devices: the bypass valve, the
    ram air inlet, the compressor outlet temperature sensor or the flow control valve. The ECAM
    bleed page can be used to determine which device is at fault.</para>

    <para>Regardless of the device at fault, the ramification is the same; the pack will continue to
    operate but there may be a degradation in temperature regulation. If temperatures become
    uncomfortable, consideration should be given to turning off the affected pack.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AIR</emphasis> PACK 1(2) REGUL FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AIR]</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>ACSC single lane failure</title>

    <para>Each ACSC has two fully redundant “lanes”, so loss of a single “lane” results in loss of
    redundancy only.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AIR</emphasis> COND CTL 1(2) A(B) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AIR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Duct overheat</title>

    <para>A duct overheat is defined as a duct reaching 88°C or a duct reaching 80°C four times in
    one flight. If this occurs, the hot air pressure regulating valve and trim air valves close
    automatically and the FAULT light illuminates in the HOT AIR button. This light will extinguish
    when the temperature drops to 70°C.</para>

    <para>Once the duct has cooled, an attempt can be made to recover the hot air system by cycling
    the HOT AIR button. If recovery is not possible, basic temperature regulation will continue to
    be provided by the packs.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">
    COND</emphasis> FWD CAB/AFT CAB/CKPT DUCT OVHT, FCOM PRO.AEP.COND]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Hot air fault</title>

    <para>If the hot air pressure regulating valve is not in its commanded position, the effects
    will depend on its actual position. If it is closed when commanded open, the packs will provide
    basic temperature regulation. More serious is if it has been commanded closed in response to a
    duct overheat and it fails to close. Manual control may be effective, but if it is not the only
    option is to turn off both packs and proceed as per <xref linkend="pack-fault"/>.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">COND</emphasis> HOT AIR FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.COND]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Trim air faults</title>

    <para>Either a fault with one of the trim air valves or an overpressure downstream of the hot
    air valve. An associated message indicates which condition exists.</para>

    <para>Failure of a trim valve leads to loss of optimised temperature regulation for the
    corresponding zone; basic temperature regulation is still available.</para>

    <para>The TRIM AIR HIGH PR message may be disregarded if triggered when all the trim air valves
    are closed. This occurs during the first 30 seconds after the packs are selected on and in
    flight if all zone heating demands are fulfilled.<footnote><para>The FCOM is not very
    informative regarding response to overpressure when this does not apply. However the MEL
    operating procedures for dispatch with this condition indicate that turning the HOT AIR pb-sw
    off is probably a good idea.</para></footnote></para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">COND</emphasis> TRIM AIR SYS FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.COND]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Cabin fan faults</title>

    <para>If both cabin fans fail, their flow should be replaced by increasing the pack flow to
    HI.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">COND</emphasis> L + R CAB FAN FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.COND]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Lavatory and galley fan faults</title>

    <para>The cabin zone temperature sensors are normally ventilated by air extracted by these
    fans. Loss of the fans therefore leads to loss of accurate zone temperature indication.</para>

    <para>On older aircraft, temperature control reverts to maintenance of a fixed cabin zone inlet
    duct temperature of 15°C.</para>

    <para>On newer aircraft the temperature controls for the cabin revert to controlling temperature
    in the ducts. If ACSC 2 has also failed, the duct temperatures are maintained at the same level
    as the cockpit duct temperature, and may therefore be controlled with the cockpit temperature
    selector.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">COND</emphasis> LAV + GALLEY FAN FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.COND]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="pressure-controller">
    <title>Pressure controller faults</title>

    <para>Loss of a single cabin pressure controller leads to loss of redundancy only.</para>

    <para>If both pressure controllers are lost, use manual control. The outflow valve reacts slowly
    in manual mode, and it may be 10 seconds before positive control of the outflow valve can be
    verified. It may also react too slowly to prevent a temporary depressurisation.</para>

    <para>Manual pressurisation control is activated by pressing the MODE SEL button. This allows
    the MAN V/S CTL toggle switch to directly control the outflow valve. Moving the toggle to DN
    closes the outflow valve causing the cabin altitude to descend, whilst moving the toggle to UP
    opens the outflow valve causing the cabin altitude to climb. The target climb and descent rates
    are 500fpm and 300fpm, these being displayed on the status page for easy reference.</para>

    <para>A table of FL versus ‘CAB ALT TGT’ is also provided on the status page; no guidance is
    given for the interpretation of this table. The final action of the procedure is to fully open
    the outflow valve when 2500ft QFE in preparation for an unpressurised landing, so to avoid large
    pressurisation changes during this action, the final cabin altitude target needs to be aerodrome
    elevation plus 2500ft . This gives an indication of how ‘CAB ALT TGT’ should be interpreted: it
    is the lowest cabin altitude that results in a safe &#x394;P at a given FL. A cabin altitude
    greater then ‘CAB ALT TGT’ is always acceptable<footnote><para>A reasonable maximum cabin
    altitude is 8800ft, which is when the CAB ALTITUDE advisory triggers.</para></footnote> and,
    moreover, for the final stages of the approach, it is necessary. The method is therefore to
    avoid cabin altitudes below ‘CAB ALT TGT’ for your actual FL while ensuring that a cabin
    altitude of aerodrome elevation plus 2500ft will be achieved by the time you need to fully open
    the outflow valve.</para>

    <para>Ensure cabin diff pressure is zero before attempting to open the doors.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">CAB PR</emphasis> SYS 1(2)(1+2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.CAB PR]</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Low diff pressure</title>

    <para>High rates of descent may lead to the aircraft descending through the cabin altitude when
    more than 3000ft above the landing altitude. An ECAM warning indicates that this situation is
    projected to occur within the next 1½ minutes. If the rate of descent of the aircraft is not
    reduced, the pressure controllers will have to resort to high rates of change of cabin altitude,
    which may cause passenger discomfort. The aircraft’s vertical speed should be reduced unless
    there is a pressing reason not to.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">CAB PR</emphasis> LO DIFF PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.CAB PR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Outflow valve closed on ground</title>

    <para>If the outflow valve fails to automatically open on the ground, manual control should be
    attempted. If that doesn’t work, depressurise the aircraft by turning off both packs.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">CAB PR</emphasis> OFV NOT OPEN,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.CAB PR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Open safety valve</title>

    <para>There are safety valves for both cabin overpressure and negative differential pressure;
    the associated ECAM message does not distinguish between the two.</para>

    <para>If diff pressure is above 8psi, it is the overpressure valve that has opened. Attempt
    manual pressurisation control and if that fails, reduce aircraft altitude.</para>

    <para>If diff pressure is below zero, it is the negative differential valve. Reduce aircraft
    vertical speed or expect high cabin rates.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">CAB PR</emphasis> SAFETY VALVE OPEN,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.CAB PR]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Blower fault</title>

    <para>Defined as low blowing pressure or duct overheat. Unless there is a DC ESS Bus fault, the
    blower fan should be set to OVRD. This puts the avionics ventilation into closed configuration
    and adds cooling air from the air conditioning system.<!-- {TODO:investigate --> <!--
    involvement of DC ESS BUS fault} --></para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">VENT</emphasis> BLOWER FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.VENT]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Extract fault</title>

    <para>Defined as low extract pressure. The extract fan should be put in OVRD. This puts the
    avionics ventilation into closed configuration and adds cooling air from the air conditioning
    system.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">VENT</emphasis> EXTRACT FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.VENT]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Skin valve fault</title>

    <para>Defined as one of three faults: the inlet valve is not fully closed in flight, the extract
    valve is fully open in flight or the extract valve did not automatically close on application of
    take-off power. The ECAM Cab Press page will differentiate.</para>

    <para>If the fault is with the inlet valve, no action is required since it incorporates a
    non-return valve.</para>

    <para>If the extract valve is affected, the system should be put into smoke configuration; this
    sends additional close signals to the extract valve. If this fails, the aircraft must be
    depressurised<!-- {TODO: find out why} -->.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">VENT</emphasis> SKIN VALVE FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.VENT]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Avionics ventilation system fault</title>

    <para>Defined as either a valve not in its commanded position or the Avionics Equipment
    Ventilation Controller (AEVC) being either unpowered or failing its power-up test. The system
    will automatically default to a safe configuration similar to smoke configuration. No crew
    action is required.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">VENT</emphasis> AVNCS SYS FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.VENT]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Electrical</title>

  <sect1 id="emerg-elec-config">
    <title>Emergency configuration</title>

    <para>Attempt to restore normal power by recycling the main generators. If that fails, try again
    after splitting the systems with the BUS TIE button.</para>

    <para>If normal power cannot be restored, ensure that the emergency generator is on line (deploy
    the RAT manually if required) and maintain speed &gt;140kt to avoid RAT stall. Cycling FAC 1
    will recover rudder trim. Once 45 seconds have elapsed and when below FL250, the APU can be
    started.</para>

    <para>So much equipment is lost in the emergency configuration that QRH AEP.ELEC provides a
    table of surviving equipment. Notable losses are all the fuel pumps (so ignition on, avoid
    negative G, center tank fuel is unusable), the anti-skid and three fifths of the
    spoilers. Landing speeds and distances are increased significantly.</para>

    <para>QRH AEP.ELEC also provides a paper summary which should be applied once ECAM actions are
    complete.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> EMER CONFIG, QRH AEP.ELEC,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Battery only</title>

    <para>Power is available for approximately 30 minutes.<footnote><para>This information was part
    of Airbus CBT training. There is no figure available in the FCOM.</para></footnote> QRH AEP.ELEC
    provides details of remaining equipment. This is very similar to the emergency electrical
    configuration (see <xref linkend="emerg-elec-config"/>) with the additional loss of FAC1 and
    FMGC1. An attempt should be made to bring the emergency generator on line by ensuring speed is
    &gt;140kt and deploying the RAT with the EMER ELEC PWR MAN ON button.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> ESS BUSES ON BAT,
    QRH AEP.ELEC, FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>IDG low oil pressure/ high oil temperature</title>

    <para>The IDG should be disconnected. Assuming the associated engine is running, press the IDG
    button until the GEN FAULT light comes on. Do not press the button for more than 3
    seconds.</para>

    <para>The APU generator should be used if available.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> IDG 1(2) OIL LO PR/OVHT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Generator fault</title>

    <para>Try to reset the generator by turning it off, then after a short pause, turning it on
    again. If unsuccessful, turn it back off.</para>

    <para>If an engine driven generator cannot be recovered, the APU generator should be used if
    available.</para>

    <para>Single generator operation leads to shedding of the galley. Loss of an engine driven
    generator leads to loss of CAT III DUAL capability.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis>(APU) GEN (1)(2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Battery fault</title>

    <para>The affected battery contactor opens automatically. APU battery start is unavailable with
    a single battery.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> BAT 1(2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>AC Bus 1 fault</title>

    <para>Some or all of the equipment on AC bus 1 becomes unavailable, including TR1. DC Bus 2 is
    powered from DC Bus 1 via the battery bus. Power must be re-routed to the Essential AC bus via
    AC bus 2. This is automatic on some aircraft. Manual re-routing is achieved with the AC ESS FEED
    button. Once Essential AC is powered, the Essential TR powers the DC Essential bus.</para>

    <para>Notable lost equipment includes the blue hydraulic system and associated services
    (including spoiler 3), radio altimeter 1 (and hence Cat III capability), half the fuel pumps,
    the nose wheel steering, the avionics blower fan and p1 windshield heat.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> AC BUS 1 FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>AC Bus 2 fault</title>

    <para>Some or all of the equipment on AC bus 2 becomes unavailable, including TR2. DC bus 2 is
    powered from DC bus 1 via the battery bus. The majority of this equipment has a redundant
    backup, the loss of the FO’s PFD and ND and a downgrade to Cat I being the major issue. Landing
    distances are unchanged.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> AC BUS 2 FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>AC Ess Bus fault</title>

    <para>It may be possible to recover the bus by transferring its power source to AC BUS 2 with
    the AC ESS FEED button. If this is unsuccessful, some or all of the equipment on the AC ESS bus
    will be lost. The majority of this equipment has a redundant backup, with the loss of the
    Captain’s PFD and ND and a downgrade to Cat I being the major issues. Landing distances are
    unchanged.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> AC ESS BUS FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>AC Essential Shed Bus lost</title>

    <para> Some or all of the equipment on the AC ESS SHED bus is lost. The major issue is the loss
    of the passenger oxygen masks. Landing distances are unchanged.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> AC ESS BUS SHED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>DC Bus 1 fault</title>

    <para>Some or all of the equipment on DC Bus 1 is lost. Most of the equipment loss causes loss
    of redundancy only. Landing distances are unchanged.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> DC BUS 1 FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>DC Bus 2 fault</title>

    <para>Some or all of the equipment on DC Bus 2 is lost. The F/O’s static probe sensor is lost,
    so ADR3 should be selected on the F/O’s side. FCU2 is lost, so check that the baro ref on the
    FCU and PFD agree. Landing distance increases by up to 35% due to the loss of 3 ground spoilers
    per side and one reverser. Autobrake is also unavailable. Due to the loss of SFCC2, the slats
    and flaps will be slow and the engines will remain in approach idle. FAC2 is lost, so the
    characteristic speeds on both PFDs are provided by FAC1. F/O window heat, wipers and rain
    repellent are lost.</para>

    <para>The other lost systems either have redundant backups or are non-essential. It should be
    noted that the only flight computers remaining are ELAC 1, SEC 1 and FAC 1.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> DC BUS 2 FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="dc-ess">
    <title>DC Essential Bus fault</title>

    <para> The major headache associated with DC Essential Bus failure is significant loss of
    communications systems. This is exacerbated by a design flaw which, at time of writing, affects
    MSNs 2037–2402 and MSNs 2471–3122. By design, ACP1 and ACP2 are lost, along with VHF1. This
    allows two-way communication to be recovered by one pilot using ACP3 (selected via the AUDIO
    SWTG rotary selector) with VHF2 or VHF3. Since speaker 1 is also lost, having P2 handle the
    radios with speaker 2 at high volume is the only method of both pilots having awareness of ATC
    communications. On the MSNs detailed above, however, the audio cards connecting cockpit mikes
    and headsets are <emphasis>all</emphasis> powered from the DC Essential Bus. It may be possible
    to receive transmissions with a combination of VHF2/3, ACP3 on FO and speaker 2 on, but
    transmission is limited to morse code on the transmit switch<footnote><para>I am only inferring
    this solution from the list of equipment lost; there is no specific documentation to indicate
    that it will work.</para></footnote>.</para>

    <para>FCU1 is lost, so the baro refs should be checked. The GPWS is lost and should be turned
    off.</para>

    <para>Landing distances are increased due to the loss of reverser 2 and the loss of the blue
    hydraulic system (and hence spoiler 3). Wing anti-ice is also lost, so landing distances will
    also increase significantly if ice is accreted and increased approach speeds are
    required.</para>

    <para>Slats and flaps are slow due to the loss of SFCC1. This also leads to the engines
    reverting to approach idle.</para>

    <para>Landing capability is Cat 2 due to the loss of the auto-thrust. The ECAM status page
    incorrectly reports Cat 3 single.</para>

    <para>The FCOM lists additional systems beyond those listed on the STATUS page that are lost
    with DC Essential Bus failure. Of note among these is loss of HP fuel shutoff valves. This
    requires that the engines are shut down with the Engine Fire pushbutton switches.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> DC ESS BUS FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>DC Essential shed</title>

    <para>The only major issue is the loss of wing anti-ice. Therefore, avoid icing conditions, and
    apply landing distance procedure if ice accretes.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> DC ESS BUS SHED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="dc-1and2">
    <title>Loss of DC Bus 1 and DC Bus 2</title>

    <para>Some or all of the systems supplied by DC Bus 1 and DC Bus 2 are lost.</para>

    <para>The implications are the same as for <xref
    linkend="dc-emerg-conf"/> except that the RAT will not need to be deployed since ESS TR will be
    supplied from AC 1 instead of the emergency generator.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> DC BUS 1+2 FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Generator overload</title>

    <para>Shed some load by switching off the galleys.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> GEN 1(2) OVERLOAD, <emphasis
    role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> APU GEN OVERLOAD, FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="loss-of-trs">
    <title>Loss of TRs</title>

    <para>No systems are lost as a result of failure of a single TR. If the
    fault is with TR1 or TR2, DC ESS will be supplied by the ESS TR via AC ESS; in this case only
    Cat 3 single will be available.</para>

    <para>If TR1 and TR2 are both lost then DC Bus 1, DC Bus 2 and the DC
    Battery Bus will also be lost. DC ESS will remain powered by the ESS TR. The FCOM is not very
    forthcoming regarding this failure; there is only a description in the DSC section and nothing
    specific in the PRO section. The situation is, however, very similar to the “ECAM complete”
    phase of <xref linkend="dc-emerg-conf"/>; the only difference is that AC 1 rather than the
    emergency generator is providing the power to the ESS TR, and hence you don't need to worry
    about RAT deployment or RAT stall.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> TR 1(2), <emphasis
    role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> ESS TR FAULT, FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="dc-bat">
    <title>Battery bus fault</title>

    <para>Some or all of the equipment on the Battery bus is lost. The only major items lost are APU
    fire detection and APU battery start.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> DC BAT BUS FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="dc-emerg-conf">
    <title>DC Emergency configuration</title>

    <para>Defined as the loss of DC BUSSES 1 + 2, DC ESS BUS and DC BAT BUS. Recovery assumes that
    the DC ESS BUS can be fully restored by deploying the RAT with the EMER ELEC PWR button.</para>

    <para>Equipment powered or controlled through DC BUS 1, DC BUS 2 and the
    BAT BUS is lost. Loss of the equipment associated with the BAT BUS is fairly benign: mainly APU
    Battery Start is unavailable due to loss of the APU ECB and APU fire detection is inop. A lot of
    equipment is lost with the loss of DC BUS 1+2, but it is worth remembering that all three busses
    are also lost in Emergency Electrical Config, so you will have, at minimum, all the equipment
    detailed in QRH 24.1. The main items of note are:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>A long runway is required. Minimum V<subscript>APP</subscript> is 140kt to
      prevent RAT stall. Antiskid, reversers and 60% of the spoilers are lost. Loss of nosewheel
      steering adds to the difficulty. Braking is from the ABCU, so only manual braking is
      available.<footnote><para>easyJet aircraft automatically modulate to 1000psi, but the sim may
      not.</para></footnote></para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Flight computer redundancy is significantly reduced, with only ELAC 1, SEC 1
      and FAC 1 available. This is, however, sufficient to keep Normal Law, so a CONF FULL landing
      and, indeed, CAT 3 SINGLE autoland (using AP1 and FMGS1) are available. The latter may be
      useful since wipers and window heat are lost. Only FCU 1 is available.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Deployment of lift devices is slow due do loss of SFCC 2, but they are all
      available. Normal gear operation is available through LGCIU 1.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Pressurised fuel is available from the #1 wing tank pumps, but center tank
      fuel is unusable.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Redundancy in the pressurisation system is seriously compromised. Manual
      pressure control and CPC 2 are lost, so you are reliant on CPC 1 for control. Pack 2, BMC 2
      and cross bleed control are all lost, so you are reliant on ENG 1 Bleed and Pack 1 for
      supply. Ram Air remains available, so if required a slow depressurisation through turning off
      Pack 1 followed by a depressurised landing with Ram Air is achievable.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Communications are limited to VHF 1, controlled by RMP 1.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Redundancy in the fire detection and suppression systems is compromised. The
      engines each retain one detection loop and one fire bottle. APU fire detection and cargo fire
      extinguishing are lost.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Heating for all static ports is lost, so be alert for unreliable airspeed and
      altitude.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> DC EMER CONFIG,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Static inverter fault</title>

    <para>Normal operations are not affected.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> STAT INV FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="gen1-line-off">
    <title>Generator 1 line off</title>

    <para>Pressing the GEN 1 LINE button on the emergency electrical panel has much the same effect
    as pressing the GEN 1 button on the main electrical panel, with the difference that GEN 1
    continues to supply its associated fuel pumps. It is primarily used for the smoke drill. If it's
    not meant to be off, turn it on.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ELEC</emphasis> EMER GEN 1 LINE OFF,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Tripped circuit breakers</title>

    <para>It is generally not recommended to reset circuit breakers in flight. It is, however,
    acceptable to attempt a single reset if it is judged necessary for the safe continuation of the
    flight.</para>

    <para>On the ground, any circuit breakers other than those for the fuel pumps may be reset as
    long as the action is coordinated with MOC.</para>

    <para>The ECAM warning will be triggered if a green circuit breaker trips.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">C/B</emphasis> TRIPPED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ELEC]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Flight controls</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Elevator faults</title>

    <para>If a single elevator fails, the SECs use the remaining elevator to provide pitch control
    in alternate law (see <xref linkend="alternate-law"/>). In addition, speed brake should not be
    used and the autopilots are unserviceable.</para>

    <para>If both elevators fail, the only mechanism for pitch control available is manual pitch
    trim, so pitch reverts to mechanical back up and roll reverts to direct law. For the approach
    fly a long final, initiating the descent from at least 5000ft AAL. Do not try to flare using
    trim and do not remove power until after touchdown. From 1000ft AAL, try to keep power changes
    to within 2% N1. In the event of a go-around, power <emphasis>must</emphasis> be applied very
    slowly if control is not to be lost.<footnote><para>This is Boeing advice – Airbus does not
    provide guidance for the flare or go-around technique when elevators are
    frozen.</para></footnote></para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> L(R)(L+R) ELEV FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Stabilizer jam</title>

    <para>Manual pitch trim is a mechanical connection to the stabilizer actuator. It may be
    possible to use manual pitch trim when the ELACs have detected a stabilizer jam, although it may
    be heavier than normal. If it is usable, trim for neutral elevators.</para>

    <para>The flight controls will revert to Alternate Law. If the stabilizer could not be moved,
    gear extension should be delayed until CONF 3 and V<subscript>APP</subscript> are achieved so
    that the elevators are properly trimmed.</para>

    <para>If the jam is caused by the mechanical connection, it is possible that the ELACs will not
    detect the problem. The procedure in this case is similar, but Normal Law will remain.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> STABILIZER JAM,
    QRH AEP.F/CTL, FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Aileron faults</title>

    <para>The lateral aircraft handling is not adversely affected even if both ailerons fail, as the
    systems compensate by using the spoilers. Fuel consumption will, however, increase by
    approximately 6%.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> L(R) AIL FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="spoiler-faults" >
    <title>Spoiler faults</title>

    <para>The effect of a spoiler fault depends on whether the spoiler fails retracted or
    extended.</para>

    <para>If the spoiler fails in the retracted position, handling should not be adversely
    affected. A CONF 3 landing may reduce any buffeting that is encountered. Speed brake should not
    be used if spoilers 3 + 4 are affected. The loss of ground spoilers will significantly increase
    landing distances.</para>

    <para>Airbus have identified a failure scenario that leads to high pressure hydraulic fluid
    reaching the extend chamber of a spoiler actuator via a failed o-ring. This has the effect of a
    spoiler failing in the fully extended position. In this case, the autopilot does not necessarily
    have sufficient authority to control the aircraft, and it should be disconnected. Fuel burn will
    increase significantly; FMGC fuel predictions do not account for the failure and should be
    disregarded. Green dot speed will minimize this increased fuel burn, but may not be viable if
    there is excessive buffet – attempt to find a compromise speed. Landing will be flap 3;
    V<subscript>APP</subscript> and LDG DIST factors are available in QRH IFP.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> (GND) SPLR (1+2)(3+4) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Rudder Jam</title>

    <para>The main indication of jammed rudder is undue and adverse pedal movement during rolling
    manoeuvres caused by the yaw damper orders being fed back to the pedals when they are no longer
    sent to the rudder.</para>

    <para>Crosswinds from the side that the rudder is deflected should be avoided, and a cross wind
    limit of 15kt applies. Control on the ground will require differential braking until the
    steering handle can be used (below 70kt), so landing distances are increased. Do not use
    autobrake.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> RUDDER JAM, QRH_AEP.F/CTL,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="flight-controls.slats-flaps-fault">
    <title>Flaps and/or slats fault/locked</title>

    <para>The most pressing concern following a flap or slat problem is to establish a max operating
    speed that will avoid overspeeding the device in its locked position. A table is provided on
    page AEP.F/CTL “Landing with Slats or Flaps Jammed” of the QRH for this purpose,
    but a quick estimation can be made by establishing
    what flap lever position would be required to get the device into its current position and using
    V<subscript>FE</subscript> for the configuration associated with that flap lever position as
    V<subscript>MO</subscript>. In doing this, it must be remembered that slat deployment in CONF 2
    and CONF 3 is the same (tip: think of available slat positions as being 0, 1, Intermediate or
    Full). This also affects use of the QRH table; the second dot on the slat indicator on the E/WD
    should be considered slat 3 for the purpose of this table, not slat 2 as might be expected. The
    barber’s pole displayed for V<subscript>FE</subscript> on the PFD is a function of the flap
    lever position, so it may be worth initially selecting the flap lever to the matching CONF to
    have this reference available. For minimum speeds, the V<subscript>LS</subscript> displayed on
    the PFD is calculated from actual flap and slat position and can be trusted.</para>

    <para>Unless there is an obvious reason not to (e.g. wing tip brake on, alignment fault or fault
    due to dual hydraulic failure), the flap lever can be recycled.</para>

    <para>If normal operation cannot be restored, there are two major issues that must be quickly
    addressed. Firstly, fuel burn will be dramatically higher when flying with a locked device. With
    slats extended, fuel burn will increase by 60%. With flaps extended it will increase by
    80%. With slats and flaps extended, fuel burn will double. These figures are available in
    QRH OPS. The second issue is that landing distances are significantly increased, in the
    worst case by a factor of 2.2. It may be that the combination of these factors requires a fairly
    prompt diversion decision.</para>

    <para>The flap and slat systems are largely independent, so the flap lever will continue to move
    the slats if the flaps are locked and vice versa. In general, flap 3 should be selected for
    landing. There are two exceptions. If flaps are locked at &gt;3, flap full should be used. If
    both slats and flaps are locked at 0, flap 1 should be used so that the AP/FD go-around is
    armed. Configurations and V<subscript>REF</subscript> increments are available on page
    IFP.LDwSFSF of the QRH. If a flapless and slatless landing is required, the threshold speed may
    be below V<subscript>LS</subscript>. This is necessary as the landing speeds in this
    configuration are very close to tyre limit speeds.</para>

    <para>During configuration, V<subscript>LS</subscript> is computed from actual configuration and
    V<subscript>FE next</subscript> is computed from flap lever position. F and S speeds are
    essentially meaningless.</para>

    <para>The recommended deployment method is to select speed to 5kt below
    V<subscript>FE next</subscript> then select the next configuration as the speed reduces through
    V<subscript>FE next</subscript>. To prevent overspeeds in case of turbulence, it is acceptable
    to configure at lower speeds as long as speed remains above V<subscript>LS</subscript>. If
    V<subscript>LS</subscript>&gt;V<subscript>FE next</subscript>, prioritise
    V<subscript>LS</subscript>: fly V<subscript>LS</subscript>, select the next configuration, then
    track V<subscript>LS</subscript> as it reduces with the extension of the lift device. Use of
    autothrust with selected speed is generally recommended for all phases of the approach, but in
    this case it will need to be temporarily disconnected until landing configuration is
    established.</para>

    <para>It is worth noting that failure of the slat channels of both SFCCs appears to result in
    the loss of characteristic speed display on both PFDs. This is not mentioned in the FCOM but
    occurs in the sim. The upshot of this is that neither V<subscript>LS</subscript> nor
    V<subscript>SW</subscript> are available at all, since they are not displayed and there is no
    way to calculate them. This is of particular concern when trying to configure to flaps 2 since
    the aircraft must be slowed to V<subscript>FE(conf 2)</subscript> when still clean (remember
    conf 1 is slats only when configuring from conf 0). It is highly likely that the stall warner
    will activate during the transition, and if not anticipated, the subsequent recovery will
    overspeed the flaps. The solution is to brief that speed will be reduced very slowly and if the
    stall warning occurs the speed will be maintained whilst allowing the deployment of the flaps to
    recover the stall margin.</para>

    <para>The autopilot may be used down to 500ft AAL, but since it is not tuned for the abnormal
    configuration it must be closely monitored.</para>

    <para>For the go-around, initially maintain flap/ slat configuration. A speed 10kt lower than
    max operating speed should be flown. If it is the slats that are jammed or if the flaps are
    jammed at 0, clean configuration can be used to transit to a diversion airfield.</para>

    <para>Other issues include the possible loss of the automatic operation of the centre tank pumps
    (which is sequenced to the slats) and possible reversion to Alternate Law.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> FLAPS(SLATS) FAULT(LOCKED),
    QRH_AEP.F/CTL, FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>SFCC faults</title>

    <para>Each SFCC has fully independent slat and flap channels. A failure of a channel in a single
    controller will lead to slow operation of the associated surfaces. In addition, the flap channel
    of SFCC1 provides input to the idle control part of the FADECs and to the EGPWC.</para>

    <para>Failure of both flap channels or failure of both slat channels is covered in <xref
    linkend="flight-controls.slats-flaps-fault"/>. </para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> FLAP(SLAT) SYS 1(2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="flight-controls.elac">
    <title>ELAC fault</title>

    <para>In normal operations, ELAC 1 controls the ailerons and ELAC 2 controls the elevators and
    stabiliser. Failure of a single ELAC will result in failover to the remaining computer. Provided
    no uncommanded manoeuvres occurred, an attempt can be made to reset the failed ELAC.</para>

    <para>Failure of both ELACs leads to loss of ailerons and hence Alternate Law. One of the SECs
    will take over control of the elevators and stabiliser. Again, an attempt can be made to reset
    the computers.</para>

    <para>If the fault is designated a pitch fault, only the pitch function of the associated ELAC
    is lost.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> ELAC 1(2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>SEC fault</title>

    <para>Each SEC controls either 1 or 2 spoilers per wing. SEC 1 and 2 also provide back up for
    the ELACs (see <xref linkend="flight-controls.elac"/>). Loss of a SEC leads to loss of its
    associated spoilers. SEC 1 provides spoiler position to the FACs. If speedbrakes are deployed
    with SEC 1 u/s and SEC 3 operative, spoiler 2 will deploy without a corresponding increase in
    V<subscript>LS</subscript>. Therefore, do not use speedbrake if SEC 1 is affected (it won’t do
    much anyway!).</para>

    <para>Pairs of SECs also provide the signal for reverse thrust lever angle to the reversers and
    spoiler deployment to the autobrake. A dual SEC failure will therefore lead to a loss of a
    reverser and loss of autobraking.</para>

    <para>If all SECs are lost, all the above holds true. Furthermore the flight controls revert to
    Alternate Law due to the complete loss of spoilers. Also, due to routing of LGCIU data to the
    ELACs via the SECs, Direct Law will occur at slat extension rather than gear extension.</para>

    <para>An attempt should be made to reset the affected SEC(s).</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> SEC 1(2)(3) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>FCDC faults</title>

    <para>The two FCDCs are redundant, so a single failure has no immediate effect.</para>

    <para>If both FCDCs fail, the ELACs and SECs can no longer supply data to the EIS. The major
    effect of this is that F/CTL ECAM warnings are no longer generated. The warning lights on the
    overhead panel continue to give valid information and should be monitored. The aircraft remains
    in normal law with all protections, but protection indications (bank and pitch limits,
    V<subscript>&alpha;&#x2011;prot</subscript> and V<subscript>&alpha;&#x2011;max</subscript>) are
    not shown and the stall warning system becomes active.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> FCDC 1(2)(1+2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="direct-law">
    <title>Direct Law</title>

    <para>In Direct Law, deflection of the control surfaces is a linear function of deflection of
    the side-stick and trimming must be done manually. The controls are very sensitive at high
    speeds. Use of manual thrust is recommended as power changes will result in pitch
    changes. Similarly, use of the speed brake will result in nose up pitch changes so it should be
    used with care. Protections are unavailable, so speed is limited to 320kt/0.77M and care must be
    taken in GPWS or windshear manoeuvres. Approach speed is increased by 10kt and landing distances
    increase by a factor of 1.2.</para>

    <para>The major handling difficulty in direct law is the go-around. There
    is no compensation for the large pitch moment introduced by selecting TOGA power on the
    under-slung engines, the thrust levers are non-linear and the use of the manual pitch trim wheel
    will be unfamiliar. Apply power smoothly and progressively and anticipate a requirement for
    unusual side-stick inputs.</para>

    <para>Direct Law works with or without yaw dampers. The aircraft is
    <emphasis>always</emphasis> convergent in dutch roll, so use lateral control, not rudder, if
    dutch roll is experienced.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> DIRECT LAW,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="alternate-law">
    <title>Alternate Law</title>

    <para>In alternate law, pitch is as in normal law, but roll is as in direct law. Load factor
    protection is retained, but other protections are either replaced with static stability or are
    lost, depending on the nature of the failure. Stall warnings and overspeed warnings become
    active.</para>

    <para>The main effects are that speed is limited to 320kt and stall warnings must be respected
    when carrying out EGPWS manoeuvres.</para>

    <para>The autopilot may be available.</para>

    <para>Expect Direct Law after landing gear extension (see <xref linkend="direct-law"/>), and
    hence increased approach speeds and landing distances due to a CONF 3 landing (see
    QRH IFP.LDwFCSF).</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> ALTN LAW, ,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Wingtip brake fault</title>

    <para>The wingtip brakes activate in case of asymmetry, mechanism overspeed, symmetrical runaway
    or uncommanded movements. This protection is lost.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> FLAP(SLAT) TIP BRK FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Flap attach sensor failure</title>

    <para>The flap attach sensor detects excessive differential movement between the inner and outer
    flaps which would indicate failure of a flap attachment. This protection is lost.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> FLAP ATTACH SENSOR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Flight control servo faults</title>

    <para>All flight controls have redundant servos. In the case of an elevator servo fault, a
    restriction to not use speedbrake above V<subscript>MO</subscript>/M<subscript>MO</subscript>
    applies.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> AIL(ELEV) SERVO FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Speed brake disagree</title>

    <para>This indicates that the spoiler positions do not correspond with the speedbrake lever
    position. This may be as a result of automatic retraction (alpha floor activation or speed
    brakes deployed when full flap selected) or as a result of spoiler malfunction. In both cases
    retract the speedbrake lever and in the case of spoiler malfunction consider the speedbrakes
    unserviceable.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> SPD BRK DISAGREE,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Speed brake fault</title>

    <para>This indicates a failure of the speedbrake lever transducers rather than a problem with
    the spoilers. Ground spoiler activation may be expected on selection of reverse, so providing
    reversers are used, landing distances should not be affected.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">F/CTL</emphasis> SPD BRK (2)(3+4) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Stiff sidestick/ rudder pedals</title>

    <para>This may affect both sidesticks at the same time, but not the rudder pedals or it may
    affect the rudder pedals and one sidestick. Control forces will remain moderate and the aircraft
    remains responsive. Confirm autopilot disengagement and consider transferring control if one of
    the sidesticks is unaffected.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH_AEP.F/CTL, FCOM PRO.AEP.F/CTL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="sidestick-transducer">
    <title>Sidestick unannunciated transducer faults</title>

    <para>It is possible for a failed sidestick transducer to cause uncommanded control inputs. If
    no fault is detected, the result is that the aircraft behaves as if that input had actually been
    made. Generally, the autopilot will disconnect and any attempt to control the aircraft with the
    failed sidestick will fail. The aircraft should be recovered with the other sidestick using the
    takeover button. Keeping this button pressed for 40 seconds will lock out the failed sidestick,
    and the autopilot can then be re-engaged. The autopilot should not be disconnected in the normal
    manner as pressing the takeover button will re-introduce the failed sidestick and the
    uncommanded input; use the FCU instead.</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Fire</title>

  <sect1 id="smoke-fumes">
    <title>Smoke and fumes</title>

    <para>The QRH procedure should be applied when smoke is detected and the crew suspect the
    avionics, air conditioning or cabin equipment as the source. The paper procedure includes all
    the steps of the avionics smoke ECAM procedure, so if this caution is triggered, the paper
    procedure should be applied instead of the ECAM<footnote><para>There is an odd airframe
    dependency with this; on some airframes the instruction is to run the paper checklist at latest
    after completing the immediate actions of the Avionics Smoke ECAM, whilst on others it is when
    requested by the Avionics Smoke ECAM. Unfortunately the Avionics Smoke ECAM itself is not
    described in the FCOM. A general policy of running the paper procedure instead of the Avionics
    Smoke ECAM procedure seems to cover all eventualities.</para></footnote>. <phrase
   >The FCTM also adds that the AVIONICS SMOKE ECAM procedure should be applied
    only if the flight crew can confirm it visually or by smell, otherwise it should be considered
    spurious.</phrase></para>

    <para>In the case of other smoke related ECAMs, the relevant ECAM procedure should be applied
    first and then the use of the paper checklist considered.</para>

    <para>While the smoke aspect of these procedures is fairly unambiguous, the
    fumes aspect has led to both under- and over-reaction in the simulator. Training department
    guidance is that if a “smell” is detected in the cabin and it is having no physiological
    effects, no immediate action is required. If there are physiological effects, the
    SMOKE/FUMES/AVNCS SMOKE QRH procedure should be actioned. However, only the first line, LAND
    ASAP, is actioned since there is no perceptible smoke and the rest of the checklist is below the
    line “if perceptible smoke apply immediately”. Thus after cross-confirming LAND ASAP,
    immediately move on to the REMOVAL OF SMOKE/FUMES QRH checklist. It should be noted that
    confirmation of the correctness of this advice is currently being sought from Airbus, and that
    in a number of in-service events the source of the smell has been positively identified as one
    of the packs.</para>

    <para>Rain repellent fluid leaks are not covered. Orange peel smells are toxic, pine needle
    smells non-toxic.</para>

    <para>The SMOKE/ FUMES/ AVNCS SMOKE checklist attempts to isolate the source of the smoke. It is
    possible that it may become impossible to carry out this checklist due to smoke density. In this
    case, interrupt the checklist and carry out the smoke removal drill (see <xref
    linkend="smoke-fumes-removal"/>). It is also possible that the situation may deteriorate to a
    level that an immediate forced landing becomes the preferable option. In general, unless the
    source of the smoke is obvious and extinguishable, a diversion should be initiated
    immediately. The smoke removal drill is most effective and adaptable at lower levels, so a
    descent to 10,000ft or MSA is also a priority.</para>

    <para>The first priority is to protect yourself, so get an oxygen mask on. The mask must be set
    to 100% oxygen to exclude fumes; at minimum dispatch oxygen levels this will provide as little
    as 15 minutes of protection. Pushing the “Emergency pressure selector” knob will provide a few
    seconds of overpressure, which can be used to clear any smoke trapped in the mask as it was
    donned.</para>

    <para>Likely sources of smoke are the avionics, the cabin fans and the
    galleys. Smoke from these sources can be contained with simple and reversible actions which can
    be initiated immediately: put the avionics ventilation into smoke removal mode by selecting both
    blower and extract fans to OVRD, turn off the cabin fans and turn off the galleys.</para>

    <para>Where the source is immediately obvious, accessible and
    extinguishable, isolate the faulty equipment. Otherwise the QRH provides seperate drills for
    suspected air conditioning smoke, suspected cabin equipment smoke or suspected avionics/
    electrical smoke. In addition the avionics/ electrical smoke drill includes undetermined and
    continuing smoke sources.</para>

    <para>Suspect air conditioning smoke if it initially comes out of the ventilation
    outlets. Several ECAM warnings are also likely to occur as sensors detect the smoke in other
    areas. The displayed ECAM procedures must be applied. Following an engine or APU failure, smoke
    may initially enter the air conditioning system but should dissipate quickly once the failure is
    contained. The air conditioning drill starts by turning the APU bleed off in case this is the
    source. The packs are then turned off one at a time to determine if the source of the smoke is a
    pack.</para>

    <para>The cabin equipment smoke drill involves selecting the commercial button off and searching
    for faulty cabin equipment.</para>

    <para>Suspect avionics smoke if the only triggered ECAM is AVIONICS
    SMOKE. If an item of electrical equipment fails immediately prior to the appearance of the
    smoke, that equipment should be suspected as the source. The avionics/ electrical drill (which
    includes the undetermined source drill) reduces the amount of electrically powered equipment to
    a minimum by adopting a slightly modified emergency electrical configuration.<footnote><para>The
    EMER ELEC GEN 1 LINE button rather than the GEN 1 button is used to disconnect generator 1 which
    disconnects generator 1 from the electrical system but allows it to directly supply one fuel
    pump in each wing tank.</para></footnote> The resulting ECAM <emphasis>may
    </emphasis><footnote><para>Which ECAM procedure is displayed is dependent on whether an AVIONICS
    SMOKE ECAM has been triggered prior to the adoption of emergency electrical
    configuration.</para></footnote> contain instructions to reset the generators; these
    instructions should be disregarded, although the rest of the ECAM procedure must be
    actioned. The intention is to restore power 3 minutes before landing or at 2000ft aal. Since you
    will not be able to restore the two IRs that were depowered, the landing will be in Direct Law
    and hence CONF 3.<footnote><para>QRH AEP.ELEC ELEC EMER CONFIG Sys Remaining indicates that by
    selecting the ATT HDG selector to CAPT 3 it may be possible to retain IR3 and hence have
    sufficient equipment for a Cat 3A landing once power is restored. This has not yet been
    confirmed by Airbus.</para></footnote> This is not mentioned in QRH AEP.SMOKE SFAS, and is only
    mentioned on the ECAM once gear is extended.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AVIONICS</emphasis> SMOKE, QRH AEP.SMOKE,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.SMOKE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="smoke-fumes-removal">
    <title>Smoke/ fumes removal</title>

    <para>Smoke removal procedures initially use the pressurisation system to draw smoke and fumes
    overboard by increasing the cabin altitude. If there are no fuel vapours present, the packs are
    used to drive the smoke overboard. Otherwise it is driven overboard by residual pressure.</para>

    <para>The final target configuration is packs off, outflow valve fully open and ram air on. As
    this depressurises the aircraft, it can only be achieved at lower levels (preferably FL100). If
    in emergency configuration, turning the APU master switch on connects the batteries for a
    maximum of 3 minutes and allows manual control of the DC powered outflow valve motor. Once at a
    suitable level and below 200kt, as a last resort PNF’s cockpit window can be opened.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.SMOKE, FCOM PRO.AEP.SMOKE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="eng_fire">
    <title>Engine fire</title>

    <para>The basic sequence is to bring the thrust lever of the affected engine to idle, turn off
    its engine master, push its fire button, wait 10 seconds then deploy its first fire bottle. If
    the fire is not extinguished after 30 seconds, indicated by the fire button remaining lit,
    deploy the second bottle.</para>

    <para>This sequence is modified on the ground in that both fire bottles are fired immediately,
    and the remaining engine is then also shut down. Note that shutting down both engines without
    the APU running will leave only batteries, resulting in loss of all COMS except VHF1 and loss of
    ECAM reference for the final actions.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2) FIRE</emphasis>,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="lithium-battery-fire">
    <title>Lithium Battery Fire</title>

    <para>If there are flames, they should be attacked with a halon extinguisher. This will
    necessitate PF donning a crew oxygen mask and PNF donning the smoke hood.</para>

    <para>If there are no flames, or once the flames have been extinguished, the cabin crew should
    remove the device from the cockpit and store it in a lined container filled with water. If the
    device cannot be removed, water or non-alcoholic liquid should be poured on the device, and it
    should be continuously monitored for re-ignition.</para>

    <para>Note that these procedures assume that you are dealing with lithium ion batteries
    (i.e. rechargeable batteries found in laptops, tablets, phones etc.) where the amount of water
    reactive lithium metal is actually fairly low. Once the flames have been knocked down, the focus
    is on cooling to prevent thermal runaway in adjacent cells. Counter-intuitively, it is vital
    that ice is <emphasis>not</emphasis> used as this acts as a thermal insulator and will likely
    cause adjacent cells to explode. For the same reason, smothering with anything that might
    thermally insulate the battery pack (e.g. a fire bag) is probably a bad idea.</para>

    <para>If smoke becomes the biggest threat, see <xref linkend="smoke-fumes-removal"/>. If the
    situation becomes unmanageable, consider an immediate landing.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.SMOKE, FCOM PRO.AEP.SMOKE, FAA videos (available on youtube)]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Fuel</title>

  <sect1 id="fuel-leak">
    <title>Fuel leak</title>

    <para>Whenever a non-normal fuel event occurs, the possibility that the underlying cause of the
    event is a fuel leak should be considered. Only when a fuel leak has been categorically ruled
    out should the cross-feed valve be opened.</para>

    <para>The primary method used to detect fuel leaks is a regular check that actual fuel remaining
    corresponds to expected fuel remaining and that fuel used plus fuel remaining corresponds to
    fuel at engine start. The latter parameter is monitored on some aircraft and may trigger an ECAM
    warning. Other indications of a leak include fuel imbalance or excessive fuel flow from an
    engine. It also possible that a fuel leak may be detected visually or by a smell of fuel in the
    cabin.</para>

    <para>If a leak can be confirmed to be coming from an engine or pylon, the affected engine must
    be shut down. In this case, cross-feeding is allowable. Otherwise, the cross-feed must be kept
    closed.</para>

    <para>If the leak cannot be confirmed to be originating from an engine or pylon, an attempt
    should be made to identify the source of the leak by monitoring the inner tank depletion rates
    with the crossfeed valve closed and the center tank pumps off.</para>

    <para>If depletion rates are similar, a leak from the center tank or from the APU feeding line
    should be suspected. If there is a smell of fuel in the cabin, it is likely that the APU feeding
    line is at fault and the APU should be turned off. Fuel from the center tank should be used once
    one of the inner tanks has &lt;3000kg.<footnote><para>The logic here is strange. An unofficial
    explanation of the requirement for &lt;3000kg in the inner tank was given to me: some of the
    fuel lines from the center tank run through the wing tanks, so fuel from a center tank leak may
    end up transferring to the wing tanks and with full wing tanks might be lost overboard by
    venting the wing tank overflow. As for the APU feeding line leak, I would expect the left tank
    to decrease faster than the right in this case; my guess is that the expectation is that an APU
    feeding line leak will be detected as a smell in the cabin and the leak will be too small to
    become apparent as an imbalance.</para></footnote></para>

    <para>If, after 30 minutes, one tank has been depleted by 300kg more than the other, the
    location of leak is narrowed down to the engine or the wing on the more depleted side. To
    confirm which it is, shut down the engine.  If the leak then stops, an engine leak is confirmed
    and the cross feed can be used. If not, a leak from the wing is most likely. In this case, an
    engine restart should be considered.</para>

    <para>In an emergency, a landing may be carried out with maximum fuel imbalance.</para>

    <para>Do not use thrust reversers.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> F USED/FOB DISAGREE,
    QRH AEP.FUEL, FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Fuel imbalance</title>

    <para>All fuel balancing must be carried out in accordance with QRH AEP.FUEL “Fuel Imbalance”,
    paying particular attention to the possibility of a fuel leak. Any action should be delayed
    until sufficient time has passed for a fuel leak to become apparent. FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL adds a
    note not found in the QRH that “there is no requirement to correct an imbalance until the ECAM
    fuel advisory limit is displayed”, an event that occurs when one inner tank holds &gt;1500kg
    more than the other. The limitations for fuel imbalance in FCOM LIM.FUEL, however, show that the
    fuel advisory does not necessarily indicate that a limitation is likely to be breached. In
    particular, when the outer tanks are balanced and the heavier inner tank contains &le;2250kg,
    there are no imbalance limitations. Furthermore, the aircraft handling is not significantly
    impaired even at maximum imbalance. </para>

    <para>To balance the fuel, open the cross-feed valve and turn the lighter side pumps and the
    center tank pumps off.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.FUEL, FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL, FCOM LIM.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="gravity-feeding">
    <title>Gravity fuel feeding</title>

    <para>Turn on ignition in case of fuel interruption and avoid negative G. The ceiling at which
    fuel can be reliably gravity fed depends on whether the fuel has had time to deaerate. If the
    aircraft has been above FL300 for more than 30 minutes, the fuel may be considered deaerated and
    the current flight level maintained. Otherwise, the fuel must be considered aerated and the
    gravity feed ceiling is FL300 if the aircraft exceeded FL300 or FL150 if it didn’t. If gravity
    feeding is required, descend to the gravity feed ceiling.</para>

    <para>It is also possible to gravity cross feed by side slipping the aircraft with a bank angle
    of 2° to 3° should this become necessary.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.FUEL, FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Wing tank pump(s) low pressure</title>

    <para>Failed pumps should be turned off.</para>

    <para>Failure of a single pump in either tank results in reduced redundancy only.</para>

    <para>Failure of both pumps in a given tank means that the fuel in that tank is only available
    by gravity feeding. Pressurized fuel may be available from the center tank (use manual mode if
    necessary) or by cross-feeding. A descent to gravity feed ceiling may be required (see <xref
    linkend="gravity-feeding"/>).</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> L(R) TK PUMP 1(2)(1+2) LO PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Center tank pumps low pressure</title>

    <para>Failed pumps should be turned off.</para>

    <para>Failure of a single center tank pump results in a loss of redundancy. The crossfeed should
    be opened until the center tank fuel has been exhausted so that the remaining pump can supply
    both engines.</para>

    <para>Failure of both center tank pumps makes the fuel in the center tank unusable.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> CTR TK PUMP(S)(1(2)) LO PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Auto feed fault</title>

    <para>The center tank pumps must be managed manually. They must be switched off whenever slats
    are extended, wing tank fuel &gt;5000kg or center tank fuel is exhausted.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> AUTO FEED FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="low-fuel">
    <title>Low fuel level</title>

    <para>The ECAM is triggered at approximately 750kg. The warning may be spurious if the ECAM is
    triggered just before the wing cell transfer valves open. If center tank fuel remains, it should
    be used by selecting the center tank pumps to manual mode. If there is a fuel imbalance and a
    fuel leak can be ruled out, crossfeed fuel as required.</para>

    <para>If both tanks are low level, about 30 minutes of flying time remain.</para>

    <para>If any change to the current clearance will lead to landing with less than minimum reserve
    fuel, declare "minimum fuel" to ATC. This is just a heads up to ATC, not a declaration of an
    emergency situation. If it is calculated that less than minimum fuel will remain after landing,
    declare a MAYDAY.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis>(R)(L+R) WING TK LO LVL,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL, EOMA 8.3.8.2]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Outer tank transfer valves failed closed</title>

    <para>If both transfer valves fail to open when a wing tank reaches low level, the fuel in that
    outer tank becomes unusable. The fuel balance will remain within limits since maximum outer tank
    imbalances are acceptable if the total fuel in either wing is the same [FCOM LIM.FUEL].</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> L(R) XFR VALVE CLOSED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Outer tank transfer valve open out of sequence</title>

    <para>Maximum outer tank imbalances are acceptable if the total fuel in either wing is the same
    [FCOM LIM.FUEL], so no action is required.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> L(R) XFR VALVE OPEN,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Cross-feed valve fault</title>

    <para>If the valve has failed open, fuel balance can be maintained through selective use of fuel
    pumps. If it has failed closed, crossfeeding is unavailable.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> FEED VALVE FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Low fuel temperature</title>

    <para>ECAM is triggered at approx -43°C. If on the ground, delay takeoff until temperatures are
    within limits. If in flight, descending or increasing speed should be considered.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> L(R) OUTER(INNER) TK LO TEMP,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>High fuel temperature</title>

    <para>This ECAM is known to be triggered spuriously by interference from communication
    equipment. The procedure should only be applied if the message has not disappeared within 2
    minutes.</para>

    <para>The ECAM temperature triggers on the ground are 55°C for the outer cell and 45°C for the
    inner cell. In the air they are 60°C for the outer cell and 54°C for the inner cell.</para>

    <para>The temperature of fuel returning to the tanks is primarily a function of IDG cooling
    requirement. The immediate action, therefore is to turn the galley off to reduce the IDG
    load.</para>

    <para>On the ground, the engine on the affected side must be shut down if the outer cell reaches
    60°C or the inner cell reaches 54°C. An expeditious taxi may, therefore, be advantageous.</para>

    <para>In the air, if only one side is affected, fuel flow can be increased so that less hot fuel
    is returned to the tanks. If the temperature gets too high (&gt;65°C outer or &gt;57° inner),
    IDG disconnection will be required. The engine must be running when the IDG button is pressed,
    and it must not be held for more than 3 seconds.[FCOM SYS.24.20]</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FUEL</emphasis> L(R) OUTER(INNER) TK HI TEMP,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FUEL]</para>
  </sect1>

</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Landing gear</title>

  <sect1 id="loss-of-braking">
    <title>Loss of braking <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>

    <para>If it is simply an autobrake failure, just brake manually. Otherwise, apply max reverse
    and attempt to use the alternate brake system. To do this, release the brake pedals and turn off
    the ASKID &amp; NW STRG switch. If the alternate system also appears to have failed, short
    successive applications of the parking brake may be used. Use of the parking brake in this way
    risks tire burst and lateral control difficulties (due brake onset asymmetry) so delay until low
    speed if at all possible.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Residual braking procedure</title>

    <para>Residual brake pressure must be checked after landing gear extension as there is no ECAM
    warning. A brief brake pressure indication is expected as the alternate system self tests after
    the gear is down locked, but pressure should quickly return to zero. If the triple indicator
    shows residual pressure after this test, try to zero it by pressing the brake pedals several
    times. If a landing must be made with residual pressure in the alternate braking system, use
    autobrake MED or immediate manual braking to prioritise the normal system. Anticipate brake
    asymmetry at touchdown.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.BRAKES, FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="gear-gravity-extension">
    <title>Gravity extension</title>

    <para>Gravity extension is achieved by turning the GRAVITY GEAR EXTN handcrank clockwise three
    times until a mechanical stop is reached. Once the gear is down, the LG lever should be set to
    down to extinguish the UNLK lights and remove the LG CTL message from the WHEEL page.</para>

    <para>Availability of landing gear indications depends on the nature of the failure that
    resulted in the requirement for gravity extension. LDG GEAR control panel indications may still
    be available if LGCIU 1 is otherwise unserviceable, providing that it is electrically
    supplied.</para>

    <para>Gear doors may show amber on the WHEEL page after gravity extension. There may also be
    spurious LGCIU 2 FAULT or BRAKES SYS 1(2) FAULT ECAM warnings.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.L/G, FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="asymmetric-braking">
    <title>Asymmetric braking</title>

    <para>Defined as all brakes on one gear released (indicated by amber brake release indicators on
    both wheels of one main gear on the WHEEL SD page<!-- {TODO: check this} -->). When the
    remaining brakes are applied, the aircraft will tend to swing towards them. This tendency must
    be countered with rudder, hence the braking must be progressive and co-ordinated with available
    rudder authority.  Crosswinds from the side of the available brakes will re-inforce the swing,
    so anything greater than 10kt from that side should be avoided.</para>

    <para>If a reverser is inoperative on the same side as the inoperative brakes, do not use the
    remaining reverser since it would also re-inforce the swing.</para>

    <para>Landing distances will increase significantly.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.BRAKES, FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Landing with abnormal landing gear</title>

    <para>A landing should be carried out on a hard surface runway using any available landing
    gear. Foaming of the runway is recommended. Manual braking should be used. Reverse thrust should
    not be used as it will cause ground spoiler extension. The GRVTY GEAR EXTN handcrank should be
    turned back to normal to allow the landing gear down actuators to be pressurised and thus reduce
    the chance of gear collapse.</para>

    <para>If the nose gear is not available, move the CG aft by moving passengers to the rear of the
    aircraft. Use elevator to keep the nose off the runway, but lower the nose onto the runway
    before elevator control is lost. Braking must be progressive and balanced against available
    elevator authority. The engines should be shut down with the ENG MASTER switches prior to nose
    impact.</para>

    <para>If one main gear is not available, consider crossfeeding to remove the fuel from the wing
    with the unserviceable gear. The anti-skid system cannot operate with a single main gear
    extended and must be switched off to avoid permanent brake release. The ground spoilers should
    not be armed in order to maintain the maximum possible roll authority. The engines should be
    shut down at touchdown. After touchdown, use roll control to keep the unsupported wing from
    touching down for as long as possible.</para>

    <para>If both main gear are unavailable, the engines should be shut down in the flare. Pitch
    attitude at touchdown must be >6°.</para>

    <para>All doors and slides are available for evacuation in any of the normal gear up
    attitudes.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.L/G, FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="flight-with-gear-extended">
    <title>Flight with landing gear extended</title>

    <para>Flight into expected icing conditions is not approved. Gear down ditching has not been
    demonstrated. FMGC predictions will be erroneous – selected speed should be used for all phases
    except approach. CLB and DES modes should not be used. Altitude alerting will not be
    available. Any failure that normally causes a degradation to alternate law will instead cause a
    degradation to direct law.</para>

    <para>The dual engine failure scenario is modified to reflect the gear limiting speed. Assisted
    start should be preferred. If the APU is not available, gear limit speeds should be disregarded
    to achieve a windmill start. Flight controls will be in direct law; manual pitch trim should be
    available, even when not annunciated on the PFD.</para>

    <para>Performance in all phases will be affected. In particular, approach climb limiting weights
    for go-around (see FCOM PRO.NOR.SUP.L/G) must be reduced by 14%. Fuel burn will increase
    (approximate factor is 2.3). Engine out ceiling and take-off performance are also
    impacted.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.NOR.SUP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Gear shock absorber fault</title>

    <para>A shock absorber did not extend when airborne or did not compress on landing. If airborne
    the gear cannot be retracted. Respect the gear extended limit speed of 280kt and see <xref
    linkend="flight-with-gear-extended"/>.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">L/G</emphasis> SHOCK ABSORBER FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Gear not uplocked</title>

    <para>Landing gear retraction sequence has not completed within 30 seconds. If the gear doors
    have closed, the gear will rest on the doors so avoid excess g loads. If the doors have not
    closed, recycle the gear. If this does not work, select the gear down and see <xref
    linkend="flight-with-gear-extended"/>.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">L/G</emphasis> GEAR NOT UPLOCKED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="gear-not-downlocked">
    <title>Gear not downlocked</title>

    <para>If the landing gear extension sequence has not completed within 30 seconds, retract the
    gear, wait until it has fully stowed, and then redeploy it. Recent studies show that if the gear
    does not immediately deploy successfully following reselection, it may deploy normally within
    the next two minutes as hydraulic pressure continues to act on the gear and doors throughout
    this time. If still unsuccessful after two minutes, attempt to deploy the gear by gravity (see
    <xref linkend="gear-gravity-extension"/>).</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">L/G</emphasis> GEAR NOT DOWNLOCKED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Gear doors not closed</title>

    <para>A gear door is not uplocked. Recycle the gear. If the doors cannot be closed, speed is
    limited to 250kt/M0.6.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">L/G</emphasis> DOORS NOT CLOSED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>

    <title>Uplock fault</title>

    <para>An uplock is engaged when the corresponding gear is downlocked. As the uplock will not
    move to accept the gear the gear must be left down. See <xref
    linkend="flight-with-gear-extended"/>.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">L/G</emphasis> GEAR UPLOCK FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>LGCIU disagreement</title>

    <para>The LGCIUs disagree on the position of the gear. In the absence of other ECAM warnings,
    the gear position can be assumed to agree with the gear lever position.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">L/G</emphasis> SYS DISAGREE,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>LGCIU fault</title>

    <para>The FADECs use LGCIU input to determine idle mode. If a LGCIU is determined to be faulty,
    the system failsafes to approach idle mode, and modulated idle and reverse idle (and hence
    reversers) will not be available.</para>

    <para>The GPWS uses LGCIU 1 to determine landing gear position. If this LGCIU is faulty, the
    GPWS will need to be inhibited to prevent spurious warnings.</para>

    <para>If both LGCIUs are lost, normal landing gear control and indicating systems are lost. The
    gear must be gravity extended (see <xref linkend="gear-gravity-extension"/>).<!-- {TODO:
    Autopilot and autothrust are also lost – --> <!-- find out why this is} --></para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">L/G</emphasis> LGCIU 1(2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Gear not down</title>

    <para>Indicates that the landing gear is not downlocked when radio altitude is below 750ft rad
    alt and N1 and flap setting indicate that the aircraft is on approach. If rad alt data is not
    available, it indicates gear is not down when flap 3 or flap full is selected. In some cases the
    warning may be cancelled with the emergency cancel pushbutton.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">L/G</emphasis> GEAR NOT DOWN,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.L/G]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Park brake on</title>

    <para>The parking brake is set when the thrust levers are set to FLX or TOGA. Check the position
    of the brake handle position and for pressure indications on the brake triple gauge.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">CONFIG</emphasis> PARK BRK ON,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.CONFIG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Nosewheel steering fault</title>

    <para>Nosewheel steering is unavailable so differential braking must be used to steer the
    aircraft. The nosewheel may not be aligned if the L/G shock absorber ECAM is also displayed, in
    which case delay nosewheel touch down as long as possible. Cat III dual will not be
    available.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">WHEEL</emphasis> N/W STRG FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.WHEEL]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="antiskid-nosewheel-steering-off">
    <title>Antiskid nosewheel steering off</title>

    <para>The A/SKID &amp; NW STRG switch is off. The ABCU controls braking through the alternate
    braking system. Antiskid is not available so landing distance will increase
    significantly. Autobrake and nosewheel steering will also not be available.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> ANTI SKID/NWS OFF,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Antiskid nosewheel steering fault</title>

    <para>Either:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>both BSCU channels have failed or</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>the normal brake system has been lost and the yellow hydraulic pressure is
          low.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>Effects are as for <xref linkend="antiskid-nosewheel-steering-off"/>, although if yellow
    hydraulic pressure is low braking will be accumulator only.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> A/SKID NWS FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Brake system fault</title>
    <para>A fault has been detected in one channel of the BSCU. Loss of redundancy only.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> SYS 1(2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Brakes hot</title>

    <para>At least one brake temperature is &gt;300°C. Check <xref
    linkend="brake-temperature-limitations"/> if the temperature is excessive or the brake
    temperatures are not reasonably even.</para>

    <para>Temperature must be &lt;300°C for takeoff to prevent ignition of any hydraulic fluid that
    leaks onto the brake. Use brake fans as necessary to bring the temperature down in time for the
    next takeoff. The brake fans also cool the temperature sensor, so assume the real brake
    temperature is twice that indicated if they have recently been used. <!-- {TODO: Check whether
    we use chocks and release the parking brake}. --></para>

    <para>If the warning appears in flight, providing that performance permits, the landing gear
    should be extended to allow the brakes to cool.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> HOT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Auto brake fault</title>

    <para>A failure was detected when the autobrake was armed. Brake manually.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> AUTO BRK FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Hydraulic selector valve fault</title>

    <para>This ECAM message may indicate two completely different conditions:
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem><para>The normal brake selector valve has failed in the open position. The
          normal servo valves (downstream of the selector valve) will have continuous full pressure
          at their inlets, but, as long as anti-skid is operative, will control brake pressure and
          anti-skid normally.</para></listitem>

          <listitem><para>The steering selector valve has failed in the open position. This means
          that the steering will remain pressurised as long as there is pressure in the yellow
          hydraulic system. This has obvious implications if towing is attempted, but will also mean
          that the nosewheel will go to maximum deflection if the A/SKID &amp; N/W STRG switch is
          selected off or the BSCU is reset.</para></listitem>
        </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">WHEEL</emphasis> HYD SEL FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.ABN.32]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Failure of normal braking system</title>

    <para>Normal braking is lost, but alternate braking and anti-skid are available. Landing
    distance increases slightly.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> NORM BRK FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Failure of alternate braking system</title>

    <para>Loss of redundancy only.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> ALTN BRK FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Failure of normal and alternate braking systems</title>

    <para>The only braking remaining is the parking brake. See <xref linkend="loss-of-braking"/> for
    method.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> NORM + ALTN FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Brake accumulator low pressure</title>

    <para>Braking is not available unless either the green or yellow hydraulic systems are
    pressurised. If the engines are shut down, attempt to recharge the accumulator using the yellow
    system electrical pump. When parking the aircraft, use chocks.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> BRK Y ACCU LO PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="released-normal-brakes">
    <title>Released brakes, normal system</title>

    <para>If normal braking is active and at least one engine is running, the BSCU self tests when
    it receives a “gear downlocked” signal from either of the LGCIUs. The BRAKES RELEASED ECAM is
    provided if at least one set of brakes on a main wheel is incorrectly released during this
    test. The failed brake is shown by an amber release symbol on the WHEEL page. Loss of a brake
    leads to increased landing distances. If both brakes on the same gear are released, see <xref
    linkend="asymmetric-braking"/>.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> RELEASED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Released brakes, alternate system</title>

    <para>The ABCU self tests the brakes in a similar manner to the BSCU (see <xref
    linkend="released-normal-brakes"/>). If this test is failed, normal braking can be expected as
    long as the normal braking system is active. If the alternate braking system is active, braking
    will be asymmetric (see <xref linkend="asymmetric-braking"/>).</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">BRAKES</emphasis> ALTN L(R) RELEASED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.BRAKES]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="brake-temperature-limitations">
    <title>Brake temperature limitations requiring maintenance action</title>

    <para>Maintenance is required if:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>One brake temp is &gt;600°C and the other brake on the same gear is 150°C
      less</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>One brake temp is &lt;60°C and the other brake on the same gear is 150°C
      more</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>The average temp of one gear is 200°C more than the average temp of the
      other</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Any brake temp exceeds 900°C</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>A fuse plug has melted</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para role="multicite">[EOMB 2.3.21]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter id="power-plant">
  <title>Power plant</title>

  <sect1 id="dual-engine-failure">
    <title>Dual engine failure</title>

    <para>If time is short due to the failure occuring at low altitude, “quick”
    ditching and forced landing procedures are available on the back of the normal checklist. These
    are discussed in <xref linkend="ditching"/> and <xref linkend="forced-landing"/>.</para>

    <para>The ENG DUAL FAILURE ECAM may not be triggered under some
    circumstances. The QRH procedure, therefore, includes all items provided by the ECAM; indeed,
    after a few initial items the ECAM simply refers to the QRH procedure.</para>

    <para>First priority, assuming fuel remains, is to attempt a relight by turning the ignitors on
    and setting the thrust levers to idle. The speed should initially be increased to 300kt to
    increase windmilling and improve the chance of a relight. At this speed, the aircraft will cover
    approximately 2nm for every 1000ft lost. With this in mind, a suitable plan should be
    constructed to cover the possibility that relight is not possible.</para>

    <para>Whilst awaiting a relight, ensure that the emergency electrical generator is on line and
    recycle FAC1 to recover characteristic speed display and rudder trim. For communications, VHF1
    and ATC1 are available in the emergency electrical config. Due to lack of engine bleeds, a slow
    depressurisation will be occurring, so be ready to don oxygen masks.</para>

    <para>If there has been no relight after 30 seconds, the combustion chambers should be
    ventilated by turning both engine masters off for 30 seconds. Another attempt can then be made
    by turning them back on. This sequence should be repeated until successful or until APU bleed
    air becomes available at FL200.</para>

    <para>Once below FL250, the APU can be started. Once below FL200, speed should be reduced to
    green dot and assisted starts should be attempted. At green dot speed, 2½nm will be covered for
    every 1000ft lost. Attempt to start one engine at a time in the normal manner.</para>

    <para>If a landing must be made without power, CONF 3 slats are recommended (flaps are
    unavailable). V<subscript>app</subscript> should be V<subscript>ref</subscript>+25kt or 150kt,
    whichever is higher. The gear is available with gravity extension. The stabilizer will be frozen
    once engine driven hydraulics are lost and elevator trimming will cease with transition to
    direct law at gear extension. Therefore, gear extension should be delayed until CONF 3 and
    V<subscript>app</subscript> are reached. If ditching, do not extend the gear.</para>

    <para>If an airfield can be reached, arrange to be inbound on the runway centreline at 4nm and
    2400ft aal with CONF 1, S speed and gear up. To help achieve this, for a clean aircraft, the
    following rules of thumb apply:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A standard one minute leg holding pattern loses 8000ft and an orbit loses 4000ft. Thus
        for every 15 seconds outbound in a holding pattern, approximately 1000ft is lost.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Wings level, 400ft is lost per nm.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    For the segment inbound from 4nm, macro adjustment of glide path is available through the timing
    of gear and slat deployment, then micro adjustment is available from temporarily increasing
    speed above V<subscript>app</subscript>. If necessary, disregard slat limiting speeds. It is
    better to land fast then long. CONF 3, gear down will give a glide ratio of approximately 850ft
    per nm.</para>

    <para>If an airfield cannot be reached, refer to <xref linkend="ditching"/> or <xref
    linkend="forced-landing"/> as appropriate.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG</emphasis> DUAL FAILURE, QRH AEP.ENG,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG, FCTM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Single Engine failure</title>

    <para>Defined as a rapid decrease in EGT, N2 and FF, followed by a decrease in N1. The crew must
    determine whether the engine has been damaged or whether a simple flame-out has
    occurred. Indications of damage are loud noises, significantly increased vibration or buffeting,
    repeated or uncontrollable engine stalls or abnormal post-failure indications (e.g. hydraulic
    fluid loss, zero N1 or N2 etc.).</para>

    <para>Firstly, the ignitors are turned on to protect the remaining engine and to confirm an
    immediate relight attempt. The thrust lever of the failed engine is then moved to idle (PF moves
    the lever after confirmation from PNF). If the FADEC hasn’t relit the failed engine within 30
    seconds of the failure, it is shut down with the master switch. If damage is believed to have
    occurred, the associated fire button is pushed and, after 10 seconds, agent 1 discharged.</para>

    <para>If it is believed that the engine is undamaged, a relight can be considered. The relight
    procedure is fairly long and highly unlikely to be successful; do not delay diversion and
    landing by attempting a relight. Also note that a relight attempt will erase FADEC
    troubleshooting data.</para>

    <para>If there is vibration and/or buffeting, attempt to find an airspeed and altitude
    combination that minimizes the symptoms.</para>

    <para>Refer to <xref linkend="engine-shut-down"/> if unable to relight the engine.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> FAIL,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="engine-shut-down">
    <title>Single engine operation</title>

    <para>The most pressing issue is that a single engine bleed cannot support wing anti-ice and two
    packs. With the crossbleed valve selector in the normal AUTO position, the crossbleed valve is
    effectively synchronised to the APU bleed valve<footnote><para>The exception is that the
    crossbleed won't open if a bleed air duct leak is detected except during engine
    start.</para></footnote> and thus will most probably be closed; wing anti-ice, if it is in use,
    will be operating asymmetrically. If a fire button has been pushed, its associated side of the
    pneumatic system will be locked out and thus the only option is to turn the wing anti-ice
    off. PRO.NOR.SUP.AW “Minimum Speed with Ice Accretion” provides mitigation of icing in the event
    of inoperative wing anti-ice. If both sides of the cross bleed system are available, the cross
    bleed valve can be manually opened at a cost of 1200ft to the single engine gross ceiling. With
    the cross bleed valve open, wing anti-ice is available, but one of the packs must be turned
    off<footnote><para>It will need to be pack 1 in Emergency Electrical config; otherwise it will
    generally be the pack on the dead engine side.</para></footnote> whenever it is used.</para>

    <para>The remaining engine must be safeguarded. To this end, continuous ignition should be
    selected.</para>

    <para>A fuel imbalance may develop. Fuel imbalance limitations are detailed in FCOM LIM.FUEL.  If
    the outer tanks are balanced, once the fuller inner tank contains less than 2250kg, fuel balance
    will never be limiting. Since this first occurs with approximately 5900kg of fuel remaining,
    fuel balancing due to balance limitations will generally not be required. Fuel may, however,
    still need to be crossfed to prevent fuel starvation of the remaining engine. Balance this
    concern against feeding your live engine the same fuel that was feeding your failed engine when
    it stopped working.</para>

    <para>TCAS should be selected to TA to avoid unflyable climb RAs.</para>

    <para>If a reverser is unlocked with associated buffet, speed should be limited to 240kt. See
    <xref linkend="reverser-unlocked"/> for more details of this scenario.</para>

    <para>If the remaining engine is operated at maximum power with the aircraft at low speed
    (e.g. responding to windshear) it is possible that directional control may be lost before the
    flight computer protections apply. Be cautious about reducing speed below
    V<subscript>LS</subscript> on one engine.</para>

    <para>The main systems lost are the generator, bleed and hydraulic pump
    associated with the engine. Other systems may be lost depending on the reason for the
    shutdown. The APU can be used to replace the lost generator and, providing the left side of the
    pneumatic system is available and isolated (i.e. cross bleed valve closed), provide
    pressurisation through pack 1, thus giving additional margin for the go-around. The BMCs
    automatically close the engine bleeds when the APU bleed valve is opened, so it is not necessary
    to manually turn them off to achieve this additional go-around margin. Note, however, that the
    APU cannot support wing anti-ice.</para>

    <para>Approach and landing will be fairly normal. The main provisos are

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Full flap should only be selected once descending on the glidepath; if a level
      off is required, the landing should be CONF3 [QRH AEP.ENG “OEI – Straight in
      approach”].</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Only Cat 3 Single is available due to the loss of the ability to split the
      electrical system.[QRH OPS]</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>On A319s, the autopilot cannot fly FINAL APP, NAV/VS or NAV/FPA
      approaches. All modes are available for manual flight with flight
      directors. [FCOM LIM.AFS.GEN]</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If flying manually, consider using manual thrust to better anticipate the
      rudder inputs required by thrust changes. Also consider setting rudder trim to zero at a late
      stage of the approach.[FCTM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG</emphasis> 1(2) SHUT DOWN,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Engine relight in flight</title>

    <para>A graph showing the in flight relight envelope is provided in section AEP.ENG of the
    QRH. The ceiling is 27000 ft. Automatic start is recommended, but crew action is required in
    case of abnormal start.</para>

    <para>To prepare for the start, ensure the affected engine master switch is turned off and the
    affected thrust lever is at idle. Select ignition on the engine mode selector and open the cross
    bleed. If it is anticipated starter assist may be required, ensure wing anti ice is selected
    off.</para>

    <para>To begin the start sequence, select the affected master switch on. The FADEC will
    determine whether starter assist is required and will open the start valve as needed. Both
    ignitors are energised as soon as the master switch is turned on, and the HP fuel valve opens at
    15% N2. Closure of the start valve and de-energisation of the ignitors occurs at 50% N2 as
    normal. Light off must occur within 30 seconds of fuel flow initiation. If uncertain about
    successful relight, move the thrust lever to check for engine response. The START FAULT ENG
    STALL ECAM may be disregarded if all other parameters are normal. </para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.ENG, FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="engine-stall">
    <title>Engine stall</title>

    <para>A stall is indicated by abnormal engine noise, flame from the engine exhaust (and possibly
    inlet in extreme cases), fluctuating performance parameters, sluggish thrust lever response,
    high EGT and/ or rapid EGT rise when the thrust lever is advanced. The ECAM warning will be
    triggered when N2 is between 50% and idle (approx 60%). If N2 is above idle, the QRH should be
    used.</para>

    <para>The ECAM simply instructs the master switch to be turned off, and then secures the engine
    using the after engine shut down procedure (see <xref linkend="engine-shut-down"/>). This
    procedure should also be followed if a stall occurs on the ground.</para>

    <para>In flight, if no ECAM is triggered, the affected thrust lever should be retarded to
    idle. If the engine parameters remain abnormal, shut the engine down with the master switch. If
    the parameters are normal, turn on all the anti-icing to increase bleed demand and slowly
    advance the thrust lever. If the stall recurs, the engine can be operated at low thrust
    settings, otherwise it can be operated normally.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> STALL, QRH AEP.ENG,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Engine tailpipe fire</title>

    <para>An internal engine fire may be encountered during engine start or shutdown. It will either
    be seen by ground crew or may be indicated by EGT failing to decrease after the master switch is
    selected off.</para>

    <para>Start by getting the engine to a known state by ensuring the man start button is selected
    off and the affected engine master is selected off.</para>

    <para>The concept is to blow the fire out by dry cranking the engine. It is therefore essential
    that the fire button is <emphasis>not</emphasis> pressed, as this will remove external power
    from the FADEC and prevent dry cranking. Firstly, a source of bleed air must be available to
    power the starter. Possibilities, in order of preference, are the APU, the opposite engine or a
    ground air cart. If using the opposite engine, the source engine bleed must be on, the target
    engine bleed should be off, the cross bleed should be opened and thrust increased to provide 30
    psi of pressure.<!-- {TODO: This is just the crossbleed start procedure from QRH SI.150 – -->
    <!-- check that there are no differences} --> If using ground air, both engine bleeds should be
    off and the cross bleed opened. Once high pressure air is available, select the engine mode
    selector to crank and select the man start button to on. Once the fire is extinguished, select
    the man start button off and the engine mode selector to normal.</para>

    <para>As a last resort, external fire suppression agents may be used. They are, however, highly
    corrosive and the engine will be a write off.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.ENG, FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="engine-vibrations">
    <title>High engine vibration</title>

    <para>The ECAM VIB advisory (N1≥6 units, N2≥4.3 units) is simply an indication that engine
    parameters should be monitored more closely. High VIB indications alone do not require the
    engine to be shut down.</para>

    <para>High engine vibration combined with burning smells may be due to contact of compressor
    blade tips with associated abradable seals.</para>

    <para>If in icing conditions, high engine vibration may be due to fan blade or spinner
    icing. The QRH provides a drill to shed this ice, after which normal operations can be
    resumed.</para>

    <para>If icing is not suspected and if flight conditions permit, reduce
    thrust so that vibrations are below the advisory level. Shut down the engine after landing for
    taxiing if vibrations above the advisory level have been experienced.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.ENG, FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Low oil pressure</title>

    <para>The sources for the gauge on the ECAM ENG page and the ECAM warning are different. If
    there is a discrepancy between the two, a faulty transducer is the most likely cause and the
    engine can continue to be operated normally. If both sources agree, the engine should be shut
    down by retarding its thrust lever and selecting its master switch off and the after shutdown
    procedure applied (see <xref linkend="engine-shut-down"/>).</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> OIL LO PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="high-oil-temp">
    <title>High oil temperature</title>

    <para>It may be possible to reduce oil temperature by increasing engine fuel flow.</para>

    <para>If oil temperature exceeds 155°C or exceeds 140°C for 15 minutes, the engine must be shut
    down.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> OIL HI TEMP,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Oil filter clog</title>

    <para>If a warning occurs during a cold engine start with oil temperature &lt;40°C, the warning
    may be considered spurious. The oil filter features a bypass mechanism, so there is no immediate
    problem.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> OIL FILTER CLOG,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Fuel filter clog</title>

    <para>No immediate crew action required. I assume there is some sort of bypass mechanism, but
    this isn’t apparent from the FCOM.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> FUEL FILTER CLOG,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Uncommanded reverser pressurisation</title>

    <para>There are two valves that prevent pressure reaching the thrust reverser actuators at an
    inopportune moment, plus a third that commands direction of movement. The most upstream of
    these, controlled by the SECs, prevents any hydraulic pressure reaching the Hydraulic Control
    Unit (HCU) when the thrust levers are not in the reverse quadrant. If this protection is lost,
    the correct operation of the HCU should keep the doors properly stowed. An HCU malfunction,
    however, could result in an in-flight reverser deployment. If flight conditions permit, idle
    thrust should be selected on the affected engine.</para>

    <para>It is unclear from the FCOM whether the ECAM indicates pressure has reached the
    directional solenoid valve and hence that the reverser door jacks are pressurised, albeit in the
    closed direction, although the existence of the REV ISOL FAULT ECAM indicates that this is
    probably the case.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> REV PRESSURIZED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="reverser-unlocked">
    <title>Reverser unlocked in flight</title>

    <para>If one or more reverser doors are detected as not stowed in flight, the associated FADEC
    will automatically command idle on the affected engine. This should be backed up by setting the
    thrust lever to idle.</para>

    <para>A warning without associated buffet is likely to be spurious. In this case limit speed to
    300kt/M.78, keep the engine running at idle and expect to make a normal single engine approach
    and landing.</para>

    <para>If there is buffet, shut the engine down and limit speed to 240kt. Full rudder trim may be
    required. The ECAM will provide one of two approach procedures depending on how many doors are
    detected as not stowed:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>If all 4 doors are not stowed, it will be a flap 1 landing, with approach
      speed V<subscript>REF</subscript>+55kt slowing to V<subscript>REF</subscript>+40kt below
      800ft. Gear should only be deployed once landing is assured.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Otherwise, it will be a flap 3 landing at
      V<subscript>REF</subscript>+10kt.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> REVERSE UNLOCKED,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="eiu-fault">
    <title>EIU fault</title>

    <para>The Engine Interface Unit (EIU) receives data from the engine start system, the
    auto-thrust system, the LGCIUs, the air conditioning controller and the engine anti ice system
    and feeds it to its related FADEC. Thus loss of the EIU leads to loss of auto-thrust, reverser,
    idle control (defaults to approach idle) and start for the affected engine. If engine anti ice
    is used, the ignitors must be manually selected.</para>

    <para>If an engine fails whilst its associated EIU is inoperative, the usual ECAM messages will
    not be generated. The failure can still be diagnosed from the system pages and an appropriate
    drill can be actioned from the FCOM.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> EIU FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>N1/N2/EGT overlimit</title>

    <para>If the overlimit is moderate, the associated thrust lever can be retarded until the
    overlimit ceases, and the flight may be continued normally.</para>

    <para>If the overlimit is excessive, the engine should generally be shut down. If there are
    over-riding factors precluding a shut down, the engine may be run at minimum required
    thrust.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> N1/N2/EGT OVERLIMIT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>N1/N2/EGT/FF discrepancy</title>

    <para>The system can detect a discrepancy between actual and displayed values of N1, N2, EGT and
    fuel flow. This is indicated by an amber CHECK beneath the affected parameter. Attempt to
    recover normal indications by switching from DMC1 to DMC3. If this fails, values can be inferred
    from the opposite engine.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis
    role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> N1(N2)(EGT)(FF) DISCREPANCY, FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Start valve fault</title>

    <para>If a start valve fails open, remove bleed sources supplying the faulty valve. If on the
    ground, turn off the MAN START button if used, and shut the engine down with its master
    switch.</para>

    <para>If the start valve fails closed, it may be that insufficient pressure is reaching it. Try
    opening the cross bleed and turning on the APU bleed.</para>

    <para>On the ground, a start may still be possible with manual operation of the start
    valve.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> START VALVE FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="start-faults">
    <title>Start faults</title>

    <para>Start faults include ignition faults (no light off within 18 seconds of ignition start),
    engine stalls, EGT overlimit (>725°C) and starter time exceedance (2 mins max).</para>

    <para>On the ground, nearly all starts are auto starts. In this case the FADEC will
    automatically abort as needed. It will then automatically carry out the required dry crank phase
    and make further attempts. Once the FADEC gives up, an ECAM message will instruct the crew to
    turn off the relevant engine master. If the fault was a stall due to low pressure, consider
    another automatic start using cross bleed air.</para>

    <para>If a manual start is attempted, the crew must monitor the relevant parameters (the FADECs
    will provide some passive monitoring) and, if necessary, abort the start by turning the engine
    master and man start button off. The crew must then carry out a 30 second dry crank phase
    manually. Note that this is not mentioned in the relevant supplementary procedure, nor are the
    relevant lines displayed on the ECAM. It is probably worth having FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG handy when
    carrying out manual starts.</para>

    <para>Following an aborted start in flight, the engine master should be turned off for 30
    seconds to drain the engine. A further start attempt can then be made.</para>

    <para>If the electrical power supply is interrupted during a start (indicated by loss of ECAM
    DUs) turn the master switch off, then perform a 30 second dry crank.</para>

    <para>If a fuel leak from the engine drain mast is reported, run the
    engine at idle for 5 minutes. If the leak disappears within this time the aircraft may dispatch
    without maintenance action.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> START FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG, EOMB 2.3.8.1]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Ignition faults</title>

    <para>Each engine has two ignitors. If both fail on a single engine, avoid heavy rain,
    turbulence and, as far as possible, icing conditions.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> IGN FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Thrust lever angle sensor faults</title>

    <para>Each thrust lever has two thrust lever angle (TLA) sensors.</para>

    <para>Failure of one sensor only leads to a loss of redundancy; the proviso is that it must have
    failed in a way that the system can positively detect.</para>

    <para>More difficult is when the sensors are in disagreement. In this case, the FADEC makes the
    assumption that one of the sensors is accurate and provides a default thrust setting based on
    this assumption:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>On the ground, if neither sensor is in a take-off position, idle power is
      commanded. If one sensor is in take-off position and the other is above idle, take-off thrust
      is commanded. This leaves the completely conflicted case of one sensor at take-off and the
      other at idle or below; the FADEC selects idle power as the best compromise.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>In flight, once above thrust reduction altitude the FADEC will assume that the
      largest TLA, limited to CLB, is correct. The autothrust can then manage the thrust between
      idle and this position. For approach (slats extended), as long as both TLAs indicate less than
      MCT, thrust is commanded to idle.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>If both TLA sensors fail, the FADEC again goes for sensible defaults. On the ground, idle
    thrust is set. In flight, if the thrust was TO or FLEX at the time of failure, this setting will
    be maintained until slat retraction, whereupon CLB will be selected. If the thrust was between
    IDLE and MCT, CLB will be selected immediately. As soon as slats are deployed, IDLE is
    commanded; this remains the case even for go-around. Autothrust will manage thrust between IDLE
    and CLB whenever CLB is assumed.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> THR LEVER DISAGREE,
    <emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> THR LEVER FAULT, <emphasis
    role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> ONE TLA FAULT, FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>FADEC faults</title>

    <para>The FADECs have two redundant channels; loss of a single channel does not generally
    require crew action. Single channel FADEC faults during start may be considered spurious on
    successful application of the reset procedure detailed in FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG</para>

    <para>If both channels of a FADEC are lost, the thrust lever should be set to idle. Engine
    indications will be lost. If all other parameters are normal (check all ECAM system pages), the
    engine can be left running. Otherwise, shut it down.</para>

    <para>If a FADEC overheats, reducing engine power may reduce temperature in the ECU area
    sufficiently to prevent shutdown. If on the ground the engine must be shut down and the FADEC
    depowered.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> FADEC A(B) FAULT,
    <emphasis role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> FADEC FAULT, <emphasis
    role="underline">ENG 1(2)</emphasis> FADEC HI TEMP, FCOM PRO.AEP.ENG]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Navigation</title>

  <sect1 id="egpws">
    <title>EGPWS alerts <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>

    <para>EPGWS alerts can be categorised into warnings and cautions. A warning is any alert with
    the instruction “Pull up” or “Avoid” attached. All other alerts are cautions. A warning may be
    downgraded to a caution if flying in daylight VMC and positive visual verification is made that
    no hazard exists, or if an applicable nuisance warning notice is promulgated in Company
    documentation [EOMA 8.3.6].</para>

    <para>The response to a “Pull up” type warning is to call “Pull up, TOGA”, disconnect the
    autopilot and simultaneously roll the wings level, apply full backstick and set TOGA power. The
    speedbrake should then be checked retracted. Once the flight path is safe and the warning stops,
    accelerate and clean up as required. Note that it is highly likely that the autothrust ALPHA
    FLOOR protection will have engaged and thus the autothrust will need to be disengaged to cancel
    TOGA LK mode.</para>

    <para>An “Avoid” warning indicates that a vertical manoeuvre alone is insufficient to prevent
    collision, and lateral avoiding action must also be taken. The response is essentially the same
    except that instead of rolling wings level, a turn must be initiated. The direction of the turn
    is at the discretion of the pilot, with the terrain or obstacle that is the source of the
    warning being displayed in red and black crosshatch on the ND.</para>

    <para>The response to a caution is to correct the flight path or aircraft configuration as
    necessary. A configuration warning will almost always require a go around.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.AEP.SURV]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="TCAS">
    <title>TCAS warnings <emphasis>(memory item)</emphasis></title>

    <para>TCAS warnings may be either traffic advisories ("Traffic, Traffic") or resolution
    advisories (anything else).</para>

    <para>From 28th January 2017, new easyJet deliveries are fitted with the
    new AP/FD TCAS mode. When this mode is fitted, the autopilot is capable of autonomously flying
    the TCAS escape manoeuvre. PF simply calls “TCAS blue, I have control" to establish who will
    take over if the autopilot does not respond appropriately, then calls the FMAs and monitors the
    autopilot as it flies the manoeuvre. If flying manually with flight directors and autothrust on,
    the flight directors will give standard guidance to fly the manoeuvre. If flying fully manually,
    the flight directors will pop up and the autothrust will engage, although it may be necessary to
    set the thrust levers to the climb gate.</para>

    <para>If AP/FD TCAS mode is not installed or not available, the first response to either
    advisory is to call “TCAS, I have control” to unequivocally establish who will be carrying out
    any manoeuvres. If it is a resolution advisory, the autopilot should be disconnected and
    <emphasis>both</emphasis> flight directors turned off<footnote><para>If one FD is left engaged,
    the autothrust will not revert to speed mode, possibly resulting in speed decay and engagement
    of normal law protections.</para></footnote>. The autothrust remains engaged and reverts to
    speed mode. A vertical manoeuvre should then be flown to keep the <acronym>V/S</acronym> needle
    out of the red areas shown on the <acronym>V/S</acronym> scale. ATC should then be notified (e.g
    “Radar, Easy 123 – TCAS RA”). When clear of conflict, return to assigned level and re-engage the
    automatics (ATC phraseology: “Radar, Easy 123 – clear of conflict, returning to FL XXX”).</para>

    <para>If a climb resolution advisory occurs on final approach, a go around must be flown.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.AEP.SURV, CAP413 1.7]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="rnav-downgrade">
    <title>RNAV downgrades</title>

    <para>RNAV operations fall into three main categories:

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>RNAV approach (usually RNP 0.3)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>RNP-1 (aka PRNAV)</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>RNP-5 (aka BRNAV)</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    The equipment that must be serviceable is listed in EOMB 2.3.18.3.2 for RNAV approach and
    FCOM PRO.SPO.51 for RNP SID/STAR.</para>

    <para>The following messages indicate loss of RNAV capability:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>NAV ACCUR DOWNGRAD (MCDU and ND)<footnote><para>For RNP-1 and RNP-5
      procedures, if NAV ACCUR DOWNGRAD occurs on one side only, the procedure may be continued
      using the unaffected FMGC.</para></footnote></para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>FMS1/FMS2 POS DIFF (MCDU)</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><emphasis role="underline">NAV</emphasis> FM/GPS POS DISAGREE
      (ECAM)</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>CHECK IRS 1(2)(3)/FM POSITION (MCDU)<footnote><para>This is missing from the
      RNP-1 list in EOMB but is listed in the FCOM. It is not listed as a go around criteria for
      RNAV approach, but continuing would seem somewhat brave…</para></footnote></para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>For RNAV approaches, a go-around is mandated for any of these messages or if GPS PRIMARY
    LOST is annunciated on both NDs<footnote><para>If GPS PRIMARY LOST is annunciated on only one
    ND, the approach may be continued using the unaffected FMGC. There is also conflict between EOMA
    and EOMB as to whether GPS PRIMARY is required at all for RNAV(VOR/DME) or RNAV(DME/DME) etc. –
    I've gone with the most restrictive here.</para></footnote>.</para>

    <para>In an RNP-1 (PRNAV) environment, an RNAV downgrade may leave the aircraft unsure of
    position and below MSA. The initial response is to notify ATC with the phrase “Unable RNAV due
    equipment” and request reclearance. An immediate climb above MSA should be considered if a
    suitable alternative navigation method (e.g. radar vectors) is not available.</para>

    <para>Some RNP-1 procedures specify additional downgrade criteria such as a requirement for dual
    RNAV systems or GPS. If GPS is not specifically mandated as an additional restriction, an RNP-1
    procedure may still be flown without GPS PRIMARY: set RNP to 1, check NAV ACCURACY is HIGH and
    carry out a raw data check prior to commencement (see <xref linkend="pos-disagree"/>).</para>

    <para>Downgrades in an RNP-5 (BRNAV) environment are less critical as the aircraft will be above
    MSA. The IRSs provides RNP-5 required accuracy for two hours from last full alignment regardless
    of MCDU ENP, and it is acceptable to carry out a raw data check (see EOMB 2.3.15) to confirm
    that RNP-5 capability is maintained. If loss of RNP-5 capability is confirmed, inform ATC and
    continue with conventional navigation.</para>


    <para role="multicite">[FCOM PRO.SPO.51, EOM A.8.3.3.5, EOMB 2.3.18.3]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="adr-faults">
    <title>ADR faults</title>

    <para>A single ADR fault simply requires switching to the hot spare and turning the affected
    unit off. Loss of ADR1 will lead to the loss of the extended functions of the EGPWS. Loss of
    ADR2 will lead to both baro reference channels being driven by the same FCU channel <!-- {TODO:
    Find out details of this} -->, so the baro refs should be checked.</para>

    <para>Loss of two ADRs will lead to Alternate Law with associated speed restrictions and landing
    configuration considerations. Air data switching is used as necessary, and the affected ADRs are
    turned off. ATC switching may be required to restore transponder. If ADR 1 and 3 are lost, the
    landing gear safety valve is controlled closed, so the gear must be gravity extended and cannot
    subsequently be retracted. This is not mentioned by the ECAM – the gear will simply fail to
    extend normally.</para>

    <para>If all three ADRs are lost, the result is airframe dependent. Some of the fleet now have a
    <emphasis role="underline">NAV</emphasis> ADR 1+2+3 FAULT ECAM and an appropriate procedure
    utilising the Backup Speed Scale, completing with the QRH AEP.NAV ALL ADR OFF paper
    procedure. For older airframes the ECAM displayed will be for Dual ADR failure and must be
    ignored since it will request meaningless air data and ATC switching. Instead revert to standby
    instruments (the standby ASI and Altimeter have direct pressure feeds from the the standby pitot
    and static ports) and refer to QRH AEP.NAV ADR 1+2+3 FAULT. Interestingly, when Backup Speed
    Scale is available, the ECAM advises that the standby instrument indications may be
    unreliable…</para>

    <para>Triple ADR failure has a few additional ramifications. Of note is loss of automatic cabin
    pressure control (see <xref linkend="pressure-controller"/> for manual pressure control
    methodology), Alternate Law and gravity gear extension. Of lesser concern are loss of stall
    warning, rudder travel limiter frozen until slat extension and loss of auto flap
    retraction.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis
    role="underline">NAV</emphasis> ADR 1(2)(3)(1+2)(1+3)(2+3) FAULT, QRH AEP.NAV,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.NAV]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="adr-disagree">
    <title>ADR disagree</title>

    <para>The ECAM message indicates that, following an ADR fault or rejection, there is a speed or
    angle of attack disagreement between the two remaining ADRs. This will cause a degradation to
    alternate law. If there is a speed disagreement, see <xref linkend="unreliable-airspeed"/>. If
    the speed does not disagree, an AOA sensor is providing incorrect data and there is a risk of
    spurious stall warnings.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">NAV</emphasis> ADR DISAGREE,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.NAV]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>RA faults</title>

    <para>A single RA fault results in degradation of approach capability to Cat II. Loss of both
    RAs will lead to direct law at landing gear extension and a loss of ILS APPR mode
    capability. Therefore, landing will be CONF 3 with associated corrections, the approach should
    be flown in LOC and FPA and autopilot disconnect should be anticipated at gear extension.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">NAV</emphasis> RA 1(2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.NAV]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>IR faults</title>

    <para>In case of simultaneous loss of the ADR and IR associated with an ADIRU, apply the ADR
    FAULT procedure first.</para>

    <para>A single IR fault will simply require ATT/HDG switching. This may lead to loss of the
    extended functions of the EPGWS and/or loss of TCAS. It may be possible to recover the IR in ATT
    mode (see <xref linkend="att-mode"/>).</para>

    <para>A dual IR fault will lead to loss of PFD indications on at least one side so use ATT/HDG
    switching to recover. It will also lead to Alternate Law and associated speed restrictions and
    landing configuration considerations.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis
    role="underline">NAV</emphasis> IR 1(2)(3)(1+2)(1+3)(2+3) FAULT, FCOM PRO.AEP.NAV]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>IR disagree</title>

    <para>Following rejection or failure of an IR, there is disagreement between the two remaining
    IRs. Normal and alternate laws are lost, but alternate law with reduced protections can be
    recovered by isolating the faulty IR (use standby horizon to cross-check) and resetting the
    ELACs.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">NAV</emphasis> IR DISAGREE,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.NAV]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="att-mode">
    <title>IR alignment in ATT mode</title>

    <para>If IR alignment is lost, it may be possible to recover attitude and heading information by
    switching the ADIRU selector to ATT and maintaining level constant speed flight for 30
    seconds. The magnetic heading will need to be entered, the exact method being dependent on the
    ADIRS CDU fitted.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[IR Alignment IN ATT Mode, QRH AEP.NAV, FCOM PRO.AEP.NAV]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="pos-disagree">
    <title>FM/GPS position disagree</title>

    <para>This can be disregarded if on an ILS or LOC approach. On an overlay approach, revert to
    raw data. On an RNAV approach, go around unless visual.</para>

    <para>In other flight phases, manually tune a VOR and check against either the needle and DME on
    the ND or the BRG/DIST TO field on the PROG page. If the error is greater than 3nm in the cruise
    or greater than 1nm for approach, raw data navigation and AP/FD selected lateral and vertical
    modes should be used.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">NAV</emphasis> FM/GPS POS DISAGREE,
    QRH AEP.NAV, FCOM PRO.AEP.NAV]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Auto-flight</title>

  <sect1 id="fac-faults">
    <title>FAC faults</title>

    <para>Failure of a single FAC results in loss of redundancy and hence loss of Cat 3 Dual. In
    particular, a single FAC provides all the characteristic speeds (V<subscript>SW</subscript>,
    V<subscript>LS</subscript>, V<subscript>FE</subscript>, V<subscript>FE-next</subscript>,
    V<subscript>LE</subscript>, V<subscript>MO</subscript>/M<subscript>MO</subscript>, Green dot, S
    speed and F speed). It may be worth cross-checking against QRH OPS.OD “Operating Speeds“.</para>

    <para>If both FACs are lost the rudder travel limit system, rudder trim control, yaw damper and
    PFD characteristic speeds are lost and Alternate Law with mechanical yaw control becomes
    active. Recovery of full rudder authority at flap extension should be anticipated, but use
    rudder with care above 160kt.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AUTO FLT</emphasis> FAC 1(2)(1+2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AUTO FLT]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="yaw-damper">
    <title>Yaw damper faults</title>

    <para>A single failure leads to loss of redundancy, and hence loss of Cat 3 Dual. On some
    airframes a reset of the affected FAC can be attempted.</para>

    <para>With a dual failure a reset of the FACs should be attempted. If the yaw damper is not
    recovered, the flight controls revert to alternate law (see <xref
    linkend="alternate-law"/>). Unless the failure occurred below alert height, only Cat I will be
    available.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AUTO FLT</emphasis> YAW DAMPER 1(2)(SYS),
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AUTO FLT]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="rudder-trim">
    <title>Rudder trim faults</title>

    <para>Loss of a rudder trim from a single FAC leads to loss of redundancy and hence loss of Cat
    3 Dual.</para>

    <para>If complete loss of rudder trim occurs, an attempt should be made to reset the FACs. If
    this is not successful, only Cat I is available.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis
    role="underline">AUTO FLT</emphasis> RUDDER TRIM SYS(1(2) FAULT), FCOM PRO.AEP.AUTO FLT]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="rudder-limit">
    <title>Rudder travel limiter faults</title>

    <para>Loss of rudder limit functionality from a single FAC leads to loss of redundancy
    only.</para>

    <para>The effect of complete loss of rudder limiter functionality depends on when the failure
    occurred. In general, the rudder should be used with caution when above 160kt. An attempt should
    be made to recover the limiter by resetting the FACs. If unsuccessful, full rudder travel
    authority may or may not be recovered at slat extension. If a landing must be made with the
    rudder travel limiter frozen in the high speed regime, max crosswind is reduced to 15kt and
    differential braking may be required on the landing roll (do not arm autobrake).</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AUTO FLT</emphasis> RUD TRV LIM_1(2)(SYS),
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AUTO FLT]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="fcu-fault">
    <title>FCU faults</title>

    <para>Loss of a single channel will result in the spare channel automatically taking over. All
    that is required is a cross check of the baro refs.</para>

    <para>Loss of both channels leads to loss of all FCU and EFIS panels. The
    autopilots, flight directors<footnote><para>Flight Directors will pop up to provide guidance in
    the event of a go-around.</para></footnote> and autothrust are lost and parameters that are
    normally controlled by the panels revert to sensible default values. If the weather radar image
    remains displayed, disregard it since the scale will be incorrect. Since it will only be
    possible to set the QNH on the standby altimeters, the MDA should not be set in the MCDU;
    instead the PM should make standard callouts from the standby altimeter.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AUTO FLT</emphasis> FCU 1(2)(1+2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.AUTO FLT]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Hydraulics</title>

  <sect1 id="dualhyd.gy">
    <title>Green + yellow systems low pressure</title>

    <para>It may be possible to recover the yellow system using the yellow electrical pump. Systems
    lost because of low air pressure in the reservoir will be recoverable at lower
    altitudes. Systems lost due to reservoir overheats may be usable for the approach once they have
    cooled down.</para>

    <para>Roll control is available from ailerons and spoiler 3. Pitch control is available from the
    elevators, but the THS is frozen. Yaw damping is lost. Slats are available, but slow. Flaps are
    frozen. Control law reverts to alternate law without stability protections. The autopilots are
    lost.</para>

    <para>The gear must be gravity extended, but due to the frozen THS this must be delayed until
    V<subscript>APP</subscript> is achieved in CONF 3. Furthermore, transition to CONF 3 must be
    achieved in accordance with <xref linkend="flight-controls.slats-flaps-fault"/> due to the flaps
    being frozen. Transition to direct law on gear deployment adds to the fun, especially as pitch
    trim is unavailable.</para>

    <para>Cat 2 and 3 capability is lost. The landing will be CONF 3, most probably with only the
    slats deployed; the flare attitude will be abnormal. There will only be one spoiler (#3), no
    reversers, accumulator only braking and no nose wheel steering. Hence required landing distances
    almost triple.</para>

    <para revisionflag="changed">The go around, in some ways, is exceptionally straightforward. The
    gear cannot be raised and the configuration should be maintained. Due to the frozen stabiliser,
    a speed close to V<subscript>APP</subscript> should be flown<footnote><para>Airbus originally
    suggested flying V<subscript>FE</subscript>-10kt; I assume this was found to cause handling
    difficulties due to pitch trim not being available.</para></footnote>. As long as the flaps are
    frozen at zero, the slats can be retracted for a subsequent diversion; fuel flow will be
    approximately 3 times normal due to the extended gear. If flaps are not at zero, fuel flow
    will be up to 4 times normal.</para>

    <para>A paper summary is available in section AEP.HYD of the QRH, and this should be applied
    once all ECAM actions are completed.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G + Y SYS LO PR, QRH AEP.HYD,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="dualhyd.by">
    <title>Blue + yellow systems low pressure</title>

    <para>It may be possible to recover the yellow system using the yellow electrical pump or the
    blue system using the RAT. Systems lost because of low air pressure in the reservoir will be
    recoverable at lower altitudes. Systems lost due to reservoir overheats may be usable for the
    approach once they have cooled down.</para>

    <para>Roll control is provided by ailerons and spoiler 5, pitch control by the THS and left
    elevator. Slats and flaps are available at reduced rate. The autopilots are lost but Normal law
    is retained. Speedbrake is unavailable.</para>

    <para>Cat 2 and 3 capability is lost. Landing distances are increased due to loss of spoilers 2,
    3 and 4 and loss of #2 reverser. Approach configuration is normal apart from slow flaps and
    slats and gravity gear extension (protects green system). Nose wheel steering is lost.</para>

    <para revisionflag="changed">Gear cannot be retracted on go-around. Fuel burn for a subsequent
    diversion will be significantly greater (approx factor 3 times normal); see <xref
    linkend="flight-with-gear-extended"/> for further details.</para>

    <para>A paper summary is available in section AEP.HYD of the QRH, and this should be applied
    once all ECAM actions are completed.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> B + Y SYS LO PR, QRH AEP.HYD,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="dualhyd.gb">
    <title>Green + blue systems low pressure</title>

    <para>If the blue system has been lost due to the loss of its electrical pump, it may be
    recovered by deploying the RAT. Systems lost because of low air pressure in the reservoir will
    be recoverable at lower altitudes. Systems lost due to reservoir overheats may be usable for the
    approach once they have cooled down.</para>

    <para>Roll control is provided by spoilers 2 and 4 only. Use of speedbrake would therefore lead
    to loss of roll control. Pitch control is available from the starboard elevator; the THS remains
    available. Due to the limited control surfaces available, the aircraft will be slightly
    sluggish. The slats are frozen, but flaps are available. Control law reverts to alternate law
    without stability protections. The autopilots are lost. The approach will be flown with the
    autothrust off.</para>

    <para>Due to the frozen slats, configuration changes must be carried out in accordance with
    <xref linkend="flight-controls.slats-flaps-fault"/>. The gear must be gravity extended; to
    benefit from the improved elevator response available in direct law, this is done at
    200kt. Manual trim will be available.</para>

    <para>Cat 2 and 3 capability is lost. The landing will be CONF 3. Two spoilers per wing are
    available, reverser 2 is available, alternate braking is available and nose wheel steering is
    available. Landing distances approximately double.</para>

    <para revisionflag="changed">Go around is straightforward – the gear cannot be retracted and the
    flap configuration should be maintained. Simply select V<subscript>FE</subscript>&#x2011;10. For
    diversion, the flaps can be retracted. With the gear remaining down, fuel burn will increase by
    a factor of approximately 3 if the slats are at zero or up to approximately 3½ if they are
    extended.</para>

    <para>A paper summary is available in section AEP.HYD of the QRH, and this should be applied
    once all ECAM actions are completed.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G + B SYS LO PR, QRH AEP.HYD,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="green-low-pr">
    <title>Green system low pressure</title>

    <para>The major lost systems are normal landing gear operation (gravity extension is available
    but gear retraction is not) and the normal brake system, including the autobrake (alternate
    braking is available). Landing distance will be increased due to loss of two spoilers per wing
    and reverser 1. Flap and slat deployment will be slow.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G SYS LO PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="yellow-low-pr">
    <title>Yellow system low pressure</title>

    <para>It may be possible to recover the yellow system by using the yellow electric pump.</para>

    <para>Two spoilers per wing and reverser 2 are lost, so landing distance will increase
    slightly. Nose wheel steering is lost. Flap deployment will be slow. As the alternate braking
    system is only available through the brake accumulator, ensure there is sufficient pressure when
    the parking brake is set.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> Y SYS LO PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="blue-low-pr">
    <title>Blue system low pressure</title>

    <para>One spoiler per wing will be lost but this has negligible effect on landing
    distance. Slats will be slow to deploy. Deployment of the RAT is not recommended unless another
    system is lost. If the system is lost due to low reservoir level, emergency generation
    capability is lost.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> B SYS LO PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Engine driven pump low pressure</title>

    <para>Turn off the affected pump. The PTU will pressurise the affected system.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G(Y) ENG 1(2) PUMP LO PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Electric pump low pressure or overheat</title>

    <para>Turn off the affected pump. In the case of an overheat, the pump may be re-engaged for the
    approach providing the relevant FAULT light on the overhead panel has extinguished.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> Y(B) ELEC PUMP LO PR(OVHT),
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Low reservoir air pressure</title>

    <para>Loss of air pressure to a hydraulic reservoir may lead to pump cavitation and hence
    fluctuating pressures. If this occurs, turn off the affected pump, and if applicable, turn off
    the PTU. Cavitation reduces with altitude, so it may be possible to reinstate the system during
    the descent.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G(Y)(B) RSVR LO AIR PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Reservoir overheat</title>

    <para>Turn off all affected pumps and if applicable, turn off the PTU. The system should be
    reinstated for the approach if it has cooled sufficiently. This is indicated by the FAULT light
    going out on the overhead panel.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G(Y)(B) RSVR OVHT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Low reservoir fluid level</title>

    <para>Turn off all affected pumps and, if applicable, turn off the PTU. The affected system is
    not recoverable. In the case of low reservoir level in the yellow system, it is possible that
    the fluid from the brake accumulator may also be lost. This usually occurs within 10 minutes of
    the initial warning. Without the brake accumulator, the parking brake is not available, so chock
    the aircraft before shutting down engine 1.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> G(Y)(B) RSVR LO LVL,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>PTU fault</title>

    <para>In flight this indicates that either the green or yellow system is low on fluid and has
    low system pressure. The PTU must be turned off to prevent overheating the supplying
    system.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> PTU FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>RAT fault</title>

    <para>Indicates that either the RAT is not fully stowed, pressure is present in the RAT stowing
    actuator or that the RAT pump is not available. No action is required.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">HYD</emphasis> RAT FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.HYD]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Ice and rain protection</title>

  <sect1>
    <title>Double AOA heat fail</title>

    <para>If two AOA probes are affected by icing, the computers may erroneously deselect the
    remaining good ADR. Switching off one of the affected ADRs leaves the system in the state
    described in <xref linkend="adr-disagree"/>.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.A-ICE, FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Single pitot probe heat or static port heat fault</title>

    <para>The ADR associated with the failed probe or port should be considered unreliable. ADR1 or
    ADR2 can be replaced with ADR3 using air data switching. If using standby instruments with ADR3
    unreliable, air data information must be monitored closely.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis
    role="underline">ANTI ICE</emphasis> CAPT(F/O)(STBY) PITOT(L(R) STAT),
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>

  <title>Multiple pitot heat failures</title>

    <para>The issue with loss of anti-ice on more than one pitot probe is that it is possible that
    the two unprotected pitot probes will ice up at the same time and provide erroneous but coherent
    data. This leads to a situation where the ADR associated with the remaining protected probe is
    locked out despite being the single correct source.</para>

    <para>Obviously, the first thing to do is to avoid icing conditions. If there is a working ADR
    connected to a protected probe, turn one of the ADRs associated with an unprotected probe
    off. This ensures that an “ADR DISAGREE” ECAM caution is triggered by significant speed
    discrepancies and ensures that the protected ADR will not be automatically deselected.</para>

    <para>If pitot heat is lost on all probes, one of the ADRs should, again, be turned off to
    ensure the “ADR DISAGREE” ECAM caution is provided. If icing is expected, turn off a second ADR
    and be ready to apply unreliable airspeed procedures (see <xref
    linkend="unreliable-airspeed"/>).</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis
    role="underline">ANTI ICE</emphasis> ALL(CAPT(F/O)+F/O(STBY)) PITOT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Single AOA or TAT heat fault</title>

    <para>No immediate operational effect.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ANTI ICE</emphasis> CAPT(F/O)(STBY) AOA(TAT),
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Probe heat computer failure</title>

    <para>If applicable, deselect the affected ADR.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ANTI ICE</emphasis> CAPT(F/O)(STBY) PROBES,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Window heat fault</title>

    <para>No immediate operational effect.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis
    role="underline">ANTI ICE</emphasis> L(R)(L+R) WINDSHIELD(WINDOW),
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Engine anti-ice valve fault</title>

    <para>If a valve fails to open when commanded, avoid icing conditions. If it fails to close when
    commanded, a thrust limit penalty applies<!-- {TODO: Check this is automatically applied by the
    relevant FADEC} -->.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis
    role="underline">ANTI ICE</emphasis> ENG 1(2) VALVE OPEN(CLSD),
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="wai-valve-open">
    <title>Wing anti-ice valve open when commanded closed</title>

    <para>In the air, just allow the failed side to be continually anti-iced and use wing anti-ice
    on the working side when required. A thrust limit penalty will apply. On the ground, isolate and
    depressurize the pneumatic system on the failed side.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">WING ANTI ICE</emphasis> L(R) VALVE OPEN,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="waa-valve-closed">
    <title>Wing anti-ice valve closed when commanded open</title>

    <para>The wing anti-ice must be turned off to avoid asymmetrically
    de-icing the wings. Avoid icing conditions. If ice accretion does occur, landing distances and
    V<subscript>app</subscript> adjustments are in QRH IFP  and speed must be maintained above the
    higher of V<subscript>LS</subscript>+10kt or Green Dot.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">WING ANTI ICE</emphasis> SYS FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE, FCOM PRO.NOR.SUP.AW]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Wing anti-ice valves fail to close after ground self-test</title>

    <para>Simply switch off the wing anti-ice with the push button. If the valves still do not
    close, see <xref linkend="wai-valve-open"/>.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">ANTI ICE</emphasis> OPEN ON GND,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>High pressure detected when wing anti-ice turned on</title>

    <para>A thrust limit penalty is applied automatically. <!-- {TODO: Check that this is automatic}
    --></para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">WING ANTI ICE</emphasis> L(R) HI PR,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.A-ICE]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Indicating/ Recording</title>

  <sect1 id="du-failure">
    <title>Display unit failure</title>

    <para>Intermittent flashing of DUs may be indicative of a generator issue. If P1 DUs are
    flashing, try turning off generator 1. If P2 DUs are flashing, try turning off generator 2. The
    APU generator can be used if successful.</para>

    <para>In the case of a blank DU, a large amber “F”, a distorted display or minimum brightness,
    on some airframes a reset may be attempted by selecting the DU brightness to OFF then back to
    ON. If the reset is not applicable or the DU does not recover after 10 seconds, the affected DU
    can be turned off. In the case of an INVALID DISPLAY UNIT message, an automatic recovery attempt
    is initiated; this can take 40 seconds or more. If automatic recovery does not succeed, the DU
    can be turned off.</para>

    <para>An INVALID DATA message is indicative of a DMC problem; EIS DMC switching may recover the
    DU, as may turning the DU OFF then ON. It is possible that this message will appear
    simultaneously on <emphasis>all</emphasis> DUs; this initiates an automatic recovery attempt,
    which, again, can take 40 seconds or more. DUs that are not automatically recovered may be
    recovered manually by sequentially turning them off for 40 seconds then back on. If resetting a
    DU triggers a recurrence of the original problem, leave that DU off for the next recovery
    cycle.</para>

    <para>In the event of an unrecoverable failure of a display unit, some automatic display
    switching will occur: PFD will auto-transfer to NDUs and E/WD will auto-transfer to SDU. Each
    pilot has a PFD/ND XFR button that allows their PFD to be toggled onto their NDU and their ND to
    be toggled onto their PFDU. An ECAM/ND XFR switch on the switching panel allows either the SD
    (when SDU <emphasis role="bold">xor</emphasis> E/WDU failed) or E/WD (SDU <emphasis
    role="bold">and</emphasis> E/WDU failed) to be displayed on an NDU.</para>

    <para>The most likely end result of a DU failure is that one ND must be shared and/or that the
    SD is not displayed. The ECAM can be operated with just the E/WD. When a SYS page is needed,
    press and hold the required SYS page button. When STATUS is required, press and maintain the STS
    key. The E/WD will be displayed 2s after the STS key is released. To access STATUS overflow,
    release then repress the STS key within 2s.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.EIS, FCOM PRO.AEP.EIS]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="multiple-undue">
    <title>Multiple spurious ECAM alerts</title>

    <para>A faulty DMC can cause multiple spurious ECAM alerts (spurious as confirmed by SD
    pages). The EIS DMC switch should be used to identify the faulty DMC and replace it with
    DMC3.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[QRH AEP.FWS, FCOM PRO.AEP.FWS]</para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="fwc">
    <title>Flight Warning Computer failure</title>

    <para> The two identical FWCs generate alert messages, memos, aural alerts, and synthetic voice
    messages. Loss of a single FWC leads to downgrade to CAT 3 Single due to loss of redundancy. The
    major effects of loss of both FWCs are loss of ECAM (including attention getters, status page
    and takeoff/landing memos), loss of auto callouts<footnote><para>There is some question as to
    whether windshear and GPWS aural alerts are included under ‘auto callouts’. The FCOM is unclear
    on the matter.</para></footnote> (radio height and decision height) and loss of altitude
    alerting. In the sim, there is also loss of rudder trim reset, loss of APU fuel valve status and
    loss of cabin crew call alert as side-effects.</para>

    <para>The procedure is simply to use the SYS pages and overhead panel warning lights to monitor
    the systems, and for PM to make the relevant callouts. Alternative method for cabin crew to get
    flight deck attention may be required.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">FWS</emphasis> FWC 1(2)(1+2) FAULT,
    FCOM PRO.AEP.FWS]</para>

  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Pneumatic</title>

  <sect1 id="dual-bleed">
    <title>Dual bleed failure</title>

    <para>The historical failure case where supplying two packs from one bleed would overload it and
    cause it to fail appears to have been resolved. Furthermore, recent airframes have four new ECAM
    procedures associated with dual bleed failure, the variants based on whether neither, either or
    both bleeds have failed due to a wing or pylon leak on its respective side. The ECAMs all hand
    off to a new QRH paper procedure if no successful reset is achieved. Older airframes make do
    with just the QRH procedure.</para>

    <para>Whilst the procedures look complex, the underlying philosophy is fairly simple:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>A depressurisation will be underway. It should be relatively slow, but unless
      a successful reset is achieved immediately, a prompt descent to FL100/MFA needs to be
      initiated.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>A bleed lost to a wing or pylon leak is lost for good, whereas a simple bleed
      fault or bleed low pressure may be recoverable. The cross bleed should be shut and the wing
      anti-ice should be off before an attempt is made to recover a bleed.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>A leak on the left side precludes the use of the APU bleed for pressurisation,
      but otherwise the APU bleed can be used to supply pack 1 when below 22500ft. If pack 1 is
      unavailable, the APU bleed can supply pack 2 via the cross bleed provided the whole pneumatic
      system is available.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para>In line with this philosophy, both the ECAM and QRH procedures start by shutting the cross
    bleed and turning off the wing anti-ice. The ECAM procedures each then attempt an immediate
    recovery of any recoverable bleed by cycling the bleed off then on. The QRH attempts an
    immediate recovery only in the case that both bleeds are potentially recoverable.</para>

    <para>If no bleeds are recovered, the bleeds are all turned off and a descent to FL100/MFA is
    initiated. At this point, the ECAM procedures join the QRH procedure.</para>

    <para>During the descent the APU is started. If the left hand side of the pneumatic system is
    available, at attempt to use the APU bleed for pressurisation is made at FL200. If this is
    successful, the descent is stopped at FL200 and a further attempt is made to reset the engine
    bleeds; if unsuccessful, the flight can be continued at FL200 using the APU bleed for
    pressurisation.</para>

    <para>If APU cannot be used for pressurisation descent must be continued. When level at
    FL100/MFA, a final attempt is made to restore any available engine bleeds. If unsuccessful, the
    flight is completed with ram air.</para>

    <para role="multicite">[<emphasis role="underline">AIR</emphasis> 1+2 BLEED FAULT (LEFT(RIGHT)
    LEAK (AND RIGHT LEAK)) QRH AEP.AIR, FCOM PRO.AEP.AIR]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter>
  <title>Communications</title>

  <sect1 id="com-failure-icao">
    <title>Communication failure (ICAO)</title>

    <para>If all attempts to establish contact fail, transmit message twice on designated channel,
    proceeded by the phrase “Transmitting Blind.”</para>

    <para>Set Mode A Transponder Code to 7600.</para>

    <para>If in VMC, continue in VMC to the nearest suitable airfield and land, reporting arrival to
    appropriate ATS by the most expeditious means.</para>

    <para>If in IMC or unlikely to be able to maintain VMC:

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>If in airspace where a <emphasis>procedural</emphasis> separation service is
      being applied, maintain speed and level, or minimum flight altitude if higher, for a period of
      <emphasis>20 minutes</emphasis> following failure to report over a compulsory reporting point,
      then adjust level and speed in accordance with flight plan.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If in airspace where an ATS surveillance system is in use, maintain speed and
      level, or minimum flight altitude if higher, for <emphasis>7 minutes</emphasis> after Code
      7600 is set, then adjust level and speed in accordance with flight plan.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If being radar vectored or having been directed to proceed offset using RNAV
      without specified limit, rejoin the flight plan route no later than the next significant
      point.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>On reaching the appropriate NAVAID or fix serving the destination aerodrome,
      hold if necessary, then at EAT, or if no EAT has been received and acknowledged, computed
      flight plan ETA, commence an appropriate instrument approach procedure. If possible land
      within 30 minutes of this time.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Watch for visual signals from the tower:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Red Pyro: Permission to land cancelled</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Flashing Red Light: Land elsewhere</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Continuous Red: Give way to other aircraft, continue
        circling</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Flashing Green: Return to circuit, await landing clearance</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Continuous Green: Permission to land</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  </sect1>


  <sect1 id="com-failure-uk">
    <title>Communication failure (UK airspace)</title>

    <para>The UK procedures expand on the ICAO procedures:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>If following a SID fly the published lateral and vertical profiles, including
      any step climb, until the last waypoint of the procedure is reached. Maintain current speed
      and last assigned level (or minimum flight altitude if this is higher) until <emphasis>7
      minutes</emphasis> have elapsed since setting 7600. Then adjust speed and level in accordance
      with current flight plan. This procedure also applies to RNP-1 (PRNAV)
      departures.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If following a STAR, follow the lateral profile but maintain current speed and
      last assigned level (or minimum flight altitude if this is higher) until <emphasis>7
      minutes</emphasis> have elapsed since setting 7600. Subsequently, arrange descent to be as
      close as possible to published planning profile. If no profile is published, arrange to be at
      the IAF at minimum published level. This procedure also applies to RNP-1 (PRNAV)
      arrivals.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If under radar vectors from Approach Control Radar, comply with instructions
      on radar vectoring chart. If under radar vectors without specified limit from other ATS unit,
      continue in accordance with last instructions until <emphasis>3 minutes</emphasis> have
      elapsed since setting 7600, then proceed in most direct manner to rejoin current flight plan
      route. If necessary, climb to minimum flight altitude.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If performing an SRA, continue visually or by using an alternate approach
      aid. If this is not possible, carry out a missed approach and continue to the holding position
      of a suitable aerodrome with a notified instrument approach and carry out that
      procedure.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>

    <para role="multicite">[ICAO Annex 10, ICAO DOC 4444, UKAIP ENR 1.1.3.4]</para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>


<chapter id="misc-tips">
  <title>Miscellaneous Tips</title>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>When configuring, V<subscript>LS</subscript> is more critical than
    V<subscript>FE</subscript>, which in turn is more critical than manoeuvring speeds (S and F
    speeds). Both V<subscript>LS</subscript> and V<subscript>FE</subscript> are trustworthy with
    jammed flaps/slats.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>When configuring on approach, flaps do not begin to extend until CONF 2 is
    selected.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Slat position does not change between CONF 2 and CONF 3.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>The AVIONICS SMOKE ECAM is non-standard. Do not run the procedure from the ECAM,
    use the QRH procedure instead.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>The Engine Fire on the Ground procedure is non-standard. The FO must remember to
    mitigate the effects of loss of electrical power (which includes loss of ECAM and non-emergency
    lighting) before shutting down the second engine.</para></listitem>

    <listitem><para>Dual hydraulic failure fundamentals:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>You will always need to gravity extend the gear, so you will never be able to
      retract it on the go-around.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If you only have blue, you lose the flaps; if you only have yellow, you lose
      the slats. The flaps/slats jammed procedure (including go-around modifications) is therefore
      incorporated into both these procedures.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If you only have blue, the THS is frozen (think BLUE=COLD=FROZEN THS), so you
      need to go Direct Law late (at Conf 3, V<subscript>APP</subscript>) to get neutral trimming of
      the elevators. If you only have yellow, you only have one elevator (think
      YELLOW=COWARDLY=Timid control response); combined with lack of slats this requires going
      Direct Law early (at 200kt) to improve pitch response.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>You're going to need a longish runway. Worst case is if you only have blue,
      since you have, at best, accumulator braking and you're coming in fast due to lack of
      flaps. Yellow is better since you have alternate braking, and its mainly about the lack of
      slats. If you have green, its not really all that bad.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
  </listitem></itemizedlist>
</chapter>

</book>
