<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "file:///usr/share/sgml/docbook/xml-dtd-4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article id="airbus-nonnormal">
  <title>Airbus Non-Normal Notes</title>
    <sect1>
      <title>Miscellaneous</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine failure after V1</title>

        <para>Apply rudder conventionally on the runway. When airborne, adjust rudder to maintain &beta;
        target. Autopilot can be engaged once gear is up. Consider the use of TOGA if a FLX takeoff was carried
        out. Initiate ECAM actions at 400ft AGL. Delay acceleration past acceleration altitude if the engine is not yet
        secure (e.g. master switch turned off or the first fire bottle discharged). To accelerate, push V/S to level
        off. Managed target speed will jump to initial climb speed. Accelerate to either S speed if an immediate visual
        return is expected or green dot speed if transiting, then set MCT (will require selecting CL then MCT for FLX
        takeoff) and continue climb in OP CLIMB.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Immediate VMC recovery with single engine</title>
        <para>Fly circuit in CONF 1. Select CONF 2 at start of base turn. Gear will usually be extended once flaps have
        run to 2, but may be delayed until final approach if performance is an issue. Select CONF 3 once gear is down
        and CONF full when on final approach. {TODO: Check how climb gradient/ flap decision is determined.}</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine failure in cruise</title>
        <para>Set MCT on live engine then disconnect the autothrust. Start ECAM actions and notify ATC. Decide on
        strategy - standard strategy increases the chance of an engine relight, whilst obstacle strategy maintains the
        greatest possible obstacle clearance. If using standard strategy select speed .78/300kt. If using obstacle
        strategy select green dot speed. Select altitude to LRC ceiling or green dot ceiling as appropriate to allow
        drift down once speed is reached. If obstacles remain a problem, MCT and green dot speed can be maintained to
        give a shallow climbing profile. Once obstacles are no longer a problem, descend to LRC ceiling (use V/S if
        &lt;500 fpm descent rate), engage the autothrust and continue at LRC speed.
        </para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Single engine circling</title>
        <para>It may not be possible to fly level in the standard circling configuration of CONF 3 gear down. This can
        be ascertained by checking the table in Vol 3. Gear extension may be delayed until final approach if
        required.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Emergency descent</title>
        <para>Don oxygen masks, set them to the N position and establish communication. Descent with autopilot engaged
        is preferred. The configuration is thrust idle, full speed brake and maximum appropriate speed, taking into
        account possible structural damage. Target altitude is FL100 or MORA if this is higher. If speed is low, allow
        speed to increase before deploying full speedbrake to prevent activation of the angle of attack
        protection. Landing gear may be used below 25,000ft, but speed must be below V<subscript>LE</subscript> when it
        is extended and remain below V<subscript>LO</subscript>.</para>

        <para>Once descent is established, check the cabin altitude and manually deploy passenger oxygen if it is
        &gt;14,000ft. The passenger signs should be turned on, the ignitors should be turned on and ATC should be
        notified.</para>
        
        <para>Once level, restore the aircraft to a Normal configuration. When safe to do so, advise cabin crew and
        passengers that it is safe to remove their masks.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Smoke</title>
        <para>Smoke procedures are detailed on p1.08 of the QRH. Smoke removal procedures are detailed on p1.07 of the
        QRH. </para>
        <para>Immediate actions are to don oxygen masks and establish communication, then isolate the more likely
        sources by turning off the cabin fans, putting the avionics ventilation system into smoke removal configuration
        (OVRD on both BLOWER and EXTRACT) and shedding the galley and cabin electrics. The cabin signs should then be
        turned on. The origin of the smoke should be identified, possibly requiring communication with the cabin, and if
        successful, the faulty equipment should be isolated.</para>
        <para>If smoke becomes excessively dense at any time during the procedure, turn on the emergency exit lights and
        apply the smoke removal procedure. Also consider adopting the emergency electrical configuration.</para>
        <para>The eventual aim of the smoke removal procedure is depressurisation and the use of ram air. During the
        descent, the outflow valve is opened by setting the landing elevation to 10,000ft. If the packs are suspected as
        a smoke source (indicated by fuel vapors), they are turned off and the cabin fans are turned off. Otherwise, the
        air conditioning is used to provide air flow during the descent phase by setting the pack flow to HIGH and
        turning off the cabin fans. As a final resort, once below 200kt and depressurised, the cockpit windows can be
        opened.</para>
        
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Bomb on board</title>
        <para>The primary aim is to get the aircraft on the ground and evacuated ASAP.</para>

        <para>The secondary aim is to prevent detonation of the device. This is acheived by preventing further increases
        in cabin altitude through the use of manual pressure control and by avoiding sharp maneuvres and
        turbulence.</para>

        <para>The tertiary aim is to minimise the effect of any explosion, This is acheived by reducing the diff to 1
        psi, by descending to a level 2500ft above cabin altitude, and by flying at suitable speeds. As further descent
        is required, the manual controls should be used to maintain the 1 psi diff for as long as possible. The aircraft
        should be configured for landing as early as possible to avoid an explosion damaging landing systems.</para>

        <para>In the cabin, procedures are laid down for assessing the risks of moving the device and for moving the
        device to the LRBL at door 2R.</para> 

      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Electrical</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Generator fault</title>
        <para>Try to reset the generator by turning it off, then after a short pause, turning it on again. If
        unsuccessful, turn it back off.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>AC Bus 1 fault</title>
        <para>All equipment on AC bus 1 becomes unavailable, including TR1. DC Bus 2 is powered from DC Bus 1 via the
        battery bus, the Essential AC bus is powered by AC bus 2 and the Essential TR powers the DC Essential
        bus.</para>
        <para>Notable lost equipment includes the blue hydraulic system and associated services (including spoiler 3),
        radio altimeter 1 (and hence Cat III capability), half the fuel pumps, the nose wheel steering, the avionics
        blower fan and p1 windshield heat. Landing distance will increase by 10%.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>IDG low pressure or overheat</title>
        <para>The affected IDG must be disconnected. This is done by pressing the guarded IDG button until the FAULT
        light comes on on the associated generator button. The button should be held down for a maximum of three
        seconds. The unaffected generator will power the associated AC bus, with the galley being shed.</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>Emergency configuration</title>
        <para>Attempt to restore normal power by recycling the main generators. If that fails, try again after splitting
        the systems. Start the APU once at least 45 seconds has elapsed since loss of main generators.</para>
        <para>If normal power cannot be restored, ensure that the emergency generator is on line, deploying the RAT
        manually if required and maintain speed &gt;140kt to avoid RAT stall. So much equipment is lost in the emergency
        configuration that a table is provided in the QRH for surviving equipment. Notable losses are all the fuel pumps
        (so ignition on, avoid negative G, centre tank fuel is unusable), the anti-skid and three fifths of the
        spoilers. Landing speeds and distances are increased.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Flight controls</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Landing with slats or flaps jammed</title>
        <para>The selected landing configuration should be CONF 3. If the slats are jammed, the flaps will still move
        and vice versa. Therefore V<subscript>FE</subscript> (barbers pole with CONF&gt;0) and V<subscript>FE
        next</subscript>, which are a function of flap lever position, must be honored during
        configuration. V<subscript>LS</subscript> is computed according to actual configuration. It is possible that
        V<subscript>LS</subscript>&gt;V<subscript>FE next</subscript>. If this occurs, speed should be reduced below
        V<subscript>LS</subscript> as the surfaces extend. This will require temporary disconnection of the
        autothrust. Use of managed speed is not recommended during configuration.</para>
        <para>The autopilot may be used down to 500ft AAL, but since it is not tuned for the abnormal configuration it
        must be closely monitored.</para>
        <para>For the go-around, initially maintain flap/ slat configuration. Maximum speeds are available on page 2.05
        of the QRH, and in general a speed 10kt lower than max speed should be flown. If it is the slats that are jammed
        or if the flaps are jammed at 0, clean configuration can be used to transit to a diversion airfield.</para>
        <para>Diversion with flaps and/or slats extended may as much as double fuel consumption. The centre tank pumps
        will have to be manually controlled to access the fuel if slats are extended.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Fire</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Engine fire</title>
        <para>The basic sequence is to bring the thrust lever of the affected engine to idle, turn off its engine
        master, push its fire button, wait 10 seconds then deploy its first fire bottle. If the fire is not extinguished
        after 30 seconds, indicated by the fire button remaining lit, deploy the second bottle. This sequence is
        modified on the ground in that both fire bottles are fired immediately, and the remaining engine is then also
        shut down.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Landing gear</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Gear not downlocked</title>
        <para>If the gear has not downlocked, retract the gear and wait until it has fully stowed, then redeploy. If
        this is not successful, attempt to deploy the gear by gravity using page 2.11 of the QRH .</para>
      </sect2>
      <sect2>
        <title>RA fault</title>
        <para>A single RA fault results in degradation of approach capability to Cat II. Loss of both RAs will lead to
        direct law at landing gear extension and a loss of ILS APPR mode capability (so fly in LOC and FPA).</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
      <title>Power plant</title>
      <sect2>
        <title>Dual engine failure</title>
        <para>It is recommended that the QRH paper procedure on page 1.16 is used rather than the ECAM.</para>
        <para>First priority, assuming fuel remains, is to attempt a relight. The FADECs will do this automatically, but
        to improve the chances of a relight speed should initially be increased to 300kt. At this speed, the aircraft
        will cover approximately 2nm for every 1000ft lost. With this in mind, a suitable plan should be constructed to
        cover the possibility that relight is not possible.</para>
        <para>If there has been no relight after 30 seconds, the engine masters should be turned off for 30 seconds,
        then back on. This can be repeated until successful.</para>
        <para>Once below FL250, the APU can be started and then once below FL200, assisted starts can be
        attempted. Once the APU bleed is available, speed should be reduced to green dot. At this speed, 2½nm will be
        covered for every 1000ft lost.</para>
        <para>If a landing must be made without power, flaps and slats are available from blue hydraulics. CONF 3 is
        recommended. The gear is available through gravity extension. Minimum speed is V<subscript>ref</subscript>+25kt
        or 150kt, whichever is higher. Accumulator braking will be available. If ditching is required, the recommended
        configuration is CONF 3 gear up.</para>
      </sect2>
    </sect1>
</article>

